Proverbs 12

1 Whoever loves correction loves knowledge,

but he who hates reproof is stupid.

2 A good man shall obtain favor from Yahweh,

but he will condemn a man of wicked devices.

3 A man shall not be established by wickedness,

but the root of the righteous shall not be moved.

4 A worthy woman is the crown of her husband,

but a disgraceful wife is as rottenness in his bones.

5 The thoughts of the righteous are just,

but the advice of the wicked is deceitful.

6 The words of the wicked are about lying in wait for blood,

but the speech of the upright rescues them.

7 The wicked are overthrown, and are no more,

but the house of the righteous shall stand.

8 A man shall be commended according to his wisdom,

but he who has a warped mind shall be despised.

9 Better is he who is lightly esteemed, and has a servant,

than he who honors himself, and lacks bread.

10 A righteous man respects the life of his animal,

but the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.

11 He who tills his land shall have plenty of bread,

but he who chases fantasies is void of understanding.

12 The wicked desires the plunder of evil men,

but the root of the righteous flourishes.

13 An evil man is trapped by sinfulness of lips,

but the righteous shall come out of trouble.

14 A man shall be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth.

The work of a man’s hands shall be rewarded to him.

15 The way of a fool is right in his own eyes,

but he who is wise listens to counsel.

16 A fool shows his annoyance the same day,

but one who overlooks an insult is prudent.

17 He who is truthful testifies honestly,

but a false witness lies.

18 There is one who speaks rashly like the piercing of a sword,

but the tongue of the wise heals.

19 Truth’s lips will be established forever,

but a lying tongue is only momentary.

20 Deceit is in the heart of those who plot evil,

but joy comes to the promoters of peace.

21 No mischief shall happen to the righteous,

but the wicked shall be filled with evil.

22 Lying lips are an abomination to Yahweh,

but those who do the truth are his delight.

23 A prudent man keeps his knowledge,

but the hearts of fools proclaim foolishness.

24 The hands of the diligent ones shall rule,

but laziness ends in slave labor.

25 Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,

but a kind word makes it glad.

26 A righteous person is cautious in friendship,

but the way of the wicked leads them astray.

27 The slothful man doesn’t roast his game,

but the possessions of diligent men are prized.

28 In the way of righteousness is life;

in its path there is no death.

Proverbs 13

1 A wise son listens to his father’s instruction,

but a scoffer doesn’t listen to rebuke.

2 By the fruit of his lips, a man enjoys good things;

but the unfaithful crave violence.

3 He who guards his mouth guards his soul.

One who opens wide his lips comes to ruin.

4 The soul of the sluggard desires, and has nothing,

but the desire of the diligent shall be fully satisfied.

5 A righteous man hates lies,

but a wicked man brings shame and disgrace.

6 Righteousness guards the way of integrity,

but wickedness overthrows the sinner.

7 There are some who pretend to be rich, yet have nothing.

There are some who pretend to be poor, yet have great wealth.

8 The ransom of a man’s life is his riches,

but the poor hear no threats.

9 The light of the righteous shines brightly,

but the lamp of the wicked is snuffed out.

10 Pride only breeds quarrels,

but with ones who take advice is wisdom.

11 Wealth gained dishonestly dwindles away,

but he who gathers by hand makes it grow.

12 Hope deferred makes the heart sick,

but when longing is fulfilled, it is a tree of life.

13 Whoever despises instruction will pay for it,

but he who respects a command will be rewarded.

14 The teaching of the wise is a spring of life,

to turn from the snares of death.

15 Good understanding wins favor;

but the way of the unfaithful is hard.

16 Every prudent man acts from knowledge,

but a fool exposes folly.

17 A wicked messenger falls into trouble,

but a trustworthy envoy gains healing.

18 Poverty and shame come to him who refuses discipline,

but he who heeds correction shall be honored.

19 Longing fulfilled is sweet to the soul,

but fools detest turning from evil.

20 One who walks with wise men grows wise,

but a companion of fools suffers harm.

21 Misfortune pursues sinners,

but prosperity rewards the righteous.

22 A good man leaves an inheritance to his children’s children,

but the wealth of the sinner is stored for the righteous.

23 An abundance of food is in poor people’s fields,

but injustice sweeps it away.

24 One who spares the rod hates his son,

but one who loves him is careful to discipline him.

25 The righteous one eats to the satisfying of his soul,

but the belly of the wicked goes hungry.

Proverbs 14

1 Every wise woman builds her house,

but the foolish one tears it down with her own hands.

2 He who walks in his uprightness fears Yahweh,

but he who is perverse in his ways despises him.

3 The fool’s talk brings a rod to his back,

but the lips of the wise protect them.

4 Where no oxen are, the crib is clean,

but much increase is by the strength of the ox.

5 A truthful witness will not lie,

but a false witness pours out lies.

6 A scoffer seeks wisdom, and doesn’t find it,

but knowledge comes easily to a discerning person.

7 Stay away from a foolish man,

for you won’t find knowledge on his lips.

8 The wisdom of the prudent is to think about his way,

but the folly of fools is deceit.

9 Fools mock at making atonement for sins,

but among the upright there is good will.

10 The heart knows its own bitterness and joy;

he will not share these with a stranger.

11 The house of the wicked will be overthrown,

but the tent of the upright will flourish.

12 There is a way which seems right to a man,

but in the end it leads to death.

13 Even in laughter the heart may be sorrowful,

and mirth may end in heaviness.

14 The unfaithful will be repaid for his own ways;

likewise a good man will be rewarded for his ways.

15 A simple man believes everything,

but the prudent man carefully considers his ways.

16 A wise man fears and shuns evil,

but the fool is hot headed and reckless.

17 He who is quick to become angry will commit folly,

and a crafty man is hated.

18 The simple inherit folly,

but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.

19 The evil bow down before the good,

and the wicked at the gates of the righteous.

20 The poor person is shunned even by his own neighbor,

but the rich person has many friends.

21 He who despises his neighbor sins,

but blessed is he who has pity on the poor.

22 Don’t they go astray who plot evil?

But love and faithfulness belong to those who plan good.

23 In all hard work there is profit,

but the talk of the lips leads only to poverty.

24 The crown of the wise is their riches,

but the folly of fools crowns them with folly.

25 A truthful witness saves souls,

but a false witness is deceitful.

26 In the fear of Yahweh is a secure fortress,

and he will be a refuge for his children.

27 The fear of Yahweh is a fountain of life,

turning people from the snares of death.

28 In the multitude of people is the king’s glory,

but in the lack of people is the destruction of the prince.

29 He who is slow to anger has great understanding,

but he who has a quick temper displays folly.

30 The life of the body is a heart at peace,

but envy rots the bones.

31 He who oppresses the poor shows contempt for his Maker,

but he who is kind to the needy honors him.

32 The wicked is brought down in his calamity,

but in death, the righteous has a refuge.

33 Wisdom rests in the heart of one who has understanding,

and is even made known in the inward part of fools.

34 Righteousness exalts a nation,

but sin is a disgrace to any people.

35 The king’s favor is toward a servant who deals wisely,

but his wrath is toward one who causes shame.

Proverbs 15

1 A gentle answer turns away wrath,

but a harsh word stirs up anger.

2 The tongue of the wise commends knowledge,

but the mouth of fools gush out folly.

3 Yahweh’s eyes are everywhere,

keeping watch on the evil and the good.

4 A gentle tongue is a tree of life,

but deceit in it crushes the spirit.

5 A fool despises his father’s correction,

but he who heeds reproof shows prudence.

6 In the house of the righteous is much treasure,

but the income of the wicked brings trouble.

7 The lips of the wise spread knowledge;

not so with the heart of fools.

8 The sacrifice made by the wicked is an abomination to Yahweh,

but the prayer of the upright is his delight.

9 The way of the wicked is an abomination to Yahweh,

but he loves him who follows after righteousness.

10 There is stern discipline for one who forsakes the way:

whoever hates reproof shall die.

11 Sheol[*] and Abaddon are before Yahweh—

how much more then the hearts of the children of men!

12 A scoffer doesn’t love to be reproved;

he will not go to the wise.

13 A glad heart makes a cheerful face;

but an aching heart breaks the spirit.

14 The heart of one who has understanding seeks knowledge,

but the mouths of fools feed on folly.

15 All the days of the afflicted are wretched,

but one who has a cheerful heart enjoys a continual feast.

16 Better is little, with the fear of Yahweh,

than great treasure with trouble.

17 Better is a dinner of herbs, where love is,

than a fattened calf with hatred.

18 A wrathful man stirs up contention,

but one who is slow to anger appeases strife.

19 The way of the sluggard is like a thorn patch,

but the path of the upright is a highway.

20 A wise son makes a father glad,

but a foolish man despises his mother.

21 Folly is joy to one who is void of wisdom,

but a man of understanding keeps his way straight.

22 Where there is no counsel, plans fail;

but in a multitude of counselors they are established.

23 Joy comes to a man with the reply of his mouth.

How good is a word at the right time!

24 The path of life leads upward for the wise,

to keep him from going downward to Sheol.[*]

25 Yahweh will uproot the house of the proud,

but he will keep the widow’s borders intact.

26 Yahweh detests the thoughts of the wicked,

but the thoughts of the pure are pleasing.

27 He who is greedy for gain troubles his own house,

but he who hates bribes will live.

28 The heart of the righteous weighs answers,

but the mouth of the wicked gushes out evil.

29 Yahweh is far from the wicked,

but he hears the prayer of the righteous.

30 The light of the eyes rejoices the heart.

Good news gives health to the bones.

31 The ear that listens to reproof lives,

and will be at home among the wise.

32 He who refuses correction despises his own soul,

but he who listens to reproof gets understanding.

33 The fear of Yahweh teaches wisdom.

Before honor is humility.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 16

1 The plans of the heart belong to man,

but the answer of the tongue is from Yahweh.

2 All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes;

but Yahweh weighs the motives.

3 Commit your deeds to Yahweh,

and your plans shall succeed.

4 Yahweh has made everything for its own end—

yes, even the wicked for the day of evil.

5 Everyone who is proud in heart is an abomination to Yahweh:

they shall certainly not be unpunished.

6 By mercy and truth iniquity is atoned for.

By the fear of Yahweh men depart from evil.

7 When a man’s ways please Yahweh,

he makes even his enemies to be at peace with him.

8 Better is a little with righteousness,

than great revenues with injustice.

9 A man’s heart plans his course,

but Yahweh directs his steps.

10 Inspired judgments are on the lips of the king.

He shall not betray his mouth.

11 Honest balances and scales are Yahweh’s;

all the weights in the bag are his work.

12 It is an abomination for kings to do wrong,

for the throne is established by righteousness.

13 Righteous lips are the delight of kings.

They value one who speaks the truth.

14 The king’s wrath is a messenger of death,

but a wise man will pacify it.

15 In the light of the king’s face is life.

His favor is like a cloud of the spring rain.

16 How much better it is to get wisdom than gold!

Yes, to get understanding is to be chosen rather than silver.

17 The highway of the upright is to depart from evil.

He who keeps his way preserves his soul.

18 Pride goes before destruction,

and a haughty spirit before a fall.

19 It is better to be of a lowly spirit with the poor,

than to divide the plunder with the proud.

20 He who heeds the Word finds prosperity.

Whoever trusts in Yahweh is blessed.

21 The wise in heart shall be called prudent.

Pleasantness of the lips promotes instruction.

22 Understanding is a fountain of life to one who has it,

but the punishment of fools is their folly.

23 The heart of the wise instructs his mouth,

and adds learning to his lips.

24 Pleasant words are a honeycomb,

sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.

25 There is a way which seems right to a man,

but in the end it leads to death.

26 The appetite of the laboring man labors for him;

for his mouth urges him on.

27 A worthless man devises mischief.

His speech is like a scorching fire.

28 A perverse man stirs up strife.

A whisperer separates close friends.

29 A man of violence entices his neighbor,

and leads him in a way that is not good.

30 One who winks his eyes to plot perversities,

one who compresses his lips, is bent on evil.

31 Gray hair is a crown of glory.

It is attained by a life of righteousness.

32 One who is slow to anger is better than the mighty;

one who rules his spirit, than he who takes a city.

33 The lot is cast into the lap,

but its every decision is from Yahweh.

Proverbs 17

1 Better is a dry morsel with quietness,

than a house full of feasting with strife.

2 A servant who deals wisely will rule over a son who causes shame,

and shall have a part in the inheritance among the brothers.

3 The refining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold,

but Yahweh tests the hearts.

4 An evildoer heeds wicked lips.

A liar gives ear to a mischievous tongue.

5 Whoever mocks the poor reproaches his Maker.

He who is glad at calamity shall not be unpunished.

6 Children’s children are the crown of old men;

the glory of children are their parents.

7 Arrogant speech isn’t fitting for a fool,

much less do lying lips fit a prince.

8 A bribe is a precious stone in the eyes of him who gives it;

wherever he turns, he prospers.

9 He who covers an offense promotes love;

but he who repeats a matter separates best friends.

10 A rebuke enters deeper into one who has understanding

than a hundred lashes into a fool.

11 An evil man seeks only rebellion;

therefore a cruel messenger shall be sent against him.

12 Let a bear robbed of her cubs meet a man,

rather than a fool in his folly.

13 Whoever rewards evil for good,

evil shall not depart from his house.

14 The beginning of strife is like breaching a dam,

therefore stop contention before quarreling breaks out.

15 He who justifies the wicked, and he who condemns the righteous,

both of them alike are an abomination to Yahweh.

16 Why is there money in the hand of a fool to buy wisdom,

since he has no understanding?

17 A friend loves at all times;

and a brother is born for adversity.

18 A man void of understanding strikes hands,

and becomes collateral in the presence of his neighbor.

19 He who loves disobedience loves strife.

One who builds a high gate seeks destruction.

20 One who has a perverse heart doesn’t find prosperity,

and one who has a deceitful tongue falls into trouble.

21 He who becomes the father of a fool grieves.

The father of a fool has no joy.

22 A cheerful heart makes good medicine,

but a crushed spirit dries up the bones.

23 A wicked man receives a bribe in secret,

to pervert the ways of justice.

24 Wisdom is before the face of one who has understanding,

but the eyes of a fool wander to the ends of the earth.

25 A foolish son brings grief to his father,

and bitterness to her who bore him.

26 Also to punish the righteous is not good,

nor to flog officials for their integrity.

27 He who spares his words has knowledge.

He who is even tempered is a man of understanding.

28 Even a fool, when he keeps silent, is counted wise.

When he shuts his lips, he is thought to be discerning.

Proverbs 18

1 An unfriendly man pursues selfishness,

and defies all sound judgment.

2 A fool has no delight in understanding,

but only in revealing his own opinion.

3 When wickedness comes, contempt also comes,

and with shame comes disgrace.

4 The words of a man’s mouth are like deep waters.

The fountain of wisdom is like a flowing brook.

5 To be partial to the faces of the wicked is not good,

nor to deprive the innocent of justice.

6 A fool’s lips come into strife,

and his mouth invites beatings.

7 A fool’s mouth is his destruction,

and his lips are a snare to his soul.

8 The words of a gossip are like dainty morsels:

they go down into a person’s innermost parts.

9 One who is slack in his work

is brother to him who is a master of destruction.

10 Yahweh’s name is a strong tower:

the righteous run to him, and are safe.

11 The rich man’s wealth is his strong city,

like an unscalable wall in his own imagination.

12 Before destruction the heart of man is proud,

but before honor is humility.

13 He who gives answer before he hears,

that is folly and shame to him.

14 A man’s spirit will sustain him in sickness,

but a crushed spirit, who can bear?

15 The heart of the discerning gets knowledge.

The ear of the wise seeks knowledge.

16 A man’s gift makes room for him,

and brings him before great men.

17 He who pleads his cause first seems right;

until another comes and questions him.

18 The lot settles disputes,

and keeps strong ones apart.

19 A brother offended is more difficult than a fortified city;

and disputes are like the bars of a fortress.

20 A man’s stomach is filled with the fruit of his mouth.

With the harvest of his lips he is satisfied.

21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue;

those who love it will eat its fruit.

22 Whoever finds a wife finds a good thing,

and obtains favor of Yahweh.

23 The poor plead for mercy,

but the rich answer harshly.

24 A man of many companions may be ruined,

but there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.

Proverbs 19

1 Better is the poor who walks in his integrity

than he who is perverse in his lips and is a fool.

2 It isn’t good to have zeal without knowledge;

nor being hasty with one’s feet and missing the way.

3 The foolishness of man subverts his way;

his heart rages against Yahweh.

4 Wealth adds many friends,

but the poor is separated from his friend.

5 A false witness shall not be unpunished.

He who pours out lies shall not go free.

6 Many will entreat the favor of a ruler,

and everyone is a friend to a man who gives gifts.

7 All the relatives of the poor shun him:

how much more do his friends avoid him!

He pursues them with pleas, but they are gone.

8 He who gets wisdom loves his own soul.

He who keeps understanding shall find good.

9 A false witness shall not be unpunished.

He who utters lies shall perish.

10 Delicate living is not appropriate for a fool,

much less for a servant to have rule over princes.

11 The discretion of a man makes him slow to anger.

It is his glory to overlook an offense.

12 The king’s wrath is like the roaring of a lion,

but his favor is like dew on the grass.

13 A foolish son is the calamity of his father.

A wife’s quarrels are a continual dripping.

14 House and riches are an inheritance from fathers,

but a prudent wife is from Yahweh.

15 Slothfulness casts into a deep sleep.

The idle soul shall suffer hunger.

16 He who keeps the commandment keeps his soul,

but he who is contemptuous in his ways shall die.

17 He who has pity on the poor lends to Yahweh;

he will reward him.

18 Discipline your son, for there is hope;

don’t be a willing party to his death.

19 A hot-tempered man must pay the penalty,

for if you rescue him, you must do it again.

20 Listen to counsel and receive instruction,

that you may be wise in your latter end.

21 There are many plans in a man’s heart,

but Yahweh’s counsel will prevail.

22 That which makes a man to be desired is his kindness.

A poor man is better than a liar.

23 The fear of Yahweh leads to life, then contentment;

he rests and will not be touched by trouble.

24 The sluggard buries his hand in the dish;

he will not so much as bring it to his mouth again.

25 Flog a scoffer, and the simple will learn prudence;

rebuke one who has understanding, and he will gain knowledge.

26 He who robs his father and drives away his mother,

is a son who causes shame and brings reproach.

27 If you stop listening to instruction, my son,

you will stray from the words of knowledge.

28 A corrupt witness mocks justice,

and the mouth of the wicked gulps down iniquity.

29 Penalties are prepared for scoffers,

and beatings for the backs of fools.

Proverbs 20

1 Wine is a mocker, and beer is a brawler.

Whoever is led astray by them is not wise.

2 The terror of a king is like the roaring of a lion.

He who provokes him to anger forfeits his own life.

3 It is an honor for a man to keep aloof from strife;

but every fool will be quarreling.

4 The sluggard will not plow by reason of the winter;

therefore he shall beg in harvest, and have nothing.

5 Counsel in the heart of man is like deep water;

but a man of understanding will draw it out.

6 Many men claim to be men of unfailing love,

but who can find a faithful man?

7 A righteous man walks in integrity.

Blessed are his children after him.

8 A king who sits on the throne of judgment

scatters away all evil with his eyes.

9 Who can say, “I have made my heart pure.

I am clean and without sin?”

10 Differing weights and differing measures,

both of them alike are an abomination to Yahweh.

11 Even a child makes himself known by his doings,

whether his work is pure, and whether it is right.

12 The hearing ear, and the seeing eye,

Yahweh has made even both of them.

13 Don’t love sleep, lest you come to poverty.

Open your eyes, and you shall be satisfied with bread.

14 “It’s no good, it’s no good,” says the buyer;

but when he is gone his way, then he boasts.

15 There is gold and abundance of rubies;

but the lips of knowledge are a rare jewel.

16 Take the garment of one who puts up collateral for a stranger;

and hold him in pledge for a wayward woman.

17 Fraudulent food is sweet to a man,

but afterwards his mouth is filled with gravel.

18 Plans are established by advice;

by wise guidance you wage war!

19 He who goes about as a tale-bearer reveals secrets;

therefore don’t keep company with him who opens wide his lips.

20 Whoever curses his father or his mother,

his lamp shall be put out in blackness of darkness.

21 An inheritance quickly gained at the beginning,

won’t be blessed in the end.

22 Don’t say, “I will pay back evil.”

Wait for Yahweh, and he will save you.

23 Yahweh detests differing weights,

and dishonest scales are not pleasing.

24 A man’s steps are from Yahweh;

how then can man understand his way?

25 It is a snare to a man to make a rash dedication,

then later to consider his vows.

26 A wise king winnows out the wicked,

and drives the threshing wheel over them.

27 The spirit of man is Yahweh’s lamp,

searching all his innermost parts.

28 Love and faithfulness keep the king safe.

His throne is sustained by love.

29 The glory of young men is their strength.

The splendor of old men is their gray hair.

30 Wounding blows cleanse away evil,

and beatings purge the innermost parts.

Proverbs 21

1 The king’s heart is in Yahweh’s hand like the watercourses.

He turns it wherever he desires.

2 Every way of a man is right in his own eyes,

but Yahweh weighs the hearts.

3 To do righteousness and justice

is more acceptable to Yahweh than sacrifice.

4 A high look, and a proud heart,

the lamp of the wicked, is sin.

5 The plans of the diligent surely lead to profit;

and everyone who is hasty surely rushes to poverty.

6 Getting treasures by a lying tongue

is a fleeting vapor for those who seek death.

7 The violence of the wicked will drive them away,

because they refuse to do what is right.

8 The way of the guilty is devious,

but the conduct of the innocent is upright.

9 It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop,

than to share a house with a contentious woman.

10 The soul of the wicked desires evil;

his neighbor finds no mercy in his eyes.

11 When the mocker is punished, the simple gains wisdom.

When the wise is instructed, he receives knowledge.

12 The Righteous One considers the house of the wicked,

and brings the wicked to ruin.

13 Whoever stops his ears at the cry of the poor,

he will also cry out, but shall not be heard.

14 A gift in secret pacifies anger;

and a bribe in the cloak, strong wrath.

15 It is joy to the righteous to do justice;

but it is a destruction to the workers of iniquity.

16 The man who wanders out of the way of understanding

shall rest in the assembly of the departed spirits.

17 He who loves pleasure shall be a poor man.

He who loves wine and oil shall not be rich.

18 The wicked is a ransom for the righteous;

the treacherous for the upright.

19 It is better to dwell in a desert land,

than with a contentious and fretful woman.

20 There is precious treasure and oil in the dwelling of the wise;

but a foolish man swallows it up.

21 He who follows after righteousness and kindness

finds life, righteousness, and honor.

22 A wise man scales the city of the mighty,

and brings down the strength of its confidence.

23 Whoever guards his mouth and his tongue

keeps his soul from troubles.

24 The proud and haughty man, “scoffer” is his name;

he works in the arrogance of pride.

25 The desire of the sluggard kills him,

for his hands refuse to labor.

26 There are those who covet greedily all day long;

but the righteous give and don’t withhold.

27 The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination;

how much more, when he brings it with a wicked mind!

28 A false witness will perish,

and a man who listens speaks to eternity.

29 A wicked man hardens his face;

but as for the upright, he establishes his ways.

30 There is no wisdom nor understanding

nor counsel against Yahweh.

31 The horse is prepared for the day of battle;

but victory is with Yahweh.

Proverbs 22

1 A good name is more desirable than great riches,

and loving favor is better than silver and gold.

2 The rich and the poor have this in common:

Yahweh is the maker of them all.

3 A prudent man sees danger, and hides himself;

but the simple pass on, and suffer for it.

4 The result of humility and the fear of Yahweh

is wealth, honor, and life.

5 Thorns and snares are in the path of the wicked:

whoever guards his soul stays from them.

6 Train up a child in the way he should go,

and when he is old he will not depart from it.

7 The rich rule over the poor.

The borrower is servant to the lender.

8 He who sows wickedness reaps trouble,

and the rod of his fury will be destroyed.

9 He who has a generous eye will be blessed;

for he shares his food with the poor.

10 Drive out the mocker, and strife will go out;

yes, quarrels and insults will stop.

11 He who loves purity of heart and speaks gracefully

is the king’s friend.

12 Yahweh’s eyes watch over knowledge;

but he frustrates the words of the unfaithful.

13 The sluggard says, “There is a lion outside!

I will be killed in the streets!”

14 The mouth of an adulteress is a deep pit.

He who is under Yahweh’s wrath will fall into it.

15 Folly is bound up in the heart of a child:

the rod of discipline drives it far from him.

16 Whoever oppresses the poor for his own increase and whoever gives to the rich,

both come to poverty.

17 Turn your ear, and listen to the words of the wise.

Apply your heart to my teaching.

18 For it is a pleasant thing if you keep them within you,

if all of them are ready on your lips.

19 That your trust may be in Yahweh,

I teach you today, even you.

20 Haven’t I written to you thirty excellent things

of counsel and knowledge,

21 To teach you truth, reliable words,

to give sound answers to the ones who sent you?

22 Don’t exploit the poor, because he is poor;

and don’t crush the needy in court;

23 for Yahweh will plead their case,

and plunder the life of those who plunder them.

24 Don’t befriend a hot-tempered man,

and don’t associate with one who harbors anger:

25 lest you learn his ways,

and ensnare your soul.

26 Don’t you be one of those who strike hands,

of those who are collateral for debts.

27 If you don’t have means to pay,

why should he take away your bed from under you?

28 Don’t move the ancient boundary stone,

which your fathers have set up.

29 Do you see a man skilled in his work?

He will serve kings.

He won’t serve obscure men.

Proverbs 23

1 When you sit to eat with a ruler,

consider diligently what is before you;

2 put a knife to your throat,

if you are a man given to appetite.

3 Don’t be desirous of his dainties,

since they are deceitful food.

4 Don’t weary yourself to be rich.

In your wisdom, show restraint.

5 Why do you set your eyes on that which is not?

For it certainly sprouts wings like an eagle and flies in the sky.

6 Don’t eat the food of him who has a stingy eye,

and don’t crave his delicacies:

7 for as he thinks about the cost, so he is.

“Eat and drink!” he says to you,

but his heart is not with you.

8 The morsel which you have eaten you shall vomit up,

and lose your good words.

9 Don’t speak in the ears of a fool,

for he will despise the wisdom of your words.

10 Don’t move the ancient boundary stone.

Don’t encroach on the fields of the fatherless:

11 for their Defender is strong.

He will plead their case against you.

12 Apply your heart to instruction,

and your ears to the words of knowledge.

13 Don’t withhold correction from a child.

If you punish him with the rod, he will not die.

14 Punish him with the rod,

and save his soul from Sheol.[*]

15 My son, if your heart is wise,

then my heart will be glad, even mine:

16 yes, my heart will rejoice,

when your lips speak what is right.

17 Don’t let your heart envy sinners;

but rather fear Yahweh all day long.

18 Indeed surely there is a future hope,

and your hope will not be cut off.

19 Listen, my son, and be wise,

and keep your heart on the right path!

20 Don’t be among ones drinking too much wine,

or those who gorge themselves on meat:

21 for the drunkard and the glutton shall become poor;

and drowsiness clothes them in rags.

22 Listen to your father who gave you life,

and don’t despise your mother when she is old.

23 Buy the truth, and don’t sell it.

Get wisdom, discipline, and understanding.

24 The father of the righteous has great joy.

Whoever fathers a wise child delights in him.

25 Let your father and your mother be glad!

Let her who bore you rejoice!

26 My son, give me your heart;

and let your eyes keep in my ways.

27 For a prostitute is a deep pit;

and a wayward wife is a narrow well.

28 Yes, she lies in wait like a robber,

and increases the unfaithful among men.

29 Who has woe?

Who has sorrow?

Who has strife?

Who has complaints?

Who has needless bruises?

Who has bloodshot eyes?

30 Those who stay long at the wine;

those who go to seek out mixed wine.

31 Don’t look at the wine when it is red,

when it sparkles in the cup,

when it goes down smoothly.

32 In the end, it bites like a snake,

and poisons like a viper.

33 Your eyes will see strange things,

and your mind will imagine confusing things.

34 Yes, you will be as he who lies down in the middle of the sea,

or as he who lies on top of the rigging:

35 “They hit me, and I was not hurt!

They beat me, and I don’t feel it!

When will I wake up? I can do it again.

I can find another.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 24

1 Don’t be envious of evil men;

neither desire to be with them:

2 for their hearts plot violence,

and their lips talk about mischief.

3 Through wisdom a house is built;

by understanding it is established;

4 by knowledge the rooms are filled

with all rare and beautiful treasure.

5 A wise man has great power;

and a knowledgeable man increases strength;

6 for by wise guidance you wage your war;

and victory is in many advisors.

7 Wisdom is too high for a fool:

he doesn’t open his mouth in the gate.

8 One who plots to do evil

will be called a schemer.

9 The schemes of folly are sin.

The mocker is detested by men.

10 If you falter in the time of trouble,

your strength is small.

11 Rescue those who are being led away to death!

Indeed, hold back those who are staggering to the slaughter!

12 If you say, “Behold, we didn’t know this”;

doesn’t he who weighs the hearts consider it?

He who keeps your soul, doesn’t he know it?

Shall he not render to every man according to his work?

13 My son, eat honey, for it is good;

the droppings of the honeycomb, which are sweet to your taste:

14 so you shall know wisdom to be to your soul;

if you have found it, then there will be a reward,

your hope will not be cut off.

15 Don’t lay in wait, wicked man, against the habitation of the righteous.

Don’t destroy his resting place:

16 for a righteous man falls seven times, and rises up again;

but the wicked are overthrown by calamity.

17 Don’t rejoice when your enemy falls.

Don’t let your heart be glad when he is overthrown;

18 lest Yahweh see it, and it displease him,

and he turn away his wrath from him.

19 Don’t fret yourself because of evildoers;

neither be envious of the wicked:

20 for there will be no reward to the evil man;

and the lamp of the wicked shall be snuffed out.

21 My son, fear Yahweh and the king.

Don’t join those who are rebellious:

22 for their calamity will rise suddenly;

the destruction from them both—who knows?

23 These also are sayings of the wise.

To show partiality in judgment is not good.

24 He who says to the wicked, “You are righteous”;

peoples will curse him, and nations will abhor him—

25 but it will go well with those who convict the guilty,

and a rich blessing will come on them.

26 An honest answer

is like a kiss on the lips.

27 Prepare your work outside,

and get your fields ready.

Afterwards, build your house.

28 Don’t be a witness against your neighbor without cause.

Don’t deceive with your lips.

29 Don’t say, “I will do to him as he has done to me;

I will render to the man according to his work.”

30 I went by the field of the sluggard,

by the vineyard of the man void of understanding;

31 Behold, it was all grown over with thorns.

Its surface was covered with nettles,

and its stone wall was broken down.

32 Then I saw, and considered well.

I saw, and received instruction:

33 a little sleep, a little slumber,

a little folding of the hands to sleep;

34 so your poverty will come as a robber,

and your want as an armed man.

Proverbs 25

1 These also are proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied out.

2 It is the glory of God to conceal a thing,

but the glory of kings is to search out a matter.

3 As the heavens for height, and the earth for depth,

so the hearts of kings are unsearchable.

4 Take away the dross from the silver,

and material comes out for the refiner;

5 Take away the wicked from the king’s presence,

and his throne will be established in righteousness.

6 Don’t exalt yourself in the presence of the king,

or claim a place among great men;

7 for it is better that it be said to you, “Come up here,”

than that you should be put lower in the presence of the prince,

whom your eyes have seen.

8 Don’t be hasty in bringing charges to court.

What will you do in the end when your neighbor shames you?

9 Debate your case with your neighbor,

and don’t betray the confidence of another;

10 lest one who hears it put you to shame,

and your bad reputation never depart.

11 A word fitly spoken

is like apples of gold in settings of silver.

12 As an earring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold,

so is a wise reprover to an obedient ear.

13 As the cold of snow in the time of harvest,

so is a faithful messenger to those who send him;

for he refreshes the soul of his masters.

14 As clouds and wind without rain,

so is he who boasts of gifts deceptively.

15 By patience a ruler is persuaded.

A soft tongue breaks the bone.

16 Have you found honey?

Eat as much as is sufficient for you,

lest you eat too much, and vomit it.

17 Let your foot be seldom in your neighbor’s house,

lest he be weary of you, and hate you.

18 A man who gives false testimony against his neighbor

is like a club, a sword, or a sharp arrow.

19 Confidence in someone unfaithful in time of trouble

is like a bad tooth, or a lame foot.

20 As one who takes away a garment in cold weather,

or vinegar on soda,

so is one who sings songs to a heavy heart.

21 If your enemy is hungry, give him food to eat.

If he is thirsty, give him water to drink:

22 for you will heap coals of fire on his head,

and Yahweh will reward you.

23 The north wind produces rain;

so a backbiting tongue brings an angry face.

24 It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop,

than to share a house with a contentious woman.

25 Like cold water to a thirsty soul,

so is good news from a far country.

26 Like a muddied spring, and a polluted well,

so is a righteous man who gives way before the wicked.

27 It is not good to eat much honey;

nor is it honorable to seek one’s own honor.

28 Like a city that is broken down and without walls

is a man whose spirit is without restraint.

Proverbs 26

1 Like snow in summer, and as rain in harvest,

so honor is not fitting for a fool.

2 Like a fluttering sparrow,

like a darting swallow,

so the undeserved curse doesn’t come to rest.

3 A whip is for the horse,

a bridle for the donkey,

and a rod for the back of fools!

4 Don’t answer a fool according to his folly,

lest you also be like him.

5 Answer a fool according to his folly,

lest he be wise in his own eyes.

6 One who sends a message by the hand of a fool

is cutting off feet and drinking violence.

7 Like the legs of the lame that hang loose,

so is a parable in the mouth of fools.

8 As one who binds a stone in a sling,

so is he who gives honor to a fool.

9 Like a thorn bush that goes into the hand of a drunkard,

so is a parable in the mouth of fools.

10 As an archer who wounds all,

so is he who hires a fool

or he who hires those who pass by.

11 As a dog that returns to his vomit,

so is a fool who repeats his folly.

12 Do you see a man wise in his own eyes?

There is more hope for a fool than for him.

13 The sluggard says, “There is a lion in the road!

A fierce lion roams the streets!”

14 As the door turns on its hinges,

so does the sluggard on his bed.

15 The sluggard buries his hand in the dish.

He is too lazy to bring it back to his mouth.

16 The sluggard is wiser in his own eyes

than seven men who answer with discretion.

17 Like one who grabs a dog’s ears

is one who passes by and meddles in a quarrel not his own.

18 Like a madman who shoots torches, arrows, and death,

19 is the man who deceives his neighbor and says, “Am I not joking?”

20 For lack of wood a fire goes out.

Without gossip, a quarrel dies down.

21 As coals are to hot embers,

and wood to fire,

so is a contentious man to kindling strife.

22 The words of a whisperer are as dainty morsels,

they go down into the innermost parts.

23 Like silver dross on an earthen vessel

are the lips of a fervent one with an evil heart.

24 A malicious man disguises himself with his lips,

but he harbors evil in his heart.

25 When his speech is charming, don’t believe him;

for there are seven abominations in his heart.

26 His malice may be concealed by deception,

but his wickedness will be exposed in the assembly.

27 Whoever digs a pit shall fall into it.

Whoever rolls a stone, it will come back on him.

28 A lying tongue hates those it hurts;

and a flattering mouth works ruin.

Proverbs 27

1 Don’t boast about tomorrow;

for you don’t know what a day may bring.

2 Let another man praise you,

and not your own mouth;

a stranger, and not your own lips.

3 A stone is heavy,

and sand is a burden;

but a fool’s provocation is heavier than both.

4 Wrath is cruel,

and anger is overwhelming;

but who is able to stand before jealousy?

5 Better is open rebuke

than hidden love.

6 Faithful are the wounds of a friend;

although the kisses of an enemy are profuse.

7 A full soul loathes a honeycomb;

but to a hungry soul, every bitter thing is sweet.

8 As a bird that wanders from her nest,

so is a man who wanders from his home.

9 Perfume and incense bring joy to the heart;

so does earnest counsel from a man’s friend.

10 Don’t forsake your friend and your father’s friend.

Don’t go to your brother’s house in the day of your disaster:

better is a neighbor who is near than a distant brother.

11 Be wise, my son,

and bring joy to my heart,

then I can answer my tormentor.

12 A prudent man sees danger and takes refuge;

but the simple pass on, and suffer for it.

13 Take his garment when he puts up collateral for a stranger.

Hold it for a wayward woman!

14 He who blesses his neighbor with a loud voice early in the morning,

it will be taken as a curse by him.

15 A continual dropping on a rainy day

and a contentious wife are alike:

16 restraining her is like restraining the wind,

or like grasping oil in his right hand.

17 Iron sharpens iron;

so a man sharpens his friend’s countenance.

18 Whoever tends the fig tree shall eat its fruit.

He who looks after his master shall be honored.

19 Like water reflects a face,

so a man’s heart reflects the man.

20 Sheol[*] and Abaddon are never satisfied;

and a man’s eyes are never satisfied.

21 The crucible is for silver,

and the furnace for gold;

but man is refined by his praise.

22 Though you grind a fool in a mortar with a pestle along with grain,

yet his foolishness will not be removed from him.

23 Know well the state of your flocks,

and pay attention to your herds:

24 for riches are not forever,

nor does the crown endure to all generations.

25 The hay is removed, and the new growth appears,

the grasses of the hills are gathered in.

26 The lambs are for your clothing,

and the goats are the price of a field.

27 There will be plenty of goats’ milk for your food,

for your family’s food,

and for the nourishment of your servant girls.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 28

1 The wicked flee when no one pursues;

but the righteous are as bold as a lion.

2 In rebellion, a land has many rulers,

but order is maintained by a man of understanding and knowledge.

3 A needy man who oppresses the poor

is like a driving rain which leaves no crops.

4 Those who forsake the law praise the wicked;

but those who keep the law contend with them.

5 Evil men don’t understand justice;

but those who seek Yahweh understand it fully.

6 Better is the poor who walks in his integrity,

than he who is perverse in his ways, and he is rich.

7 Whoever keeps the law is a wise son;

but he who is a companion of gluttons shames his father.

8 He who increases his wealth by excessive interest

gathers it for one who has pity on the poor.

9 He who turns away his ear from hearing the law,

even his prayer is an abomination.

10 Whoever causes the upright to go astray in an evil way,

he will fall into his own trap;

but the blameless will inherit good.

11 The rich man is wise in his own eyes;

but the poor who has understanding sees through him.

12 When the righteous triumph, there is great glory;

but when the wicked rise, men hide themselves.

13 He who conceals his sins doesn’t prosper,

but whoever confesses and renounces them finds mercy.

14 Blessed is the man who always fears;

but one who hardens his heart falls into trouble.

15 As a roaring lion or a charging bear,

so is a wicked ruler over helpless people.

16 A tyrannical ruler lacks judgment.

One who hates ill-gotten gain will have long days.

17 A man who is tormented by life blood will be a fugitive until death;

no one will support him.

18 Whoever walks blamelessly is kept safe;

but one with perverse ways will fall suddenly.

19 One who works his land will have an abundance of food;

but one who chases fantasies will have his fill of poverty.

20 A faithful man is rich with blessings;

but one who is eager to be rich will not go unpunished.

21 To show partiality is not good;

yet a man will do wrong for a piece of bread.

22 A stingy man hurries after riches,

and doesn’t know that poverty waits for him.

23 One who rebukes a man will afterward find more favor

than one who flatters with the tongue.

24 Whoever robs his father or his mother, and says, “It’s not wrong.”

He is a partner with a destroyer.

25 One who is greedy stirs up strife;

but one who trusts in Yahweh will prosper.

26 One who trusts in himself is a fool;

but one who walks in wisdom is kept safe.

27 One who gives to the poor has no lack;

but one who closes his eyes will have many curses.

28 When the wicked rise, men hide themselves;

but when they perish, the righteous thrive.

Proverbs 29

1 He who is often rebuked and stiffens his neck

will be destroyed suddenly, with no remedy.

2 When the righteous thrive, the people rejoice;

but when the wicked rule, the people groan.

3 Whoever loves wisdom brings joy to his father;

but a companion of prostitutes squanders his wealth.

4 The king by justice makes the land stable,

but he who takes bribes tears it down.

5 A man who flatters his neighbor

spreads a net for his feet.

6 An evil man is snared by his sin,

but the righteous can sing and be glad.

7 The righteous care about justice for the poor.

The wicked aren’t concerned about knowledge.

8 Mockers stir up a city,

but wise men turn away anger.

9 If a wise man goes to court with a foolish man,

the fool rages or scoffs, and there is no peace.

10 The bloodthirsty hate a man of integrity;

and they seek the life of the upright.

11 A fool vents all of his anger,

but a wise man brings himself under control.

12 If a ruler listens to lies,

all of his officials are wicked.

13 The poor man and the oppressor have this in common:

Yahweh gives sight to the eyes of both.

14 The king who fairly judges the poor,

his throne shall be established forever.

15 The rod of correction gives wisdom,

but a child left to himself causes shame to his mother.

16 When the wicked increase, sin increases;

but the righteous will see their downfall.

17 Correct your son, and he will give you peace;

yes, he will bring delight to your soul.

18 Where there is no revelation, the people cast off restraint;

but one who keeps the law is blessed.

19 A servant can’t be corrected by words.

Though he understands, yet he will not respond.

20 Do you see a man who is hasty in his words?

There is more hope for a fool than for him.

21 He who pampers his servant from youth

will have him become a son in the end.

22 An angry man stirs up strife,

and a wrathful man abounds in sin.

23 A man’s pride brings him low,

but one of lowly spirit gains honor.

24 Whoever is an accomplice of a thief is an enemy of his own soul.

He takes an oath, but dares not testify.

25 The fear of man proves to be a snare,

but whoever puts his trust in Yahweh is kept safe.

26 Many seek the ruler’s favor,

but a man’s justice comes from Yahweh.

27 A dishonest man detests the righteous,

and the upright in their ways detest the wicked.

Proverbs 30

1 The words of Agur the son of Jakeh; the revelation:

the man says to Ithiel,

to Ithiel and Ucal:

2 “Surely I am the most ignorant man,

and don’t have a man’s understanding.

3 I have not learned wisdom,

neither do I have the knowledge of the Holy One.

4 Who has ascended up into heaven, and descended?

Who has gathered the wind in his fists?

Who has bound the waters in his garment?

Who has established all the ends of the earth?

What is his name, and what is his son’s name, if you know?

5 “Every word of God is flawless.

He is a shield to those who take refuge in him.

6 Don’t you add to his words,

lest he reprove you, and you be found a liar.

7 “Two things I have asked of you;

don’t deny me before I die:

8 Remove far from me falsehood and lies.

Give me neither poverty nor riches.

Feed me with the food that is needful for me;

9 lest I be full, deny you, and say, ‘Who is Yahweh?’

or lest I be poor, and steal,

and so dishonor the name of my God.

10 “Don’t slander a servant to his master,

lest he curse you, and you be held guilty.

11 There is a generation that curses their father,

and doesn’t bless their mother.

12 There is a generation that is pure in their own eyes,

yet are not washed from their filthiness.

13 There is a generation, oh how lofty are their eyes!

Their eyelids are lifted up.

14 There is a generation whose teeth are like swords,

and their jaws like knives,

to devour the poor from the earth, and the needy from among men.

15 “The leach has two daughters:

‘Give, give.’

“There are three things that are never satisfied;

four that don’t say, ‘Enough:’

16 Sheol,[*]

the barren womb;

the earth that is not satisfied with water;

and the fire that doesn’t say, ‘Enough.’

17 “The eye that mocks at his father,

and scorns obedience to his mother:

the ravens of the valley shall pick it out,

the young eagles shall eat it.

18 “There are three things which are too amazing for me,

four which I don’t understand:

19 The way of an eagle in the air;

the way of a serpent on a rock;

the way of a ship in the middle of the sea;

and the way of a man with a maiden.

20 “So is the way of an adulterous woman:

she eats and wipes her mouth,

and says, ‘I have done nothing wrong.’

21 “For three things the earth tremble,

and under four, it can’t bear up:

22 For a servant when he is king;

a fool when he is filled with food;

23 for an unloved woman when she is married;

and a servant who is heir to her mistress.

24 “There are four things which are little on the earth,

but they are exceedingly wise:

25 the ants are not a strong people,

yet they provide their food in the summer.

26 The conies are but a feeble folk,

yet make they their houses in the rocks.

27 The locusts have no king,

yet they advance in ranks.

28 You can catch a lizard with your hands,

yet it is in kings’ palaces.

29 “There are three things which are stately in their march,

four which are stately in going:

30 The lion, which is mightiest among animals,

and doesn’t turn away for any;

31 the greyhound,

the male goat also;

and the king against whom there is no rising up.

32 “If you have done foolishly in lifting up yourself,

or if you have thought evil,

put your hand over your mouth.

33 For as the churning of milk produces butter,

and the wringing of the nose produces blood;

so the forcing of wrath produces strife.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 31

1 The words of king Lemuel; the revelation which his mother taught him.

2 “Oh, my son!

Oh, son of my womb!

Oh, son of my vows!

3 Don’t give your strength to women,

nor your ways to that which destroys kings.

4 It is not for kings, Lemuel;

it is not for kings to drink wine;

nor for princes to say, ‘Where is strong drink?’

5 lest they drink, and forget the law,

and pervert the justice due to anyone who is afflicted.

6 Give strong drink to him who is ready to perish;

and wine to the bitter in soul:

7 Let him drink, and forget his poverty,

and remember his misery no more.

8 Open your mouth for the mute,

in the cause of all who are left desolate.

9 Open your mouth, judge righteously,

and serve justice to the poor and needy.”

10 [*] Who can find a worthy woman?

For her price is far above rubies.

11 The heart of her husband trusts in her.

He shall have no lack of gain.

12 She does him good, and not harm,

all the days of her life.

13 She seeks wool and flax,

and works eagerly with her hands.

14 She is like the merchant ships.

She brings her bread from afar.

15 She rises also while it is yet night,

gives food to her household,

and portions for her servant girls.

16 She considers a field, and buys it.

With the fruit of her hands, she plants a vineyard.

17 She arms her waist with strength,

and makes her arms strong.

18 She perceives that her merchandise is profitable.

Her lamp doesn’t go out by night.

19 She lays her hands to the distaff,

and her hands hold the spindle.

20 She opens her arms to the poor;

yes, she extends her hands to the needy.

21 She is not afraid of the snow for her household;

for all her household are clothed with scarlet.

22 She makes for herself carpets of tapestry.

Her clothing is fine linen and purple.

23 Her husband is respected in the gates,

when he sits among the elders of the land.

24 She makes linen garments and sells them,

and delivers sashes to the merchant.

25 Strength and dignity are her clothing.

She laughs at the time to come.

26 She opens her mouth with wisdom.

Faithful instruction is on her tongue.

27 She looks well to the ways of her household,

and doesn’t eat the bread of idleness.

28 Her children rise up and call her blessed.

Her husband also praises her:

29 “Many women do noble things,

but you excel them all.”

30 Charm is deceitful, and beauty is vain;

but a woman who fears Yahweh, she shall be praised.

31 Give her of the fruit of her hands!

Let her works praise her in the gates!

Proverbs 31:10-31 form an acrostic, with each verse starting with each letter of the Hebrew alphabet, in order.

Ecclesiastes 1

1 The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem:

2 “Vanity of vanities,” says the Preacher; “Vanity of vanities, all is vanity.” 3 What does man gain from all his labor in which he labors under the sun? 4 One generation goes, and another generation comes; but the earth remains forever. 5 The sun also rises, and the sun goes down, and hurries to its place where it rises. 6 The wind goes toward the south, and turns around to the north. It turns around continually as it goes, and the wind returns again to its courses. 7 All the rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full. To the place where the rivers flow, there they flow again. 8 All things are full of weariness beyond uttering. The eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing. 9 That which has been is that which shall be; and that which has been done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun. 10 Is there a thing of which it may be said, “Behold,[*] this is new?” It has been long ago, in the ages which were before us. 11 There is no memory of the former; neither shall there be any memory of the latter that are to come, among those that shall come after.

12 I, the Preacher, was king over Israel in Jerusalem. 13 I applied my heart to seek and to search out by wisdom concerning all that is done under the sky. It is a heavy burden that God[*] has given to the sons of men to be afflicted with. 14 I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and behold, all is vanity and a chasing after wind. 15 That which is crooked can’t be made straight; and that which is lacking can’t be counted. 16 I said to myself, “Behold, I have obtained for myself great wisdom above all who were before me in Jerusalem. Yes, my heart has had great experience of wisdom and knowledge.” 17 I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly. I perceived that this also was a chasing after wind. 18 For in much wisdom is much grief; and he who increases knowledge increases sorrow.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Ecclesiastes 2

1 I said in my heart, “Come now, I will test you with mirth: therefore enjoy pleasure”; and behold, this also was vanity. 2 I said of laughter, “It is foolishness”; and of mirth, “What does it accomplish?”

3 I searched in my heart how to cheer my flesh with wine, my heart yet guiding me with wisdom, and how to lay hold of folly, until I might see what it was good for the sons of men that they should do under heaven all the days of their lives. 4 I made myself great works. I built myself houses. I planted myself vineyards. 5 I made myself gardens and parks, and I planted trees in them of all kinds of fruit. 6 I made myself pools of water, to water from it the forest where trees were reared. 7 I bought male servants and female servants, and had servants born in my house. I also had great possessions of herds and flocks, above all who were before me in Jerusalem; 8 I also gathered silver and gold for myself, and the treasure of kings and of the provinces. I got myself male and female singers, and the delights of the sons of men—musical instruments, and that of all sorts. 9 So I was great, and increased more than all who were before me in Jerusalem. My wisdom also remained with me. 10 Whatever my eyes desired, I didn’t keep from them. I didn’t withhold my heart from any joy, for my heart rejoiced because of all my labor, and this was my portion from all my labor. 11 Then I looked at all the works that my hands had worked, and at the labor that I had labored to do; and behold, all was vanity and a chasing after wind, and there was no profit under the sun.

12 I turned myself to consider wisdom, madness, and folly: for what can the king’s successor do? Just that which has been done long ago. 13 Then I saw that wisdom excels folly, as far as light excels darkness. 14 The wise man’s eyes are in his head, and the fool walks in darkness—and yet I perceived that one event happens to them all. 15 Then I said in my heart, “As it happens to the fool, so will it happen even to me; and why was I then more wise?” Then I said in my heart that this also is vanity. 16 For of the wise man, even as of the fool, there is no memory for ever, since in the days to come all will have been long forgotten. Indeed, the wise man must die just like the fool!

17 So I hated life, because the work that is worked under the sun was grievous to me; for all is vanity and a chasing after wind. 18 I hated all my labor in which I labored under the sun, because I must leave it to the man who comes after me. 19 Who knows whether he will be a wise man or a fool? Yet he will have rule over all of my labor in which I have labored, and in which I have shown myself wise under the sun. This also is vanity.

20 Therefore I began to cause my heart to despair concerning all the labor in which I had labored under the sun. 21 For there is a man whose labor is with wisdom, with knowledge, and with skillfulness; yet he shall leave it for his portion to a man who has not labored for it. This also is vanity and a great evil. 22 For what has a man of all his labor, and of the striving of his heart, in which he labors under the sun? 23 For all his days are sorrows, and his travail is grief; yes, even in the night his heart takes no rest. This also is vanity. 24 There is nothing better for a man than that he should eat and drink, and make his soul enjoy good in his labor. This also I saw, that it is from the hand of God. 25 For who can eat, or who can have enjoyment, more than I? 26 For to the man who pleases him, God gives wisdom, knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he gives travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him who pleases God. This also is vanity and a chasing after wind.

Ecclesiastes 3

1 For everything there is a season, and a time for every purpose under heaven:

2 a time to be born,

and a time to die;

a time to plant,

and a time to pluck up that which is planted;

3 a time to kill,

and a time to heal;

a time to break down,

and a time to build up;

4 a time to weep,

and a time to laugh;

a time to mourn,

and a time to dance;

5 a time to cast away stones,

and a time to gather stones together;

a time to embrace,

and a time to refrain from embracing;

6 a time to seek,

and a time to lose;

a time to keep,

and a time to cast away;

7 a time to tear,

and a time to sew;

a time to keep silence,

and a time to speak;

8 a time to love,

and a time to hate;

a time for war,

and a time for peace.

9 What profit has he who works in that in which he labors? 10 I have seen the burden which God has given to the sons of men to be afflicted with. 11 He has made everything beautiful in its time. He has also set eternity in their hearts, yet so that man can’t find out the work that God has done from the beginning even to the end. 12 I know that there is nothing better for them than to rejoice, and to do good as long as they live. 13 Also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy good in all his labor, is the gift of God. 14 I know that whatever God does, it shall be forever. Nothing can be added to it, nor anything taken from it; and God has done it, that men should fear before him. 15 That which is has been long ago, and that which is to be has been long ago: and God seeks again that which is passed away.

16 Moreover I saw under the sun, in the place of justice, that wickedness was there; and in the place of righteousness, that wickedness was there. 17 I said in my heart, “God will judge the righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every purpose and for every work.” 18 I said in my heart, “As for the sons of men, God tests them, so that they may see that they themselves are like animals. 19 For that which happens to the sons of men happens to animals. Even one thing happens to them. As the one dies, so the other dies. Yes, they have all one breath; and man has no advantage over the animals: for all is vanity. 20 All go to one place. All are from the dust, and all turn to dust again. 21 Who knows the spirit of man, whether it goes upward, and the spirit of the animal, whether it goes downward to the earth?”

22 Therefore I saw that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his works; for that is his portion: for who can bring him to see what will be after him?

Ecclesiastes 4

1 Then I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold, the tears of those who were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter. 2 Therefore I praised the dead who have been long dead more than the living who are yet alive. 3 Yes, better than them both is him who has not yet been, who has not seen the evil work that is done under the sun. 4 Then I saw all the labor and achievement that is the envy of a man’s neighbor. This also is vanity and a striving after wind.

5 The fool folds his hands together and ruins himself. 6 Better is a handful, with quietness, than two handfuls with labor and chasing after wind.

7 Then I returned and saw vanity under the sun. 8 There is one who is alone, and he has neither son nor brother. There is no end to all of his labor, neither are his eyes satisfied with wealth. “For whom then, do I labor, and deprive my soul of enjoyment?” This also is vanity. Yes, it is a miserable business.

9 Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for their labor. 10 For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow; but woe to him who is alone when he falls, and doesn’t have another to lift him up. 11 Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth; but how can one keep warm alone? 12 If a man prevails against one who is alone, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.

13 Better is a poor and wise youth than an old and foolish king who doesn’t know how to receive admonition any more. 14 For out of prison he came out to be king; yes, even in his kingdom he was born poor. 15 I saw all the living who walk under the sun, that they were with the youth, the other, who succeeded him. 16 There was no end of all the people, even of all them over whom he was—yet those who come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and a chasing after wind.

Ecclesiastes 5

1 Guard your steps when you go to God’s house; for to draw near to listen is better than to give the sacrifice of fools, for they don’t know that they do evil. 2 Don’t be rash with your mouth, and don’t let your heart be hasty to utter anything before God; for God is in heaven, and you on earth. Therefore let your words be few. 3 For as a dream comes with a multitude of cares, so a fool’s speech with a multitude of words. 4 When you vow a vow to God, don’t defer to pay it; for he has no pleasure in fools. Pay that which you vow. 5 It is better that you should not vow, than that you should vow and not pay. 6 Don’t allow your mouth to lead you into sin. Don’t protest before the messenger that this was a mistake. Why should God be angry at your voice, and destroy the work of your hands? 7 For in the multitude of dreams there are vanities, as well as in many words: but you must fear God.

8 If you see the oppression of the poor, and the violent taking away of justice and righteousness in a district, don’t marvel at the matter: for one official is eyed by a higher one; and there are officials over them. 9 Moreover the profit of the earth is for all. The king profits from the field.

10 He who loves silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he who loves abundance, with increase: this also is vanity. 11 When goods increase, those who eat them are increased; and what advantage is there to its owner, except to feast on them with his eyes?

12 The sleep of a laboring man is sweet, whether he eats little or much; but the abundance of the rich will not allow him to sleep.

13 There is a grievous evil which I have seen under the sun: wealth kept by its owner to his harm. 14 Those riches perish by misfortune, and if he has fathered a son, there is nothing in his hand. 15 As he came out of his mother’s womb, naked shall he go again as he came, and shall take nothing for his labor, which he may carry away in his hand. 16 This also is a grievous evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go. And what profit does he have who labors for the wind? 17 All his days he also eats in darkness, he is frustrated, and has sickness and wrath.

18 Behold, that which I have seen to be good and proper is for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy good in all his labor, in which he labors under the sun, all the days of his life which God has given him; for this is his portion. 19 Every man also to whom God has given riches and wealth, and has given him power to eat of it, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labor—this is the gift of God. 20 For he shall not often reflect on the days of his life; because God occupies him with the joy of his heart.

Ecclesiastes 7

1 A good name is better than fine perfume; and the day of death better than the day of one’s birth. 2 It is better to go to the house of mourning than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men, and the living should take this to heart. 3 Sorrow is better than laughter; for by the sadness of the face the heart is made good. 4 The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth. 5 It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools. 6 For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool. This also is vanity. 7 Surely extortion makes the wise man foolish; and a bribe destroys the understanding. 8 Better is the end of a thing than its beginning.

The patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit. 9 Don’t be hasty in your spirit to be angry, for anger rests in the bosom of fools. 10 Don’t say, “Why were the former days better than these?” For you do not ask wisely about this.

11 Wisdom is as good as an inheritance. Yes, it is more excellent for those who see the sun. 12 For wisdom is a defense, even as money is a defense; but the excellency of knowledge is that wisdom preserves the life of him who has it.

13 Consider the work of God, for who can make that straight, which he has made crooked? 14 In the day of prosperity be joyful, and in the day of adversity consider; yes, God has made the one side by side with the other, to the end that man should not find out anything after him.

15 All this I have seen in my days of vanity: there is a righteous man who perishes in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man who lives long in his evildoing. 16 Don’t be overly righteous, neither make yourself overly wise. Why should you destroy yourself? 17 Don’t be too wicked, neither be foolish. Why should you die before your time? 18 It is good that you should take hold of this. Yes, also from that don’t withdraw your hand; for he who fears God will come out of them all. 19 Wisdom is a strength to the wise man more than ten rulers who are in a city. 20 Surely there is not a righteous man on earth, who does good and doesn’t sin. 21 Also don’t take heed to all words that are spoken, lest you hear your servant curse you; 22 for often your own heart knows that you yourself have likewise cursed others. 23 All this I have proved in wisdom. I said, “I will be wise”; but it was far from me. 24 That which is, is far off and exceedingly deep. Who can find it out? 25 I turned around, and my heart sought to know and to search out, and to seek wisdom and the scheme of things, and to know that wickedness is stupidity, and that foolishness is madness.

26 I find more bitter than death the woman whose heart is snares and traps, whose hands are chains. Whoever pleases God shall escape from her; but the sinner will be ensnared by her.

27 “Behold, I have found this,” says the Preacher, “to one another, to find out the scheme; 28 which my soul still seeks; but I have not found. I have found one man among a thousand; but I have not found a woman among all those. 29 Behold, I have only found this: that God made man upright; but they search for many schemes.”

Ecclesiastes 8

1 Who is like the wise man? And who knows the interpretation of a thing? A man’s wisdom makes his face shine, and the hardness of his face is changed. 2 I say, “Keep the king’s command!” because of the oath to God. 3 Don’t be hasty to go out of his presence. Don’t persist in an evil thing, for he does whatever pleases him, 4 for the king’s word is supreme. Who can say to him, “What are you doing?” 5 Whoever keeps the commandment shall not come to harm, and his wise heart will know the time and procedure. 6 For there is a time and procedure for every purpose, although the misery of man is heavy on him. 7 For he doesn’t know that which will be; for who can tell him how it will be? 8 There is no man who has power over the spirit to contain the spirit; neither does he have power over the day of death. There is no discharge in war; neither shall wickedness deliver those who practice it.

9 All this I have seen, and applied my mind to every work that is done under the sun. There is a time in which one man has power over another to his hurt. 10 So I saw the wicked buried. Indeed they came also from holiness. They went and were forgotten in the city where they did this. This also is vanity. 11 Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil. 12 Though a sinner commits crimes a hundred times, and lives long, yet surely I know that it will be better with those who fear God, who are reverent before him. 13 But it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he lengthen days like a shadow; because he doesn’t fear God.

14 There is a vanity which is done on the earth, that there are righteous men to whom it happens according to the work of the wicked. Again, there are wicked men to whom it happens according to the work of the righteous. I said that this also is vanity. 15 Then I commended mirth, because a man has no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be joyful: for that will accompany him in his labor all the days of his life which God has given him under the sun.

16 When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done on the earth (for also there is that neither day nor night sees sleep with his eyes), 17 then I saw all the work of God, that man can’t find out the work that is done under the sun, because however much a man labors to seek it out, yet he won’t find it. Yes even though a wise man thinks he can comprehend it, he won’t be able to find it.

Ecclesiastes 9

1 For all this I laid to my heart, even to explore all this: that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God; whether it is love or hatred, man doesn’t know it; all is before them. 2 All things come alike to all. There is one event to the righteous and to the wicked; to the good, to the clean, to the unclean, to him who sacrifices, and to him who doesn’t sacrifice. As is the good, so is the sinner; he who takes an oath, as he who fears an oath. 3 This is an evil in all that is done under the sun, that there is one event to all: yes also, the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead. 4 For to him who is joined with all the living there is hope; for a living dog is better than a dead lion. 5 For the living know that they will die, but the dead don’t know anything, neither do they have any more a reward; for their memory is forgotten. 6 Also their love, their hatred, and their envy has perished long ago; neither have they any more a portion forever in anything that is done under the sun.

7 Go your way—eat your bread with joy, and drink your wine with a merry heart; for God has already accepted your works. 8 Let your garments be always white, and don’t let your head lack oil. 9 Live joyfully with the wife whom you love all the days of your life of vanity, which he has given you under the sun, all your days of vanity: for that is your portion in life, and in your labor in which you labor under the sun. 10 Whatever your hand finds to do, do it with your might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in Sheol,[*] where you are going.

11 I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favor to men of skill; but time and chance happen to them all. 12 For man also doesn’t know his time. As the fish that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare, even so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falls suddenly on them.

13 I have also seen wisdom under the sun in this way, and it seemed great to me. 14 There was a little city, and few men within it; and a great king came against it, besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it. 15 Now a poor wise man was found in it, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man. 16 Then I said, “Wisdom is better than strength.” Nevertheless the poor man’s wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard. 17 The words of the wise heard in quiet are better than the cry of him who rules among fools. 18 Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but one sinner destroys much good.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Ecclesiastes 10

1 Dead flies cause the oil of the perfumer to produce an evil odor;

so does a little folly outweigh wisdom and honor.

2 A wise man’s heart is at his right hand,

but a fool’s heart at his left. 3 Yes also, when the fool walks by the way, his understanding fails him, and he says to everyone that he is a fool. 4 If the spirit of the ruler rises up against you, don’t leave your place; for gentleness lays great offenses to rest.

5 There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, the sort of error which proceeds from the ruler. 6 Folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in a low place. 7 I have seen servants on horses, and princes walking like servants on the earth. 8 He who digs a pit may fall into it; and whoever breaks through a wall may be bitten by a snake. 9 Whoever carves out stones may be injured by them. Whoever splits wood may be endangered thereby. 10 If the ax is blunt, and one doesn’t sharpen the edge, then he must use more strength; but skill brings success.

11 If the snake bites before it is charmed, then is there no profit for the charmer’s tongue. 12 The words of a wise man’s mouth are gracious; but a fool is swallowed by his own lips. 13 The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness; and the end of his talk is mischievous madness. 14 A fool also multiplies words.

Man doesn’t know what will be; and that which will be after him, who can tell him? 15 The labor of fools wearies every one of them; for he doesn’t know how to go to the city.

16 Woe to you, land, when your king is a child,

and your princes eat in the morning! 17 Happy are you, land, when your king is the son of nobles,

and your princes eat in due season,

for strength, and not for drunkenness!

18 By slothfulness the roof sinks in;

and through idleness of the hands the house leaks.

19 A feast is made for laughter,

and wine makes the life glad;

and money is the answer for all things.

20 Don’t curse the king, no, not in your thoughts;

and don’t curse the rich in your bedroom:

for a bird of the sky may carry your voice,

and that which has wings may tell the matter.

Ecclesiastes 11

1 Cast your bread on the waters;

for you shall find it after many days.

2 Give a portion to seven, yes, even to eight;

for you don’t know what evil will be on the earth.

3 If the clouds are full of rain, they empty themselves on the earth;

and if a tree falls toward the south, or toward the north,

in the place where the tree falls, there shall it be.

4 He who observes the wind won’t sow;

and he who regards the clouds won’t reap.

5 As you don’t know what is the way of the wind,

nor how the bones grow in the womb of her who is with child;

even so you don’t know the work of God who does all.

6 In the morning sow your seed,

and in the evening don’t withhold your hand;

for you don’t know which will prosper, whether this or that,

or whether they both will be equally good.

7 Truly the light is sweet,

and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to see the sun.

8 Yes, if a man lives many years, let him rejoice in them all;

but let him remember the days of darkness, for they shall be many.

All that comes is vanity.

9 Rejoice, young man, in your youth,

and let your heart cheer you in the days of your youth,

and walk in the ways of your heart,

and in the sight of your eyes;

but know that for all these things God will bring you into judgment.

10 Therefore remove sorrow from your heart,

and put away evil from your flesh;

for youth and the dawn of life are vanity.

Ecclesiastes 12

1 Remember also your Creator in the days of your youth,

before the evil days come, and the years draw near,

when you will say, “I have no pleasure in them”;

2 Before the sun, the light, the moon, and the stars are darkened,

and the clouds return after the rain;

3 in the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble,

and the strong men shall bow themselves,

and the grinders cease because they are few,

and those who look out of the windows are darkened,

4 and the doors shall be shut in the street;

when the sound of the grinding is low,

and one shall rise up at the voice of a bird,

and all the daughters of music shall be brought low;

5 yes, they shall be afraid of heights,

and terrors will be on the way;

and the almond tree shall blossom,

and the grasshopper shall be a burden,

and desire shall fail;

because man goes to his everlasting home,

and the mourners go about the streets:

6 before the silver cord is severed,

or the golden bowl is broken,

or the pitcher is broken at the spring,

or the wheel broken at the cistern,

7 and the dust returns to the earth as it was,

and the spirit returns to God who gave it.

8 “Vanity of vanities,” says the Preacher.

“All is vanity!”

9 Further, because the Preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge. Yes, he pondered, sought out, and set in order many proverbs. 10 The Preacher sought to find out acceptable words, and that which was written blamelessly, words of truth. 11 The words of the wise are like goads; and like nails well fastened are words from the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd. 12 Furthermore, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh.

13 This is the end of the matter. All has been heard. Fear God, and keep his commandments; for this is the whole duty of man. 14 For God will bring every work into judgment, with every hidden thing, whether it is good, or whether it is evil.

Song of Solomon 1

1 The Song of songs, which is Solomon’s.

2 Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth;

for your love is better than wine.

3 Your oils have a pleasing fragrance.

Your name is oil poured out,

therefore the virgins love you.

4 Take me away with you.

Let us hurry.

The king has brought me into his rooms.

We will be glad and rejoice in you.

We will praise your love more than wine!

They are right to love you.

5 I am dark, but lovely,

you daughters of Jerusalem,

like Kedar’s tents,

like Solomon’s curtains.

6 Don’t stare at me because I am dark,

because the sun has scorched me.

My mother’s sons were angry with me.

They made me keeper of the vineyards.

I haven’t kept my own vineyard.

7 Tell me, you whom my soul loves,

where you graze your flock,

where you rest them at noon;

For why should I be as one who is veiled

beside the flocks of your companions?

8 If you don’t know, most beautiful among women,

follow the tracks of the sheep.

Graze your young goats beside the shepherds’ tents.

9 I have compared you, my love,

to a steed in Pharaoh’s chariots.

10 Your cheeks are beautiful with earrings,

your neck with strings of jewels.

11 We will make you earrings of gold,

with studs of silver.

12 While the king sat at his table,

my perfume spread its fragrance.

13 My beloved is to me a sachet of myrrh,

that lies between my breasts.

14 My beloved is to me a cluster of henna blossoms

from the vineyards of En Gedi.

15 Behold,[*] you are beautiful, my love.

Behold, you are beautiful.

Your eyes are doves.

16 Behold, you are beautiful, my beloved, yes, pleasant;

and our couch is verdant.

17 The beams of our house are cedars.

Our rafters are firs.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Song of Solomon 2

1 I am a rose of Sharon,

a lily of the valleys.

2 As a lily among thorns,

so is my love among the daughters.

3 As the apple tree among the trees of the wood,

so is my beloved among the sons.

I sat down under his shadow with great delight,

his fruit was sweet to my taste.

4 He brought me to the banquet hall.

His banner over me is love.

5 Strengthen me with raisins,

refresh me with apples;

For I am faint with love.

6 His left hand is under my head.

His right hand embraces me.

7 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

by the roes, or by the hinds of the field,

that you not stir up, nor awaken love,

until it so desires.

8 The voice of my beloved!

Behold, he comes,

leaping on the mountains,

skipping on the hills.

9 My beloved is like a roe or a young deer.

Behold, he stands behind our wall!

He looks in at the windows.

He glances through the lattice.

10 My beloved spoke, and said to me,

“Rise up, my love, my beautiful one, and come away.

11 For, behold, the winter is past.

The rain is over and gone.

12 The flowers appear on the earth.

The time of the singing has come,

and the voice of the turtledove is heard in our land.

13 The fig tree ripens her green figs.

The vines are in blossom.

They give out their fragrance.

Arise, my love, my beautiful one,

and come away.”

14 My dove in the clefts of the rock,

In the hiding places of the mountainside,

Let me see your face.

Let me hear your voice;

for your voice is sweet, and your face is lovely.

15 Catch for us the foxes,

the little foxes that plunder the vineyards;

for our vineyards are in blossom.

16 My beloved is mine, and I am his.

He browses among the lilies.

17 Until the day is cool, and the shadows flee away,

turn, my beloved,

and be like a roe or a young deer on the mountains of Bether.

Song of Solomon 3

1 By night on my bed,

I sought him whom my soul loves.

I sought him, but I didn’t find him.

2 I will get up now, and go about the city;

in the streets and in the squares I will seek him whom my soul loves.

I sought him, but I didn’t find him.

3 The watchmen who go about the city found me;

“Have you seen him whom my soul loves?”

4 I had scarcely passed from them,

when I found him whom my soul loves.

I held him, and would not let him go,

until I had brought him into my mother’s house,

into the room of her who conceived me.

5 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

by the roes, or by the hinds of the field,

that you not stir up, nor awaken love,

until it so desires.

6 Who is this who comes up from the wilderness like pillars of smoke,

perfumed with myrrh and frankincense,

with all spices of the merchant?

7 Behold, it is Solomon’s carriage!

Sixty mighty men are around it,

of the mighty men of Israel.

8 They all handle the sword, and are expert in war.

Every man has his sword on his thigh,

because of fear in the night.

9 King Solomon made himself a carriage

of the wood of Lebanon.

10 He made its pillars of silver,

its bottom of gold, its seat of purple,

the middle of it being paved with love,

from the daughters of Jerusalem.

11 Go out, you daughters of Zion, and see king Solomon,

with the crown with which his mother has crowned him,

in the day of his weddings,

in the day of the gladness of his heart.

Song of Solomon 4

1 Behold, you are beautiful, my love.

Behold, you are beautiful.

Your eyes are doves behind your veil.

Your hair is as a flock of goats,

that descend from Mount Gilead.

2 Your teeth are like a newly shorn flock,

which have come up from the washing,

where every one of them has twins.

None is bereaved among them.

3 Your lips are like scarlet thread.

Your mouth is lovely.

Your temples are like a piece of a pomegranate behind your veil.

4 Your neck is like David’s tower built for an armory,

whereon a thousand shields hang,

all the shields of the mighty men.

5 Your two breasts are like two fawns

that are twins of a roe,

which feed among the lilies.

6 Until the day is cool, and the shadows flee away,

I will go to the mountain of myrrh,

to the hill of frankincense.

7 You are all beautiful, my love.

There is no spot in you.

8 Come with me from Lebanon, my bride,

with me from Lebanon.

Look from the top of Amana,

from the top of Senir and Hermon,

from the lions’ dens,

from the mountains of the leopards.

9 You have ravished my heart, my sister, my bride.

You have ravished my heart with one of your eyes,

with one chain of your neck.

10 How beautiful is your love, my sister, my bride!

How much better is your love than wine!

The fragrance of your perfumes than all kinds of spices!

11 Your lips, my bride, drip like the honeycomb.

Honey and milk are under your tongue.

The smell of your garments is like the smell of Lebanon.

12 A locked up garden is my sister, my bride;

a locked up spring,

a sealed fountain.

13 Your shoots are an orchard of pomegranates, with precious fruits:

henna with spikenard plants,

14 spikenard and saffron,

calamus and cinnamon, with every kind of incense tree;

myrrh and aloes, with all the best spices,

15 a fountain of gardens,

a well of living waters,

flowing streams from Lebanon.

16 Awake, north wind; and come, you south!

Blow on my garden, that its spices may flow out.

Let my beloved come into his garden,

and taste his precious fruits.

Song of Solomon 5

1 I have come into my garden, my sister, my bride.

I have gathered my myrrh with my spice;

I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey;

I have drunk my wine with my milk.

Eat, friends!

Drink, yes, drink abundantly, beloved.

2 I was asleep, but my heart was awake.

It is the voice of my beloved who knocks:

“Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled;

for my head is filled with dew,

and my hair with the dampness of the night.”

3 I have taken off my robe. Indeed, must I put it on?

I have washed my feet. Indeed, must I soil them?

4 My beloved thrust his hand in through the latch opening.

My heart pounded for him.

5 I rose up to open for my beloved.

My hands dripped with myrrh,

my fingers with liquid myrrh,

on the handles of the lock.

6 I opened to my beloved;

but my beloved left; and had gone away.

My heart went out when he spoke.

I looked for him, but I didn’t find him.

I called him, but he didn’t answer.

7 The watchmen who go about the city found me.

They beat me.

They bruised me.

The keepers of the walls took my cloak away from me.

8 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

If you find my beloved,

that you tell him that I am faint with love.

9 How is your beloved better than another beloved,

you fairest among women?

How is your beloved better than another beloved,

that you do so adjure us?

10 My beloved is white and ruddy.

The best among ten thousand.

11 His head is like the purest gold.

His hair is bushy, black as a raven.

12 His eyes are like doves beside the water brooks,

washed with milk, mounted like jewels.

13 His cheeks are like a bed of spices with towers of perfumes.

His lips are like lilies, dropping liquid myrrh.

14 His hands are like rings of gold set with beryl.

His body is like ivory work overlaid with sapphires.

15 His legs are like pillars of marble set on sockets of fine gold.

His appearance is like Lebanon, excellent as the cedars.

16 His mouth is sweetness;

yes, he is altogether lovely.

This is my beloved, and this is my friend,

daughters of Jerusalem.

Song of Solomon 6

1 Where has your beloved gone, you fairest among women?

Where has your beloved turned, that we may seek him with you?

2 My beloved has gone down to his garden,

to the beds of spices,

to feed in the gardens, and to gather lilies.

3 I am my beloved’s, and my beloved is mine.

He browses among the lilies,

4 You are beautiful, my love, as Tirzah,

lovely as Jerusalem,

awesome as an army with banners.

5 Turn away your eyes from me,

for they have overcome me.

Your hair is like a flock of goats,

that lie along the side of Gilead.

6 Your teeth are like a flock of ewes,

which have come up from the washing;

of which every one has twins;

no one is bereaved among them.

7 Your temples are like a piece of a pomegranate behind your veil.

8 There are sixty queens, eighty concubines,

and virgins without number.

9 My dove, my perfect one, is unique.

She is her mother’s only daughter.

She is the favorite one of her who bore her.

The daughters saw her, and called her blessed;

the queens and the concubines, and they praised her.

10 Who is she who looks out as the morning,

beautiful as the moon,

clear as the sun,

and awesome as an army with banners?

11 I went down into the nut tree grove,

to see the green plants of the valley,

to see whether the vine budded,

and the pomegranates were in flower.

12 Without realizing it,

my desire set me with my royal people’s chariots.

13 Return, return, Shulammite!

Return, return, that we may gaze at you.

Why do you desire to gaze at the Shulammite,

as at the dance of Mahanaim?

Song of Solomon 7

1 How beautiful are your feet in sandals, prince’s daughter!

Your rounded thighs are like jewels,

the work of the hands of a skillful workman.

2 Your body is like a round goblet,

no mixed wine is wanting.

Your waist is like a heap of wheat,

set about with lilies.

3 Your two breasts are like two fawns,

that are twins of a roe.

4 Your neck is like an ivory tower.

Your eyes are like the pools in Heshbon by the gate of Bathrabbim.

Your nose is like the tower of Lebanon which looks toward Damascus.

5 Your head on you is like Carmel.

The hair of your head like purple.

The king is held captive in its tresses.

6 How beautiful and how pleasant you are,

love, for delights!

7 This, your stature, is like a palm tree,

your breasts like its fruit.

8 I said, “I will climb up into the palm tree.

I will take hold of its fruit.”

Let your breasts be like clusters of the vine,

the smell of your breath like apples,

9 Your mouth like the best wine,

that goes down smoothly for my beloved,

gliding through the lips of those who are asleep.

10 I am my beloved’s.

His desire is toward me.

11 Come, my beloved, let us go out into the field.

Let us lodge in the villages.

12 Let’s go early up to the vineyards.

Let’s see whether the vine has budded,

its blossom is open,

and the pomegranates are in flower.

There I will give you my love.

13 The mandrakes produce fragrance.

At our doors are all kinds of precious fruits, new and old,

which I have stored up for you, my beloved.

Song of Solomon 8

1 Oh that you were like my brother,

who nursed from the breasts of my mother!

If I found you outside, I would kiss you;

yes, and no one would despise me.

2 I would lead you, bringing you into my mother’s house,

who would instruct me.

I would have you drink spiced wine,

of the juice of my pomegranate.

3 His left hand would be under my head.

His right hand would embrace me.

4 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

that you not stir up, nor awaken love,

until it so desires.

5 Who is this who comes up from the wilderness,

leaning on her beloved?

Under the apple tree I aroused you.

There your mother conceived you.

There she was in labor and bore you.

6 Set me as a seal on your heart,

as a seal on your arm;

for love is strong as death.

Jealousy is as cruel as Sheol.[*]

Its flashes are flashes of fire,

a very flame of Yahweh.[*]

7 Many waters can’t quench love,

neither can floods drown it.

If a man would give all the wealth of his house for love,

he would be utterly scorned.

8 We have a little sister.

She has no breasts.

What shall we do for our sister

in the day when she is to be spoken for?

9 If she is a wall,

we will build on her a turret of silver.

if she is a door,

we will enclose her with boards of cedar.

10 I am a wall, and my breasts like towers,

then I was in his eyes like one who found peace.

11 Solomon had a vineyard at Baal Hamon.

He leased out the vineyard to keepers.

Each was to bring a thousand shekels[*] of silver for its fruit.

12 My own vineyard is before me.

The thousand are for you, Solomon;

two hundred for those who tend its fruit.

13 You who dwell in the gardens, with friends in attendance,

let me hear your voice!

14 Come away, my beloved!

Be like a gazelle or a young stag on the mountains of spices!

Sheol is the place of the dead.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 1000 shekels is about 10 kilograms or about 22 pounds.

Isaiah 1

1 The vision of Isaiah the son of Amoz, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah.

2 Hear, heavens,

and listen, earth; for Yahweh[*] has spoken:

“I have nourished and brought up children,

and they have rebelled against me.

3 The ox knows his owner,

and the donkey his master’s crib;

but Israel doesn’t know,

my people don’t consider.”

4 Ah sinful nation,

a people loaded with iniquity,

offspring[*] of evildoers,

children who deal corruptly!

They have forsaken Yahweh.

They have despised the Holy One of Israel.

They are estranged and backward.

5 Why should you be beaten more,

that you revolt more and more?

The whole head is sick,

and the whole heart faint.

6 From the sole of the foot even to the head there is no soundness in it:

wounds, welts, and open sores.

They haven’t been closed, neither bandaged, neither soothed with oil.

7 Your country is desolate.

Your cities are burned with fire.

Strangers devour your land in your presence,

and it is desolate,

as overthrown by strangers.

8 The daughter of Zion is left like a shelter in a vineyard,

like a hut in a field of melons,

like a besieged city.

9 Unless Yahweh of Armies had left to us a very small remnant,

we would have been as Sodom;

we would have been like Gomorrah.

10 Hear Yahweh’s word, you rulers of Sodom!

Listen to the law of our God,[*] you people of Gomorrah!

11 “What are the multitude of your sacrifices to me?”, says Yahweh.

“I have had enough of the burnt offerings of rams,

and the fat of fed animals.

I don’t delight in the blood of bulls,

or of lambs,

or of male goats.

12 When you come to appear before me,

who has required this at your hand, to trample my courts?

13 Bring no more vain offerings.

Incense is an abomination to me;

new moons, Sabbaths, and convocations:

I can’t bear with evil assemblies.

14 My soul hates your New Moons and your appointed feasts.

They are a burden to me.

I am weary of bearing them.

15 When you spread out your hands, I will hide my eyes from you.

Yes, when you make many prayers, I will not hear.

Your hands are full of blood.

16 Wash yourselves, make yourself clean.

Put away the evil of your doings from before my eyes.

Cease to do evil.

17 Learn to do well.

Seek justice.

Relieve the oppressed.

Judge the fatherless.

Plead for the widow.”

18 “Come now, and let us reason together,” says Yahweh:

“Though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow.

Though they be red like crimson, they shall be as wool.

19 If you are willing and obedient,

you shall eat the good of the land;

20 but if you refuse and rebel, you shall be devoured with the sword;

for the mouth of Yahweh has spoken it.”

21 How the faithful city has become a prostitute!

She was full of justice; righteousness lodged in her,

but now murderers.

22 Your silver has become dross,

your wine mixed with water.

23 Your princes are rebellious, and companions of thieves.

Everyone loves bribes, and follows after rewards.

They don’t judge the fatherless,

neither does the cause of the widow come to them.

24 Therefore the Lord,[*] Yahweh of Armies,

the Mighty One of Israel, says:

“Ah, I will get relief from my adversaries,

and avenge myself on my enemies;

25 and I will turn my hand on you,

thoroughly purge away your dross,

and will take away all your tin.[*]

26 I will restore your judges as at the first,

and your counselors as at the beginning.

Afterward you shall be called ‘The city of righteousness,

a faithful town.’

27 Zion shall be redeemed with justice,

and her converts with righteousness.

28 But the destruction of transgressors and sinners shall be together,

and those who forsake Yahweh shall be consumed.

29 For they shall be ashamed of the oaks which you have desired,

and you shall be confounded for the gardens that you have chosen.

30 For you shall be as an oak whose leaf fades,

and as a garden that has no water.

31 The strong will be like tinder,

and his work like a spark.

They will both burn together,

and no one will quench them.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

or, seed

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

tin is a metal that is separated from silver during the refining and purification process.

Isaiah 2

1 This is what Isaiah the son of Amoz saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem.

2 It shall happen in the latter days, that the mountain of Yahweh’s house shall be established on the top of the mountains,

and shall be raised above the hills;

and all nations shall flow to it.

3 Many peoples shall go and say,

“Come, let’s go up to the mountain of Yahweh,

to the house of the God of Jacob;

and he will teach us of his ways,

and we will walk in his paths.”

For out of Zion the law shall go out,

and Yahweh’s word from Jerusalem.

4 He will judge between the nations,

and will decide concerning many peoples;

and they shall beat their swords into plowshares,

and their spears into pruning hooks.

Nation shall not lift up sword against nation,

neither shall they learn war any more.

5 House of Jacob, come, and let us walk in the light of Yahweh.

6 For you have forsaken your people, the house of Jacob,

because they are filled from the east,

with those who practice divination like the Philistines,

and they clasp hands with the children of foreigners.

7 Their land is full of silver and gold,

neither is there any end of their treasures.

Their land also is full of horses,

neither is there any end of their chariots.

8 Their land also is full of idols.

They worship the work of their own hands,

that which their own fingers have made.

9 Man is brought low,

and mankind is humbled;

therefore don’t forgive them.

10 Enter into the rock,

and hide in the dust,

from before the terror of Yahweh,

and from the glory of his majesty.

11 The lofty looks of man will be brought low,

the haughtiness of men will be bowed down,

and Yahweh alone will be exalted in that day.

12 For there will be a day of Yahweh of Armies for all that is proud and haughty,

and for all that is lifted up;

and it shall be brought low:

13 For all the cedars of Lebanon, that are high and lifted up,

for all the oaks of Bashan,

14 For all the high mountains,

for all the hills that are lifted up,

15 For every lofty tower,

for every fortified wall,

16 For all the ships of Tarshish,

and for all pleasant imagery.

17 The loftiness of man shall be bowed down,

and the haughtiness of men shall be brought low;

and Yahweh alone shall be exalted in that day.

18 The idols shall utterly pass away.

19 Men shall go into the caves of the rocks,

and into the holes of the earth,

from before the terror of Yahweh,

and from the glory of his majesty,

when he arises to shake the earth mightily.

20 In that day, men shall cast away their idols of silver,

and their idols of gold,

which have been made for themselves to worship,

to the moles and to the bats;

21 To go into the caverns of the rocks,

and into the clefts of the ragged rocks,

from before the terror of Yahweh,

and from the glory of his majesty,

when he arises to shake the earth mightily.

22 Stop trusting in man, whose breath is in his nostrils;

for of what account is he?

Isaiah 3

1 For, behold,[*] the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, takes away from Jerusalem and from Judah supply and support,

the whole supply of bread,

and the whole supply of water;

2 the mighty man,

the man of war,

the judge,

the prophet,

the diviner,

the elder,

3 the captain of fifty,

the honorable man,

the counselor,

the skilled craftsman,

and the clever enchanter.

4 I will give boys to be their princes,

and children shall rule over them.

5 The people will be oppressed,

everyone by another,

and everyone by his neighbor.

The child will behave himself proudly against the old man,

and the base against the honorable.

6 Indeed a man shall take hold of his brother in the house of his father, saying,

“You have clothing, you be our ruler,

and let this ruin be under your hand.”

7 In that day he will cry out, saying, “I will not be a healer;

for in my house is neither bread nor clothing.

You shall not make me ruler of the people.”

8 For Jerusalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen;

because their tongue and their doings are against Yahweh,

to provoke the eyes of his glory.

9 The look of their faces testify against them.

They parade their sin like Sodom.

They don’t hide it.

Woe to their soul!

For they have brought disaster upon themselves.

10 Tell the righteous “Good!”

For they shall eat the fruit of their deeds.

11 Woe to the wicked!

Disaster is upon them;

for the deeds of his hands will be paid back to him.

12 As for my people, children are their oppressors,

and women rule over them.

My people, those who lead you cause you to err,

and destroy the way of your paths.

13 Yahweh stands up to contend,

and stands to judge the peoples.

14 Yahweh will enter into judgment with the elders of his people,

and their leaders:

“It is you who have eaten up the vineyard.

The plunder of the poor is in your houses.

15 What do you mean that you crush my people,

and grind the face of the poor?” says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies.

16 Moreover Yahweh said, “Because the daughters of Zion are haughty,

and walk with outstretched necks and flirting eyes,

walking to trip as they go,

jingling ornaments on their feet;

17 therefore the Lord brings sores on the crown of the head of the women of Zion,

and Yahweh will make their scalps bald.”

18 In that day the Lord will take away the beauty of their anklets, the headbands, the crescent necklaces, 19 the earrings, the bracelets, the veils, 20 the headdresses, the ankle chains, the sashes, the perfume bottles, the charms, 21 the signet rings, the nose rings, 22 the fine robes, the capes, the cloaks, the purses, 23 the hand mirrors, the fine linen garments, the tiaras, and the shawls.

24 It shall happen that instead of sweet spices, there shall be rottenness;

instead of a belt, a rope;

instead of well set hair, baldness;

instead of a robe, a wearing of sackcloth;

and branding instead of beauty.

25 Your men shall fall by the sword,

and your mighty in the war.

26 Her gates shall lament and mourn;

and she shall be desolate and sit on the ground.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Isaiah 5

1 Let me sing for my well beloved a song of my beloved about his vineyard.

My beloved had a vineyard on a very fruitful hill.

2 He dug it up,

gathered out its stones,

planted it with the choicest vine,

built a tower in the middle of it,

and also cut out a wine press therein.

He looked for it to yield grapes,

but it yielded wild grapes.

3 “Now, inhabitants of Jerusalem and men of Judah,

please judge between me and my vineyard.

4 What could have been done more to my vineyard, that I have not done in it?

Why, when I looked for it to yield grapes, did it yield wild grapes?

5 Now I will tell you what I will do to my vineyard.

I will take away its hedge, and it will be eaten up.

I will break down its wall, and it will be trampled down.

6 I will lay it a wasteland.

It won’t be pruned nor hoed,

but it will grow briers and thorns.

I will also command the clouds that they rain no rain on it.”

7 For the vineyard of Yahweh of Armies is the house of Israel,

and the men of Judah his pleasant plant:

and he looked for justice, but, behold, oppression;

for righteousness, but, behold, a cry of distress.

8 Woe to those who join house to house,

who lay field to field, until there is no room,

and you are made to dwell alone in the middle of the land!

9 In my ears, Yahweh of Armies says: “Surely many houses will be desolate,

even great and beautiful, unoccupied.

10 For ten acres[*] of vineyard shall yield one bath,[*]

and a homer[*] of seed shall yield an ephah.”[*]

11 Woe to those who rise up early in the morning, that they may follow strong drink;

who stay late into the night, until wine inflames them!

12 The harp, lyre, tambourine, and flute, with wine, are at their feasts;

but they don’t respect the work of Yahweh,

neither have they considered the operation of his hands.

13 Therefore my people go into captivity for lack of knowledge.

Their honorable men are famished,

and their multitudes are parched with thirst.

14 Therefore Sheol[*] has enlarged its desire,

and opened its mouth without measure;

and their glory, their multitude, their pomp, and he who rejoices among them, descend into it.

15 So man is brought low,

mankind is humbled,

and the eyes of the arrogant ones are humbled;

16 but Yahweh of Armies is exalted in justice,

and God the Holy One is sanctified in righteousness.

17 Then the lambs will graze as in their pasture,

and strangers will eat the ruins of the rich.

18 Woe to those who draw iniquity with cords of falsehood,

and wickedness as with cart rope;

19 Who say, “Let him make speed, let him hasten his work, that we may see it;

and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel draw near and come,

that we may know it!”

20 Woe to those who call evil good, and good evil;

who put darkness for light,

and light for darkness;

who put bitter for sweet,

and sweet for bitter!

21 Woe to those who are wise in their own eyes,

and prudent in their own sight!

22 Woe to those who are mighty to drink wine,

and champions at mixing strong drink;

23 who acquit the guilty for a bribe,

but deny justice for the innocent!

24 Therefore as the tongue of fire devours the stubble,

and as the dry grass sinks down in the flame,

so their root shall be as rottenness,

and their blossom shall go up as dust;

because they have rejected the law of Yahweh of Armies,

and despised the word of the Holy One of Israel.

25 Therefore Yahweh’s anger burns against his people,

and he has stretched out his hand against them, and has struck them.

The mountains tremble,

and their dead bodies are as refuse in the middle of the streets.

For all this, his anger is not turned away,

but his hand is still stretched out.

26 He will lift up a banner to the nations from far,

and he will whistle for them from the end of the earth.

Behold, they will come speedily and swiftly.

27 No one shall be weary nor stumble among them;

no one shall slumber nor sleep;

neither shall the belt of their waist be untied,

nor the strap of their sandals be broken:

28 whose arrows are sharp,

and all their bows bent.

Their horses’ hoofs will be like flint,

and their wheels like a whirlwind.

29 Their roaring will be like a lioness.

They will roar like young lions.

Yes, they shall roar,

and seize their prey and carry it off,

and there will be no one to deliver.

30 They will roar against them in that day like the roaring of the sea.

If one looks to the land behold, darkness and distress.

The light is darkened in its clouds.

literally, ten yokes, or the amount of land that ten yokes of oxen can plow in one day, which is about 10 acres or 4 hectares.

1 bath is about 22 liters or 5.8 U. S. gallons

1 homer is about 220 liters or 6 bushels

1 ephah is about 22 liters or 0.6 bushels or about 2 pecks—only one tenth of what was sown.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Isaiah 6

1 In the year that king Uzziah died, I saw the Lord sitting on a throne, high and lifted up; and his train filled the temple. 2 Above him stood the seraphim. Each one had six wings. With two he covered his face. With two he covered his feet. With two he flew. 3 One called to another, and said,

“Holy, holy, holy, is Yahweh of Armies!

The whole earth is full of his glory!”

4 The foundations of the thresholds shook at the voice of him who called, and the house was filled with smoke. 5 Then I said, “Woe is me! For I am undone, because I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell among a people of unclean lips: for my eyes have seen the King, Yahweh of Armies!”

6 Then one of the seraphim flew to me, having a live coal in his hand, which he had taken with the tongs from off the altar. 7 He touched my mouth with it, and said, “Behold, this has touched your lips; and your iniquity is taken away, and your sin forgiven.”

8 I heard the Lord’s voice, saying, “Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?”

Then I said, “Here I am. Send me!”

9 He said, “Go, and tell this people,

‘You hear indeed,

but don’t understand;

and you see indeed,

but don’t perceive.’

10 Make the heart of this people fat.

Make their ears heavy, and shut their eyes;

lest they see with their eyes,

and hear with their ears,

and understand with their heart,

and turn again, and be healed.”

11 Then I said, “Lord, how long?”

He answered,

“Until cities are waste without inhabitant,

and houses without man,

and the land becomes utterly waste,

12 And Yahweh has removed men far away,

and the forsaken places are many within the land.

13 If there is a tenth left in it,

that also will in turn be consumed:

as a terebinth, and as an oak, whose stock remains when they are felled;

so the holy seed is its stock.”

Isaiah 7

1 In the days of Ahaz the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, went up to Jerusalem to war against it, but could not prevail against it. 2 David’s house was told, “Syria is allied with Ephraim.” His heart trembled, and the heart of his people, as the trees of the forest tremble with the wind. 3 Then Yahweh said to Isaiah, “Go out now to meet Ahaz, you, and Shearjashub your son, at the end of the conduit of the upper pool, on the highway of the fuller’s field. 4 Tell him, ‘Be careful, and keep calm. Don’t be afraid, neither let your heart be faint because of these two tails of smoking torches, for the fierce anger of Rezin and Syria, and of the son of Remaliah. 5 Because Syria, Ephraim, and the son of Remaliah, have plotted evil against you, saying, 6 “Let’s go up against Judah, and tear it apart, and let’s divide it among ourselves, and set up a king within it, even the son of Tabeel.” 7 This is what the Lord Yahweh says: “It shall not stand, neither shall it happen.” 8 For the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within sixty-five years Ephraim shall be broken in pieces, so that it shall not be a people; 9 and the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliah’s son. If you will not believe, surely you shall not be established.’”

10 Yahweh spoke again to Ahaz, saying, 11 “Ask a sign of Yahweh your God; ask it either in the depth, or in the height above.”

12 But Ahaz said, “I will not ask, neither will I tempt Yahweh.”

13 He said, “Listen now, house of David. Is it not enough for you to try the patience of men, that you will try the patience of my God also? 14 Therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign. Behold, the virgin will conceive, and bear a son, and shall call his name Immanuel.[*] 15 He shall eat butter and honey when he knows to refuse the evil, and choose the good. 16 For before the child knows to refuse the evil, and choose the good, the land whose two kings you abhor shall be forsaken. 17 Yahweh will bring on you, on your people, and on your father’s house, days that have not come, from the day that Ephraim departed from Judah; even the king of Assyria. 18 It will happen in that day that Yahweh will whistle for the fly that is in the uttermost part of the rivers of Egypt, and for the bee that is in the land of Assyria. 19 They shall come, and shall all rest in the desolate valleys, in the clefts of the rocks, on all thorn hedges, and on all pastures. 20 In that day the Lord will shave with a razor that is hired in the parts beyond the River, even with the king of Assyria, the head and the hair of the feet; and it shall also consume the beard. 21 It shall happen in that day that a man shall keep alive a young cow, and two sheep; 22 and it shall happen, that because of the abundance of milk which they shall give he shall eat butter: for everyone will eat butter and honey that is left within the land. 23 It will happen in that day that every place where there were a thousand vines at a thousand silver shekels,[*] shall be for briers and thorns. 24 People will go there with arrows and with bow, because all the land will be briers and thorns. 25 All the hills that were cultivated with the hoe, you shall not come there for fear of briers and thorns; but it shall be for the sending out of oxen, and for the treading of sheep.”

“Immanuel” means “God with us”.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 1000 shekels is about 10 kilograms or 22 pounds.

Isaiah 8

1 Yahweh said to me, “Take a large tablet, and write on it with a man’s pen, ‘For Maher Shalal Hash Baz’;[*] 2 and I will take for myself faithful witnesses to testify: Uriah the priest, and Zechariah the son of Jeberechiah.”

3 I went to the prophetess, and she conceived, and bore a son. Then Yahweh said to me, “Call his name ‘Maher Shalal Hash Baz.’ 4 For before the child knows how to say, ‘My father,’ and, ‘My mother,’ the riches of Damascus and the plunder of Samaria will be carried away by the king of Assyria.”

5 Yahweh spoke to me yet again, saying, 6 “Because this people have refused the waters of Shiloah that go softly, and rejoice in Rezin and Remaliah’s son; 7 now therefore, behold, the Lord brings upon them the mighty flood waters of the River: the king of Assyria and all his glory. It will come up over all its channels, and go over all its banks. 8 It will sweep onward into Judah. It will overflow and pass through; it will reach even to the neck; and the stretching out of its wings will fill the width of your land, Immanuel. 9 Make an uproar, you peoples, and be broken in pieces! Listen, all you from far countries: dress for battle, and be shattered! Dress for battle, and be shattered! 10 Take counsel together, and it will be brought to nothing; speak the word, and it will not stand: for God is with us.” 11 For Yahweh spoke thus to me with a strong hand, and instructed me not to walk in the way of this people, saying, 12 “Don’t say, ‘A conspiracy!’ concerning all about which this people say, ‘A conspiracy!’ neither fear their threats, nor be terrorized. 13 Yahweh of Armies is who you must respect as holy. He is the one you must fear. He is the one you must dread. 14 He will be a sanctuary, but for both houses of Israel, he will be a trap and a snare for the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 15 Many will stumble over it, fall, be broken, be snared, and be captured.” 16 Wrap up the testimony. Seal the law among my disciples. 17 I will wait for Yahweh, who hides his face from the house of Jacob, and I will look for him. 18 Behold, I and the children whom Yahweh has given me are for signs and for wonders in Israel from Yahweh of Armies, who dwells in Mount Zion.

19 When they tell you, “Consult with those who have familiar spirits and with the wizards, who chirp and who mutter:” shouldn’t a people consult with their God? Should they consult the dead on behalf of the living? 20 Turn to the law and to the testimony! If they don’t speak according to this word, surely there is no morning for them. 21 They will pass through it, very distressed and hungry; and it will happen that when they are hungry, they will worry, and curse by their king and by their God. They will turn their faces upward, 22 and look to the earth, and see distress, darkness, and the gloom of anguish. They will be driven into thick darkness.

“Maher Shalal Hash Baz” means “quick to the plunder, swift to the prey”.

Isaiah 9

1 But there shall be no more gloom for her who was in anguish. In the former time, he brought into contempt the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali; but in the latter time he has made it glorious, by the way of the sea, beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations.

2 The people who walked in darkness have seen a great light.

Those who lived in the land of the shadow of death, on them the light has shined.

3 You have multiplied the nation.

You have increased their joy.

They rejoice before you according to the joy in harvest, as men rejoice when they divide the plunder. 4 For the yoke of his burden, and the staff of his shoulder, the rod of his oppressor, you have broken as in the day of Midian. 5 For all the armor of the armed man in the noisy battle, and the garments rolled in blood, will be for burning, fuel for the fire. 6 For to us a child is born. To us a son is given; and the government will be on his shoulders. His name will be called Wonderful, Counselor, Mighty God, Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace. 7 Of the increase of his government and of peace there shall be no end, on David’s throne, and on his kingdom, to establish it, and to uphold it with justice and with righteousness from that time on, even forever. The zeal of Yahweh of Armies will perform this.

8 The Lord sent a word into Jacob,

and it falls on Israel.

9 All the people will know,

including Ephraim and the inhabitants of Samaria, who say in pride and in arrogance of heart,

10 “The bricks have fallen,

but we will build with cut stone.

The sycamore fig trees have been cut down,

but we will put cedars in their place.”

11 Therefore Yahweh will set up on high against him the adversaries of Rezin,

and will stir up his enemies,

12 The Syrians in front,

and the Philistines behind;

and they will devour Israel with open mouth.

For all this, his anger is not turned away,

but his hand is stretched out still.

13 Yet the people have not turned to him who struck them,

neither have they sought Yahweh of Armies.

14 Therefore Yahweh will cut off from Israel head and tail,

palm branch and reed, in one day.

15 The elder and the honorable man is the head,

and the prophet who teaches lies is the tail.

16 For those who lead this people lead them astray;

and those who are led by them are destroyed.

17 Therefore the Lord will not rejoice over their young men,

neither will he have compassion on their fatherless and widows;

for everyone is profane and an evildoer,

and every mouth speaks folly.

For all this his anger is not turned away,

but his hand is stretched out still.

18 For wickedness burns like a fire.

It devours the briers and thorns;

yes, it kindles in the thickets of the forest,

and they roll upward in a column of smoke.

19 Through Yahweh of Armies’ wrath, the land is burned up;

and the people are the fuel for the fire.

No one spares his brother.

20 One will devour on the right hand, and be hungry;

and he will eat on the left hand, and they will not be satisfied.

Everyone will eat the flesh of his own arm:

21 Manasseh, Ephraim; and Ephraim, Manasseh; and they together shall be against Judah.

For all this his anger is not turned away,

but his hand is stretched out still.

Isaiah 10

1 Woe to those who decree unrighteous decrees, and to the writers who write oppressive decrees; 2 to deprive the needy from justice, and to rob the poor among my people of their rights, that widows may be their plunder, and that they may make the fatherless their prey! 3 What will you do in the day of visitation, and in the desolation which will come from afar? To whom will you flee for help? Where will you leave your wealth?

4 They will only bow down under the prisoners,

and will fall under the slain.

For all this his anger is not turned away,

but his hand is stretched out still.

5 Alas Assyrian, the rod of my anger, the staff in whose hand is my indignation! 6 I will send him against a profane nation, and against the people who anger me will I give him a command to take the plunder and to take the prey, and to tread them down like the mire of the streets. 7 However he doesn’t mean so, neither does his heart think so; but it is in his heart to destroy, and to cut off not a few nations. 8 For he says, “Aren’t all of my princes kings? 9 Isn’t Calno like Carchemish? Isn’t Hamath like Arpad? Isn’t Samaria like Damascus?” 10 As my hand has found the kingdoms of the idols, whose engraved images exceeded those of Jerusalem and of Samaria; 11 shall I not, as I have done to Samaria and her idols, so do to Jerusalem and her idols? 12 Therefore it will happen that, when the Lord has performed his whole work on Mount Zion and on Jerusalem, I will punish the fruit of the willful proud heart of the king of Assyria, and the insolence of his haughty looks. 13 For he has said, “By the strength of my hand I have done it, and by my wisdom; for I have understanding: and I have removed the boundaries of the peoples, and have robbed their treasures. Like a valiant man I have brought down their rulers. 14 My hand has found the riches of the peoples like a nest, and like one gathers eggs that are abandoned, I have gathered all the earth. There was no one who moved their wing, or that opened their mouth, or chirped.”

15 Should an ax brag against him who chops with it? Should a saw exalt itself above him who saws with it? As if a rod should lift those who lift it up, or as if a staff should lift up someone who is not wood. 16 Therefore the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, will send among his fat ones leanness; and under his glory a burning will be kindled like the burning of fire. 17 The light of Israel will be for a fire, and his Holy One for a flame; and it will burn and devour his thorns and his briers in one day. 18 He will consume the glory of his forest, and of his fruitful field, both soul and body. It will be as when a standard bearer faints. 19 The remnant of the trees of his forest shall be few, so that a child could write their number.

20 It will come to pass in that day that the remnant of Israel, and those who have escaped from the house of Jacob will no more again lean on him who struck them, but shall lean on Yahweh, the Holy One of Israel, in truth. 21 A remnant will return, even the remnant of Jacob, to the mighty God. 22 For though your people, Israel, are like the sand of the sea, only a remnant of them will return. A destruction is determined, overflowing with righteousness. 23 For the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, will make a full end, and that determined, throughout all the earth. 24 Therefore the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, says “My people who dwell in Zion, don’t be afraid of the Assyrian, though he strike you with the rod, and lift up his staff against you, as Egypt did. 25 For yet a very little while, and the indignation against you will be accomplished, and my anger will be directed to his destruction.” 26 Yahweh of Armies will stir up a scourge against him, as in the slaughter of Midian at the rock of Oreb. His rod will be over the sea, and he will lift it up like he did against Egypt. 27 It will happen in that day, that his burden will depart from off your shoulder, and his yoke from off your neck, and the yoke shall be destroyed because of the anointing oil.

28 He has come to Aiath. He has passed through Migron. At Michmash he stores his baggage. 29 They have gone over the pass. They have taken up their lodging at Geba. Ramah trembles. Gibeah of Saul has fled. 30 Cry aloud with your voice, daughter of Gallim! Listen, Laishah! You poor Anathoth! 31 Madmenah is a fugitive. The inhabitants of Gebim flee for safety. 32 This very day he will halt at Nob. He shakes his hand at the mountain of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem. 33 Behold, the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, will lop the boughs with terror. The tall will be cut down, and the lofty will be brought low. 34 He will cut down the thickets of the forest with iron, and Lebanon will fall by the Mighty One.

Isaiah 11

1 A shoot will come out of the stock of Jesse,

and a branch out of his roots will bear fruit.

2 Yahweh’s Spirit will rest on him:

the spirit of wisdom and understanding,

the spirit of counsel and might,

the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of Yahweh.

3 His delight will be in the fear of Yahweh.

He will not judge by the sight of his eyes,

neither decide by the hearing of his ears;

4 but with righteousness he will judge the poor,

and decide with equity for the humble of the earth.

He will strike the earth with the rod of his mouth;

and with the breath of his lips he will kill the wicked.

5 Righteousness will be the belt of his waist,

and faithfulness the belt of his waist.

6 The wolf will live with the lamb,

and the leopard will lie down with the young goat;

The calf, the young lion, and the fattened calf together;

and a little child will lead them.

7 The cow and the bear will graze.

Their young ones will lie down together.

The lion will eat straw like the ox.

8 The nursing child will play near a cobra’s hole,

and the weaned child will put his hand on the viper’s den.

9 They will not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain;

for the earth will be full of the knowledge of Yahweh,

as the waters cover the sea.

10 It will happen in that day that the nations will seek the root of Jesse, who stands as a banner of the peoples; and his resting place will be glorious. 11 It will happen in that day that the Lord will set his hand again the second time to recover the remnant that is left of his people from Assyria, from Egypt, from Pathros, from Cush, from Elam, from Shinar, from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea. 12 He will set up a banner for the nations, and will assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the dispersed of Judah from the four corners of the earth. 13 The envy also of Ephraim will depart, and those who persecute Judah will be cut off. Ephraim won’t envy Judah, and Judah won’t persecute Ephraim. 14 They will fly down on the shoulders of the Philistines on the west. Together they will plunder the children of the east. They will extend their power over Edom and Moab, and the children of Ammon will obey them. 15 Yahweh will utterly destroy the tongue of the Egyptian sea; and with his scorching wind he will wave his hand over the River, and will split it into seven streams, and cause men to march over in sandals. 16 There will be a highway for the remnant that is left of his people from Assyria, like there was for Israel in the day that he came up out of the land of Egypt.

Isaiah 13

1 The burden of Babylon, which Isaiah the son of Amoz saw: 2 Set up a banner on the bare mountain! Lift up your voice to them! Wave your hand, that they may go into the gates of the nobles. 3 I have commanded my consecrated ones; yes, I have called my mighty men for my anger, even my proudly exulting ones. 4 The noise of a multitude is in the mountains, as of a great people; the noise of an uproar of the kingdoms of the nations gathered together! Yahweh of Armies is mustering the army for the battle. 5 They come from a far country, from the uttermost part of heaven, even Yahweh, and the weapons of his indignation, to destroy the whole land. 6 Wail; for the day of Yahweh is at hand! It will come as destruction from the Almighty. 7 Therefore all hands will be feeble, and everyone’s heart will melt. 8 They will be dismayed. Pangs and sorrows will seize them. They will be in pain like a woman in labor. They will look in amazement one at another. Their faces will be faces of flame. 9 Behold, the day of Yahweh comes, cruel, with wrath and fierce anger; to make the land a desolation, and to destroy its sinners out of it. 10 For the stars of the sky and its constellations will not give their light. The sun will be darkened in its going out, and the moon will not cause its light to shine. 11 I will punish the world for their evil, and the wicked for their iniquity. I will cause the arrogance of the proud to cease, and will humble the haughtiness of the terrible. 12 I will make people more rare than fine gold, even a person than the pure gold of Ophir. 13 Therefore I will make the heavens tremble, and the earth will be shaken out of its place in Yahweh of Armies’ wrath, and in the day of his fierce anger. 14 It will happen that like a hunted gazelle, and like sheep that no one gathers, they will each turn to their own people, and will each flee to their own land. 15 Everyone who is found will be thrust through. Everyone who is captured will fall by the sword. 16 Their infants also will be dashed in pieces before their eyes. Their houses will be ransacked, and their wives raped. 17 Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, who will not value silver, and as for gold, they will not delight in it. 18 Their bows will dash the young men in pieces; and they shall have no pity on the fruit of the womb. Their eyes will not spare children. 19 Babylon, the glory of kingdoms, the beauty of the Chaldeans’ pride, will be like when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah. 20 It will never be inhabited, neither will it be lived in from generation to generation. The Arabian will not pitch a tent there, neither will shepherds make their flocks lie down there. 21 But wild animals of the desert will lie there, and their houses will be full of jackals. Ostriches will dwell there, and wild goats will frolic there. 22 Wolves will cry in their fortresses, and jackals in the pleasant palaces. Her time is near to come, and her days will not be prolonged.

Isaiah 15

1 The burden of Moab: for in a night, Ar of Moab is laid waste, and brought to nothing; for in a night Kir of Moab is laid waste, and brought to nothing. 2 They have gone up to Bayith, and to Dibon, to the high places, to weep. Moab wails over Nebo and over Medeba. Baldness is on all of their heads. Every beard is cut off. 3 In their streets, they clothe themselves in sackcloth. In their streets and on their housetops, everyone wails, weeping abundantly. 4 Heshbon cries out with Elealeh. Their voice is heard even to Jahaz. Therefore the armed men of Moab cry aloud. Their souls tremble within them. 5 My heart cries out for Moab! Her nobles flee to Zoar, to Eglath Shelishiyah; for they go up by the ascent of Luhith with weeping; for on the way to Horonaim, they raise up a cry of destruction. 6 For the waters of Nimrim will be desolate; for the grass has withered away, the tender grass fails, there is no green thing. 7 Therefore they will carry away the abundance they have gotten, and that which they have stored up, over the brook of the willows. 8 For the cry has gone around the borders of Moab; its wailing to Eglaim, and its wailing to Beer Elim. 9 For the waters of Dimon are full of blood; for I will bring yet more on Dimon, a lion on those of Moab who escape, and on the remnant of the land.

Isaiah 16

1 Send the lambs for the ruler of the land from Selah to the wilderness, to the mountain of the daughter of Zion. 2 For it will be that as wandering birds, as a scattered nest, so will the daughters of Moab be at the fords of the Arnon. 3 Give counsel! Execute justice! Make your shade like the night in the middle of the noonday! Hide the outcasts! Don’t betray the fugitive! 4 Let my outcasts dwell with you! As for Moab, be a hiding place for him from the face of the destroyer. For the extortionist is brought to nothing. Destruction ceases. The oppressors are consumed out of the land. 5 A throne will be established in loving kindness. One will sit on it in truth, in the tent of David, judging, seeking justice, and swift to do righteousness.

6 We have heard of the pride of Moab, that he is very proud; even of his arrogance, his pride, and his wrath. His boastings are nothing. 7 Therefore Moab will wail for Moab. Everyone will wail. You will mourn for the raisin cakes of Kir Hareseth, utterly stricken. 8 For the fields of Heshbon languish with the vine of Sibmah. The lords of the nations have broken down its choice branches, which reached even to Jazer, which wandered into the wilderness. Its shoots were spread abroad. They passed over the sea. 9 Therefore I will weep with the weeping of Jazer for the vine of Sibmah. I will water you with my tears, Heshbon, and Elealeh: for on your summer fruits and on your harvest the battle shout has fallen. 10 Gladness is taken away, and joy out of the fruitful field; and in the vineyards there will be no singing, neither joyful noise. Nobody will tread out wine in the presses. I have made the shouting stop. 11 Therefore my heart sounds like a harp for Moab, and my inward parts for Kir Heres. 12 It will happen that when Moab presents himself, when he wearies himself on the high place, and comes to his sanctuary to pray, that he will not prevail. 13 This is the word that Yahweh spoke concerning Moab in time past. 14 But now Yahweh has spoken, saying, “Within three years, as a worker bound by contract would count them, the glory of Moab shall be brought into contempt, with all his great multitude; and the remnant will be very small and feeble.”

Isaiah 17

1 The burden of Damascus: “Behold, Damascus is taken away from being a city, and it will be a ruinous heap. 2 The cities of Aroer are forsaken. They will be for flocks, which shall lie down, and no one shall make them afraid. 3 The fortress shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom from Damascus, and the remnant of Syria. They will be as the glory of the children of Israel,” says Yahweh of Armies. 4 “It will happen in that day that the glory of Jacob will be made thin, and the fatness of his flesh will become lean. 5 It will be like when the harvester gathers the wheat, and his arm reaps the grain. Yes, it will be like when one gleans grain in the valley of Rephaim. 6 Yet gleanings will be left there, like the shaking of an olive tree, two or three olives in the top of the uppermost bough, four or five in the outermost branches of a fruitful tree,” says Yahweh, the God of Israel. 7 In that day, people will look to their Maker, and their eyes will have respect for the Holy One of Israel. 8 They will not look to the altars, the work of their hands; neither shall they respect that which their fingers have made, either the Asherah poles, or the incense altars. 9 In that day, their strong cities will be like the forsaken places in the woods and on the mountain top, which were forsaken from before the children of Israel; and it will be a desolation. 10 For you have forgotten the God of your salvation, and have not remembered the rock of your strength. Therefore you plant pleasant plants, and set out foreign seedlings. 11 In the day of your planting, you hedge it in. In the morning, you make your seed blossom, but the harvest flees away in the day of grief and of desperate sorrow. 12 Ah, the uproar of many peoples, who roar like the roaring of the seas; and the rushing of nations, that rush like the rushing of mighty waters! 13 The nations will rush like the rushing of many waters: but he will rebuke them, and they will flee far off, and will be chased like the chaff of the mountains before the wind, and like the whirling dust before the storm. 14 At evening, behold, terror! Before the morning, they are no more. This is the portion of those who plunder us, and the lot of those who rob us.

Isaiah 19

1 The burden of Egypt: “Behold, Yahweh rides on a swift cloud, and comes to Egypt. The idols of Egypt will tremble at his presence; and the heart of Egypt will melt within it. 2 I will stir up the Egyptians against the Egyptians, and they will fight everyone against his brother, and everyone against his neighbor; city against city, and kingdom against kingdom. 3 The spirit of Egypt will fail within it. I will destroy its counsel. They will seek the idols, the charmers, those who have familiar spirits, and the wizards. 4 I will give over the Egyptians into the hand of a cruel lord. A fierce king will rule over them,” says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies. 5 The waters will fail from the sea, and the river will be wasted and become dry. 6 The rivers will become foul. The streams of Egypt will be diminished and dried up. The reeds and flags will wither away. 7 The meadows by the Nile, by the brink of the Nile, and all the sown fields of the Nile, will become dry, be driven away, and be no more. 8 The fishermen will lament, and all those who fish in the Nile will mourn, and those who spread nets on the waters will languish. 9 Moreover those who work in combed flax, and those who weave white cloth, will be confounded. 10 The pillars will be broken in pieces. All those who work for hire will be grieved in soul. 11 The princes of Zoan are utterly foolish. The counsel of the wisest counselors of Pharaoh has become stupid. How do you say to Pharaoh, “I am the son of the wise, the son of ancient kings?” 12 Where then are your wise men? Let them tell you now; and let them know what Yahweh of Armies has purposed concerning Egypt. 13 The princes of Zoan have become fools. The princes of Memphis are deceived. They have caused Egypt to go astray, who are the cornerstone of her tribes. 14 Yahweh has mixed a spirit of perverseness in the middle of her; and they have caused Egypt to go astray in all of its works, like a drunken man staggers in his vomit. 15 Neither shall there be any work for Egypt, which head or tail, palm branch or rush, may do. 16 In that day the Egyptians will be like women. They will tremble and fear because of the shaking of Yahweh of Armies’s hand, which he shakes over them. 17 The land of Judah will become a terror to Egypt. Everyone to whom mention is made of it will be afraid, because of the plans of Yahweh of Armies, which he determines against it. 18 In that day, there will be five cities in the land of Egypt that speak the language of Canaan, and swear to Yahweh of Armies. One will be called “The city of destruction.” 19 In that day, there will be an altar to Yahweh in the middle of the land of Egypt, and a pillar to Yahweh at its border. 20 It will be for a sign and for a witness to Yahweh of Armies in the land of Egypt; for they will cry to Yahweh because of oppressors, and he will send them a savior and a defender, and he will deliver them. 21 Yahweh will be known to Egypt, and the Egyptians will know Yahweh in that day. Yes, they will worship with sacrifice and offering, and will vow a vow to Yahweh, and will perform it. 22 Yahweh will strike Egypt, striking and healing. They will return to Yahweh, and he will be entreated by them, and will heal them. 23 In that day there will be a highway out of Egypt to Assyria, and the Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria; and the Egyptians will worship with the Assyrians. 24 In that day, Israel will be the third with Egypt and with Assyria, a blessing within the earth; 25 because Yahweh of Armies has blessed them, saying, “Blessed be Egypt my people, Assyria the work of my hands, and Israel my inheritance.”

Isaiah 21

1 The burden of the wilderness of the sea. As whirlwinds in the South sweep through, it comes from the wilderness, from an awesome land. 2 A grievous vision is declared to me. The treacherous man deals treacherously, and the destroyer destroys. Go up, Elam; attack! I have stopped all of Media’s sighing. 3 Therefore my thighs are filled with anguish. Pains have taken hold on me, like the pains of a woman in labor. I am in so much pain that I can’t hear. I so am dismayed that I can’t see. 4 My heart flutters. Horror has frightened me. The twilight that I desired has been turned into trembling for me. 5 They prepare the table. They set the watch. They eat. They drink. Rise up, you princes, oil the shield! 6 For the Lord said to me, “Go, set a watchman. Let him declare what he sees. 7 When he sees a troop, horsemen in pairs, a troop of donkeys, a troop of camels, he shall listen diligently with great attentiveness.” 8 He cried like a lion: “Lord, I stand continually on the watchtower in the daytime, and every night I stay at my post. 9 Behold, here comes a troop of men, horsemen in pairs.” He answered, “Fallen, fallen is Babylon; and all the engraved images of her gods are broken to the ground. 10 You are my threshing, and the grain of my floor!” That which I have heard from Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, I have declared to you.

11 The burden of Dumah. One calls to me out of Seir, “Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night?” 12 The watchman said, “The morning comes, and also the night. If you will inquire, inquire. Come back again.”

13 The burden on Arabia. In the forest in Arabia you will lodge, you caravans of Dedanites. 14 They brought water to him who was thirsty. The inhabitants of the land of Tema met the fugitives with their bread. 15 For they fled away from the swords, from the drawn sword, from the bent bow, and from the heat of battle. 16 For the Lord said to me, “Within a year, as a worker bound by contract would count it, all the glory of Kedar will fail, 17 and the residue of the number of the archers, the mighty men of the children of Kedar, will be few; for Yahweh, the God of Israel, has spoken it.”

Isaiah 22

1 The burden of the valley of vision. What ails you now, that you have all gone up to the housetops? 2 You that are full of shouting, a tumultuous city, a joyous town; your slain are not slain with the sword, neither are they dead in battle. 3 All your rulers fled away together. They were bound by the archers. All who were found by you were bound together. They fled far away. 4 Therefore I said, “Look away from me. I will weep bitterly. Don’t labor to comfort me for the destruction of the daughter of my people. 5 For it is a day of confusion, and of treading down, and of perplexity, from the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, in the valley of vision; a breaking down of the walls, and a crying to the mountains.” 6 Elam carried his quiver, with chariots of men and horsemen; and Kir uncovered the shield. 7 Your choicest valleys were full of chariots, and the horsemen set themselves in array at the gate. 8 He took away the covering of Judah; and you looked in that day to the armor in the house of the forest. 9 You saw the breaches of David’s city, that they were many; and you gathered together the waters of the lower pool. 10 You counted the houses of Jerusalem, and you broke down the houses to fortify the wall. 11 You also made a reservoir between the two walls for the water of the old pool. But you didn’t look to him who had done this, neither did you have respect for him who purposed it long ago. 12 In that day, the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, called to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldness, and to dressing in sackcloth: 13 and behold, joy and gladness, killing cattle and killing sheep, eating meat and drinking wine: “Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we will die.” 14 Yahweh of Armies revealed himself in my ears, “Surely this iniquity will not be forgiven you until you die,” says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies.

15 Thus says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, “Go, get yourself to this treasurer, even to Shebna, who is over the house, and say, 16 ‘What are you doing here? Who has you here, that you have dug out a tomb here?’ Cutting himself out a tomb on high, chiseling a habitation for himself in the rock!” 17 Behold, Yahweh will overcome you and hurl you away violently. Yes, he will grasp you firmly. 18 He will surely wind you around and around, and throw you like a ball into a large country. There you will die, and there the chariots of your glory will be, you shame of your lord’s house. 19 I will thrust you from your office. You will be pulled down from your station.

20 It will happen in that day that I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, 21 and I will clothe him with your robe, and strengthen him with your belt. I will commit your government into his hand; and he will be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to the house of Judah. 22 I will lay the key of David’s house on his shoulder. He will open, and no one will shut. He will shut, and no one will open. 23 I will fasten him like a nail in a sure place. He will be for a throne of glory to his father’s house. 24 They will hang on him all the glory of his father’s house, the offspring and the issue, every small vessel, from the cups even to all the pitchers. 25 “In that day,” says Yahweh of Armies, “the nail that was fastened in a sure place will give way. It will be cut down, and fall. The burden that was on it will be cut off, for Yahweh has spoken it.”

Isaiah 23

1 The burden of Tyre. Howl, you ships of Tarshish! For it is laid waste, so that there is no house, no entering in. From the land of Kittim it is revealed to them. 2 Be still, you inhabitants of the coast, you whom the merchants of Sidon, that pass over the sea, have replenished. 3 On great waters, the seed of the Shihor, the harvest of the Nile, was her revenue. She was the market of nations. 4 Be ashamed, Sidon; for the sea has spoken, the stronghold of the sea, saying, “I have not travailed, nor given birth, neither have I nourished young men, nor brought up virgins.” 5 When the report comes to Egypt, they will be in anguish at the report of Tyre. 6 Pass over to Tarshish! Wail, you inhabitants of the coast! 7 Is this your joyous city, whose antiquity is of ancient days, whose feet carried her far away to travel? 8 Who has planned this against Tyre, the giver of crowns, whose merchants are princes, whose traffickers are the honorable of the earth? 9 Yahweh of Armies has planned it, to stain the pride of all glory, to bring into contempt all the honorable of the earth. 10 Pass through your land like the Nile, daughter of Tarshish. There is no restraint any more. 11 He has stretched out his hand over the sea. He has shaken the kingdoms. Yahweh has ordered the destruction of Canaan’s strongholds. 12 He said, “You shall rejoice no more, you oppressed virgin daughter of Sidon. Arise, pass over to Kittim. Even there you will have no rest.”

13 Behold, the land of the Chaldeans. This people was not. The Assyrians founded it for those who dwell in the wilderness. They set up their towers. They overthrew its palaces. They made it a ruin. 14 Howl, you ships of Tarshish, for your stronghold is laid waste! 15 It will come to pass in that day that Tyre will be forgotten seventy years, according to the days of one king. After the end of seventy years it will be to Tyre like in the song of the prostitute. 16 Take a harp; go about the city, you prostitute that has been forgotten. Make sweet melody. Sing many songs, that you may be remembered. 17 It will happen after the end of seventy years that Yahweh will visit Tyre, and she shall return to her wages, and will play the prostitute with all the kingdoms of the world on the surface of the earth. 18 Her merchandise and her wages will be holiness to Yahweh. It will not be treasured nor laid up; for her merchandise will be for those who dwell before Yahweh, to eat sufficiently, and for durable clothing.

Isaiah 24

1 Behold, Yahweh makes the earth empty, makes it waste, turns it upside down, and scatters its inhabitants. 2 It will be as with the people, so with the priest; as with the servant, so with his master; as with the maid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the creditor, so with the debtor; as with the taker of interest, so with the giver of interest. 3 The earth will be utterly emptied and utterly laid waste; for Yahweh has spoken this word. 4 The earth mourns and fades away. The world languishes and fades away. The lofty people of the earth languish. 5 The earth also is polluted under its inhabitants, because they have transgressed the laws, violated the statutes, and broken the everlasting covenant. 6 Therefore the curse has devoured the earth, and those who dwell therein are found guilty. Therefore the inhabitants of the earth are burned, and few men left. 7 The new wine mourns. The vine languishes. All the merry-hearted sigh. 8 The mirth of tambourines ceases. The sound of those who rejoice ends. The joy of the harp ceases. 9 They will not drink wine with a song. Strong drink will be bitter to those who drink it. 10 The confused city is broken down. Every house is shut up, that no man may come in. 11 There is a crying in the streets because of the wine. All joy is darkened. The mirth of the land is gone. 12 The city is left in desolation, and the gate is struck with destruction. 13 For it will be so within the earth among the peoples, as the shaking of an olive tree, as the gleanings when the vintage is done. 14 These shall lift up their voice. They will shout for the majesty of Yahweh. They cry aloud from the sea. 15 Therefore glorify Yahweh in the east, even the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel, in the islands of the sea! 16 From the uttermost part of the earth have we heard songs. Glory to the righteous! But I said, “I pine away! I pine away! woe is me!” The treacherous have dealt treacherously. Yes, the treacherous have dealt very treacherously. 17 Fear, the pit, and the snare, are on you who inhabitant the earth. 18 It will happen that he who flees from the noise of the fear will fall into the pit; and he who comes up out of the middle of the pit will be taken in the snare; for the windows on high are opened, and the foundations of the earth tremble. 19 The earth is utterly broken. The earth is torn apart. The earth is shaken violently. 20 The earth will stagger like a drunken man, and will sway back and forth like a hammock. Its disobedience will be heavy on it, and it will fall and not rise again. 21 It shall happen in that day that Yahweh will punish the army of the high ones on high, and the kings of the earth on the earth. 22 They shall be gathered together, as prisoners are gathered in the pit, and shall be shut up in the prison; and after many days shall they be visited. 23 Then the moon shall be confounded, and the sun ashamed; for Yahweh of Armies will reign on Mount Zion, and in Jerusalem; and before his elders will be glory.

Isaiah 25

1 Yahweh, you are my God. I will exalt you! I will praise your name, for you have done wonderful things, things planned long ago, in complete faithfulness and truth. 2 For you have made a city into a heap, a fortified city into a ruin, a palace of strangers to be no city. It will never be built. 3 Therefore a strong people will glorify you. A city of awesome nations will fear you. 4 For you have been a stronghold to the poor, a stronghold to the needy in his distress, a refuge from the storm, a shade from the heat, when the blast of the dreaded ones is like a storm against the wall. 5 As the heat in a dry place will you bring down the noise of strangers; as the heat by the shade of a cloud, the song of the dreaded ones will be brought low. 6 In this mountain, Yahweh of Armies will make all peoples a feast of choice meat,[*] a feast of choice wines, of choice meat full of marrow, of well refined choice wines. 7 He will destroy in this mountain the surface of the covering that covers all peoples, and the veil that is spread over all nations. 8 He has swallowed up death forever! The Lord Yahweh will wipe away tears from off all faces. He will take the reproach of his people away from off all the earth, for Yahweh has spoken it. 9 It shall be said in that day, “Behold, this is our God! We have waited for him, and he will save us! This is Yahweh! We have waited for him. We will be glad and rejoice in his salvation!” 10 For in this mountain Yahweh’s hand will rest.

Moab will be trodden down in his place, even like straw is trodden down in the water of the dunghill. 11 He will spread out his hands in the middle of it, like one who swims spreads out hands to swim, but his pride will be humbled together with the craft of his hands. 12 He has brought the high fortress of your walls down, laid low, and brought to the ground, even to the dust.

literally, fat things

Isaiah 26

1 In that day, this song will be sung in the land of Judah:

“We have a strong city.

God appoints salvation for walls and bulwarks.

2 Open the gates, that the righteous nation may enter:

the one which keeps faith.

3 You will keep whoever’s mind is steadfast in perfect peace,

because he trusts in you.

4 Trust in Yahweh forever;

for in Yah, Yahweh, is an everlasting Rock.

5 For he has brought down those who dwell on high, the lofty city.

He lays it low.

He lays it low even to the ground.

He brings it even to the dust.

6 The foot shall tread it down;

Even the feet of the poor,

and the steps of the needy.”

7 The way of the just is uprightness.

You who are upright make the path of the righteous level.

8 Yes, in the way of your judgments, Yahweh, have we waited for you. Your name and your renown are the desire of our soul. 9 With my soul I have desired you in the night. Yes, with my spirit within me will I seek you earnestly; for when your judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world learn righteousness. 10 Let favor be shown to the wicked, yet he will not learn righteousness. In the land of uprightness he will deal wrongfully, and will not see Yahweh’s majesty. 11 Yahweh, your hand is lifted up, yet they don’t see; but they will see your zeal for the people, and be disappointed. Yes, fire will consume your adversaries. 12 Yahweh, you will ordain peace for us, for you have also done all our work for us. 13 Yahweh our God, other lords besides you have had dominion over us, but by you only will we make mention of your name. 14 The dead shall not live. The departed spirits shall not rise. Therefore you have visited and destroyed them, and caused all memory of them to perish. 15 You have increased the nation, O Yahweh. You have increased the nation! You are glorified! You have enlarged all the borders of the land. 16 Yahweh, in trouble they have visited you. They poured out a prayer when your chastening was on them. 17 Like as a woman with child, who draws near the time of her delivery, is in pain and cries out in her pangs; so we have been before you, Yahweh. 18 We have been with child. We have been in pain. We gave birth, it seems, only to wind. We have not worked any deliverance in the earth; neither have the inhabitants of the world fallen. 19 Your dead shall live. My dead bodies shall arise. Awake and sing, you who dwell in the dust; for your dew is like the dew of herbs, and the earth will cast out the departed spirits.

20 Come, my people, enter into your rooms, and shut your doors behind you. Hide yourself for a little moment, until the indignation is past. 21 For, behold, Yahweh comes out of his place to punish the inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity. The earth also will disclose her blood, and will no longer cover her slain.

Isaiah 27

1 In that day, Yahweh with his hard and great and strong sword will punish leviathan, the fleeing serpent, and leviathan the twisted serpent; and he will kill the dragon that is in the sea. 2 In that day, sing to her, “A pleasant vineyard! 3 I, Yahweh, am its keeper. I will water it every moment. Lest anyone damage it, I will keep it night and day. 4 Wrath is not in me, but if I should find briers and thorns, I would do battle! I would march on them and I would burn them together. 5 Or else let him take hold of my strength, that he may make peace with me. Let him make peace with me.”

6 In days to come, Jacob will take root. Israel will blossom and bud. They will fill the surface of the world with fruit. 7 Has he struck them as he struck those who struck them? Or are they killed like those who killed them were killed? 8 In measure, when you send them away, you contend with them. He has removed them with his rough blast in the day of the east wind. 9 Therefore by this the iniquity of Jacob will be forgiven, and this is all the fruit of taking away his sin: that he makes all the stones of the altar as chalk stones that are beaten in pieces, so that the Asherah poles and the incense altars shall rise no more. 10 For the fortified city is solitary, a habitation deserted and forsaken, like the wilderness. The calf will feed there, and there he will lie down, and consume its branches. 11 When its boughs are withered, they will be broken off. The women will come and set them on fire, for they are a people of no understanding. Therefore he who made them will not have compassion on them, and he who formed them will show them no favor. 12 It will happen in that day, that Yahweh will thresh from the flowing stream of the Euphrates to the brook of Egypt; and you will be gathered one by one, children of Israel. 13 It will happen in that day that a great trumpet will be blown; and those who were ready to perish in the land of Assyria, and those who were outcasts in the land of Egypt, shall come; and they will worship Yahweh in the holy mountain at Jerusalem.

Isaiah 29

1 Woe to Ariel! Ariel, the city where David encamped! Add year to year; let the feasts come around; 2 then I will distress Ariel, and there will be mourning and lamentation. She shall be to me as an altar hearth.[*] 3 I will encamp against you all around you, and will lay siege against you with posted troops. I will raise siege works against you. 4 You will be brought down, and will speak out of the ground. Your speech will mumble out of the dust. Your voice will be as of one who has a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and your speech will whisper out of the dust. 5 But the multitude of your foes will be like fine dust, and the multitude of the ruthless ones like chaff that blows away. Yes, it will be in an instant, suddenly. 6 She will be visited by Yahweh of Armies with thunder, with earthquake, with great noise, with whirlwind and storm, and with the flame of a devouring fire. 7 The multitude of all the nations that fight against Ariel, even all who fight against her and her stronghold, and who distress her, will be like a dream, a vision of the night. 8 It will be like when a hungry man dreams, and behold, he eats; but he awakes, and his hunger isn’t satisfied; or like when a thirsty man dreams, and behold, he drinks; but he awakes, and behold, he is faint, and he is still thirsty. The multitude of all the nations that fight against Mount Zion will be like that. 9 Pause and wonder! Blind yourselves and be blind! They are drunken, but not with wine; they stagger, but not with strong drink. 10 For Yahweh has poured out on you a spirit of deep sleep, and has closed your eyes, the prophets; and he has covered your heads, the seers. 11 All vision has become to you like the words of a book that is sealed, which men deliver to one who is educated, saying, “Read this, please”; and he says, “I can’t, for it is sealed:” 12 and the book is delivered to one who is not educated, saying, “Read this, please”; and he says, “I can’t read.” 13 The Lord said, “Because this people draws near with their mouth and with their lips to honor me, but they have removed their heart far from me, and their fear of me is a commandment of men which has been taught; 14 therefore, behold, I will proceed to do a marvelous work among this people, even a marvelous work and a wonder; and the wisdom of their wise men will perish, and the understanding of their prudent men will be hidden.”

15 Woe to those who deeply hide their counsel from Yahweh, and whose deeds are in the dark, and who say, “Who sees us?” and “Who knows us?” 16 You turn things upside down! Should the potter be thought to be like clay; that the thing made should say about him who made it, “He didn’t make me”; or the thing formed say of him who formed it, “He has no understanding?”

17 Isn’t it yet a very little while, and Lebanon will be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field will be regarded as a forest? 18 In that day, the deaf will hear the words of the book, and the eyes of the blind will see out of obscurity and out of darkness. 19 The humble also will increase their joy in Yahweh, and the poor among men will rejoice in the Holy One of Israel. 20 For the ruthless is brought to nothing, and the scoffer ceases, and all those who are alert to do evil are cut off— 21 who cause a person to be indicted by a word, and lay a snare for the arbiter in the gate, and who deprive the innocent of justice with false testimony. 22 Therefore Yahweh, who redeemed Abraham, says concerning the house of Jacob: “Jacob shall no longer be ashamed, neither shall his face grow pale. 23 But when he sees his children, the work of my hands, in the middle of him, they will sanctify my name. Yes, they will sanctify the Holy One of Jacob, and will stand in awe of the God of Israel. 24 They also who err in spirit will come to understanding, and those who grumble will receive instruction.”

or, Ariel

Isaiah 30

1 “Woe to the rebellious children”, says Yahweh, “who take counsel, but not from me; and who make an alliance, but not with my Spirit, that they may add sin to sin, 2 who set out to go down into Egypt, and have not asked my advice; to strengthen themselves in the strength of Pharaoh, and to take refuge in the shadow of Egypt! 3 Therefore the strength of Pharaoh will be your shame, and the refuge in the shadow of Egypt your confusion. 4 For their princes are at Zoan, and their ambassadors have come to Hanes. 5 They shall all be ashamed because of a people that can’t profit them, that are not a help nor profit, but a shame, and also a reproach.”

6 The burden of the animals of the South. Through the land of trouble and anguish, of the lioness and the lion, the viper and fiery flying serpent, they carry their riches on the shoulders of young donkeys, and their treasures on the humps of camels, to an unprofitable people. 7 For Egypt helps in vain, and to no purpose; therefore I have called her Rahab who sits still. 8 Now go, write it before them on a tablet, and inscribe it in a book, that it may be for the time to come forever and ever. 9 For it is a rebellious people, lying children, children who will not hear Yahweh’s law; 10 who tell the seers, “Don’t see!” and to the prophets, “Don’t prophesy to us right things. Tell us pleasant things. Prophesy deceits. 11 Get out of the way. Turn aside from the path. Cause the Holy One of Israel to cease from before us.” 12 Therefore thus says the Holy One of Israel, “Because you despise this word, and trust in oppression and perverseness, and rely on it; 13 therefore this iniquity shall be to you like a breach ready to fall, swelling out in a high wall, whose breaking comes suddenly in an instant. 14 He will break it as a potter’s vessel is broken, breaking it in pieces without sparing, so that there won’t be found among the broken piece a piece good enough to take fire from the hearth, or to dip up water out of the cistern.” 15 For thus said the Lord Yahweh, the Holy One of Israel, “You will be saved in returning and rest. Your strength will be in quietness and in confidence.” You refused, 16 but you said, “No, for we will flee on horses”; therefore you will flee; and, “We will ride on the swift”; therefore those who pursue you will be swift. 17 One thousand will flee at the threat of one. At the threat of five, you will flee until you are left like a beacon on the top of a mountain, and like a banner on a hill. 18 Therefore Yahweh will wait, that he may be gracious to you; and therefore he will be exalted, that he may have mercy on you, for Yahweh is a God of justice. Blessed are all those who wait for him. 19 For the people will dwell in Zion at Jerusalem. You will weep no more. He will surely be gracious to you at the voice of your cry. When he hears you, he will answer you. 20 Though the Lord may give you the bread of adversity and the water of affliction, yet your teachers won’t be hidden any more, but your eyes will see your teachers; 21 and when you turn to the right hand, and when you turn to the left, your ears will hear a voice behind you, saying, “This is the way. Walk in it.” 22 You shall defile the overlaying of your engraved images of silver, and the plating of your molten images of gold. You shall cast them away as an unclean thing. You shall tell it, “Go away!” 23 He will give the rain for your seed, with which you will sow the ground; and bread of the increase of the ground will be rich and plentiful. In that day, your livestock will feed in large pastures. 24 The oxen likewise and the young donkeys that till the ground will eat savory feed, which has been winnowed with the shovel and with the fork. 25 There shall be brooks and streams of water on every lofty mountain and on every high hill in the day of the great slaughter, when the towers fall. 26 Moreover the light of the moon will be like the light of the sun, and the light of the sun will be seven times brighter, like the light of seven days, in the day that Yahweh binds up the fracture of his people, and heals the wound they were struck with.

27 Behold, Yahweh’s name comes from far away, burning with his anger, and in thick rising smoke. His lips are full of indignation, and his tongue is as a devouring fire. 28 His breath is as an overflowing stream that reaches even to the neck, to sift the nations with the sieve of destruction; and a bridle that leads to ruin will be in the jaws of the peoples. 29 You will have a song, as in the night when a holy feast is kept; and gladness of heart, as when one goes with a flute to come to Yahweh’s mountain, to Israel’s Rock. 30 Yahweh will cause his glorious voice to be heard, and will show the descent of his arm, with the indignation of his anger, and the flame of a devouring fire, with a blast, storm, and hailstones. 31 For through Yahweh’s voice the Assyrian will be dismayed. He will strike him with his rod. 32 Every stroke of the rod of punishment, which Yahweh will lay on him, will be with the sound of tambourines and harps. He will fight with them in battles, brandishing weapons. 33 For his burning place has long been ready. Yes, for the king it is prepared. He has made its pyre deep and large with fire and much wood. Yahweh’s breath, like a stream of sulfur, kindles it.

Isaiah 31

1 Woe to those who go down to Egypt for help,

and rely on horses,

and trust in chariots because they are many,

and in horsemen because they are very strong,

but they don’t look to the Holy One of Israel,

and they don’t seek Yahweh!

2 Yet he also is wise, and will bring disaster,

and will not call back his words, but will arise against the house of the evildoers,

and against the help of those who work iniquity.

3 Now the Egyptians are men, and not God;

and their horses flesh, and not spirit.

When Yahweh stretches out his hand, both he who helps shall stumble,

and he who is helped shall fall,

and they all shall be consumed together.

4 For Yahweh says to me,

“As the lion and the young lion growling over his prey,

if a multitude of shepherds is called together against him,

will not be dismayed at their voice,

nor abase himself for their noise,

so Yahweh of Armies will come down to fight on Mount Zion and on its heights.

5 As birds hovering, so Yahweh of Armies will protect Jerusalem.

He will protect and deliver it.

He will pass over and preserve it.”

6 Return to him from whom you have deeply revolted, children of Israel. 7 For in that day everyone shall cast away his idols of silver and his idols of gold—sin which your own hands have made for you.

8 “The Assyrian will fall by the sword, not of man;

and the sword, not of mankind, shall devour him.

He will flee from the sword,

and his young men will become subject to forced labor.

9 His rock will pass away by reason of terror,

and his princes will be afraid of the banner,”

says Yahweh, whose fire is in Zion,

and his furnace in Jerusalem.

Isaiah 32

1 Behold, a king shall reign in righteousness,

and princes shall rule in justice.

2 A man shall be as a hiding place from the wind,

and a covert from the storm,

as streams of water in a dry place,

as the shade of a large rock in a weary land.

3 The eyes of those who see will not be dim,

and the ears of those who hear will listen.

4 The heart of the rash will understand knowledge,

and the tongue of the stammerers will be ready to speak plainly.

5 The fool will no longer be called noble,

nor the scoundrel be highly respected.

6 For the fool will speak folly,

and his heart will work iniquity,

to practice profanity,

and to utter error against Yahweh,

To make empty the soul of the hungry,

and to cause the drink of the thirsty to fail.

7 The ways of the scoundrel are evil.

He devises wicked devices to destroy the humble with lying words,

even when the needy speaks right.

8 But the noble devises noble things;

and he will continue in noble things.

9 Rise up, you women who are at ease! Hear my voice!

You careless daughters, give ear to my speech!

10 For days beyond a year you will be troubled, you careless women;

for the vintage shall fail.

The harvest won’t come.

11 Tremble, you women who are at ease!

Be troubled, you careless ones!

Strip yourselves, make yourselves naked,

and put sackcloth on your waist.

12 Beat your breasts for the pleasant fields,

for the fruitful vine.

13 Thorns and briers will come up on my people’s land;

yes, on all the houses of joy in the joyous city.

14 For the palace will be forsaken.

The populous city will be deserted.

The hill and the watchtower will be for dens forever,

a delight for wild donkeys,

a pasture of flocks;

15 Until the Spirit is poured on us from on high,

and the wilderness becomes a fruitful field,

and the fruitful field is considered a forest.

16 Then justice will dwell in the wilderness;

and righteousness will remain in the fruitful field.

17 The work of righteousness will be peace;

and the effect of righteousness, quietness and confidence forever.

18 My people will live in a peaceful habitation,

in safe dwellings,

and in quiet resting places.

19 Though hail flattens the forest,

and the city is leveled completely.

20 Blessed are you who sow beside all waters,

who send out the feet of the ox and the donkey.

Isaiah 33

1 Woe to you who destroy, but you weren’t destroyed;

and who betray, but nobody betrayed you!

When you have finished destroying, you will be destroyed;

and when you have finished betrayal, you will be betrayed.

2 Yahweh, be gracious to us. We have waited for you.

Be our strength every morning,

our salvation also in the time of trouble.

3 At the noise of the thunder, the peoples have fled.

When you lift yourself up, the nations are scattered.

4 Your plunder will be gathered as the caterpillar gathers.

Men will leap on it as locusts leap.

5 Yahweh is exalted, for he dwells on high.

He has filled Zion with justice and righteousness.

6 There will be stability in your times, abundance of salvation, wisdom, and knowledge.

The fear of Yahweh is your treasure.

7 Behold, their valiant ones cry outside;

the ambassadors of peace weep bitterly.

8 The highways are desolate.

The traveling man ceases.

The covenant is broken.

He has despised the cities.

He doesn’t respect man.

9 The land mourns and languishes.

Lebanon is confounded and withers away.

Sharon is like a desert, and Bashan and Carmel are stripped bare.

10 “Now I will arise,” says Yahweh;

“Now I will lift myself up.

Now I will be exalted.

11 You will conceive chaff.

You will give birth to stubble.

Your breath is a fire that will devour you.

12 The peoples will be like the burning of lime,

like thorns that are cut down and burned in the fire.

13 Hear, you who are far off, what I have done;

and, you who are near, acknowledge my might.”

14 The sinners in Zion are afraid.

Trembling has seized the godless ones.

Who among us can live with the devouring fire?

Who among us can live with everlasting burning?

15 He who walks righteously,

and speaks blamelessly;

He who despises the gain of oppressions,

who gestures with his hands, refusing to take a bribe,

who stops his ears from hearing of blood,

and shuts his eyes from looking at evil—

16 he will dwell on high.

His place of defense will be the fortress of rocks.

His bread will be supplied.

His waters will be sure.

17 Your eyes will see the king in his beauty.

They will see a distant land.

18 Your heart will meditate on the terror.

Where is he who counted?

Where is he who weighed?

Where is he who counted the towers?

19 You will no longer see the fierce people,

a people of a deep speech that you can’t comprehend,

with a strange language that you can’t understand.

20 Look at Zion, the city of our appointed festivals.

Your eyes will see Jerusalem, a quiet habitation,

a tent that won’t be removed.

Its stakes will never be plucked up,

nor will any of its cords be broken.

21 But there Yahweh will be with us in majesty,

a place of wide rivers and streams,

in which no galley with oars will go,

neither will any gallant ship pass by there.

22 For Yahweh is our judge.

Yahweh is our lawgiver.

Yahweh is our king.

He will save us.

23 Your rigging is untied.

They couldn’t strengthen the foot of their mast.

They couldn’t spread the sail.

Then the prey of a great plunder was divided.

The lame took the prey.

24 The inhabitant won’t say, “I am sick.”

The people who dwell therein will be forgiven their iniquity.

Isaiah 34

1 Come near, you nations, to hear!

Listen, you peoples.

Let the earth and all it contains hear;

the world, and everything that comes from it.

2 For Yahweh is enraged against all the nations,

and angry with all their armies.

He has utterly destroyed them.

He has given them over for slaughter.

3 Their slain will also be cast out,

and the stench of their dead bodies will come up;

and the mountains will melt in their blood.

4 All of the army of the sky will be dissolved.

The sky will be rolled up like a scroll,

and all its armies will fade away,

as a leaf fades from off a vine or a fig tree.

5 For my sword has drunk its fill in the sky.

Behold, it will come down on Edom,

and on the people of my curse, for judgment.

6 Yahweh’s sword is filled with blood.

It is covered with fat, with the blood of lambs and goats,

with the fat of the kidneys of rams;

for Yahweh has a sacrifice in Bozrah,

And a great slaughter in the land of Edom.

7 The wild oxen will come down with them,

and the young bulls with the mighty bulls;

and their land will be drunken with blood,

and their dust made greasy with fat.

8 For Yahweh has a day of vengeance,

a year of recompense for the cause of Zion.

9 Its streams will be turned into pitch,

its dust into sulfur,

And its land will become burning pitch.

10 It won’t be quenched night nor day.

Its smoke will go up forever.

From generation to generation, it will lie waste.

No one will pass through it forever and ever.

11 But the pelican and the porcupine will possess it.

The owl and the raven will dwell in it.

He will stretch the line of confusion over it,

and the plumb line of emptiness.

12 They shall call its nobles to the kingdom, but none shall be there;

and all its princes shall be nothing.

13 Thorns will come up in its palaces,

nettles and thistles in its fortresses;

and it will be a habitation of jackals,

a court for ostriches.

14 The wild animals of the desert will meet with the wolves,

and the wild goat will cry to his fellow.

Yes, the night creature[*] shall settle there,

and shall find herself a place of rest.

15 The arrow snake will make her nest there,

and lay, hatch, and gather under her shade.

Yes, the kites will be gathered there, every one with her mate.

16 Search in the book of Yahweh, and read:

not one of these will be missing.

none will lack her mate.

For my mouth has commanded,

and his Spirit has gathered them.

17 He has cast the lot for them,

and his hand has divided it to them with a measuring line.

They shall possess it forever.

From generation to generation they will dwell in it.

literally, lilith, which could also be a night demon or night monster

Isaiah 35

1 The wilderness and the dry land will be glad.

The desert will rejoice and blossom like a rose.

2 It will blossom abundantly,

and rejoice even with joy and singing.

Lebanon’s glory will be given to it,

the excellence of Carmel and Sharon.

They will see Yahweh’s glory,

the excellence of our God.

3 Strengthen the weak hands,

and make firm the feeble knees.

4 Tell those who have a fearful heart, “Be strong.

Don’t be afraid.

Behold, your God will come with vengeance, God’s retribution.

He will come and save you.

5 Then the eyes of the blind will be opened,

and the ears of the deaf will be unstopped.

6 Then the lame man will leap like a deer,

and the tongue of the mute will sing;

for waters will break out in the wilderness,

and streams in the desert.

7 The burning sand will become a pool,

and the thirsty ground springs of water.

Grass with reeds and rushes will be in the habitation of jackals, where they lay.

8 A highway will be there, a road,

and it will be called The Holy Way.

The unclean shall not pass over it,

but it will be for those who walk in the Way.

Wicked fools will not go there.

9 No lion will be there,

nor will any ravenous animal go up on it.

They will not be found there;

but the redeemed will walk there.

10 The Yahweh’s ransomed ones will return,

and come with singing to Zion;

and everlasting joy will be on their heads.

They will obtain gladness and joy,

and sorrow and sighing will flee away.”

Isaiah 36

1 Now in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, Sennacherib king of Assyria attacked all of the fortified cities of Judah, and captured them. 2 The king of Assyria sent Rabshakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem to king Hezekiah with a large army. He stood by the aqueduct from the upper pool in the fuller’s field highway. 3 Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph, the recorder came out to him. 4 Rabshakeh said to them, “Now tell Hezekiah, ‘Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria, “What confidence is this in which you trust? 5 I say that your counsel and strength for the war are only vain words. Now in whom do you trust, that you have rebelled against me? 6 Behold, you trust in the staff of this bruised reed, even in Egypt, which if a man leans on it, it will go into his hand and pierce it. So is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all who trust in him. 7 But if you tell me, ‘We trust in Yahweh our God,’ isn’t that he whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah has taken away, and has said to Judah and to Jerusalem, ‘You shall worship before this altar?’” 8 Now therefore, please make a pledge to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give you two thousand horses, if you are able on your part to set riders on them. 9 How then can you turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master’s servants, and put your trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? 10 Have I come up now without Yahweh against this land to destroy it? Yahweh said to me, “Go up against this land, and destroy it.”’”

11 Then Eliakim, Shebna and Joah said to Rabshakeh, “Please speak to your servants in Aramaic, for we understand it; and don’t speak to us in the Jews’ language in the hearing of the people who are on the wall.”

12 But Rabshakeh said, “Has my master sent me only to your master and to you, to speak these words, and not to the men who sit on the wall, who will eat their own dung and drink their own urine with you?” 13 Then Rabshakeh stood, and called out with a loud voice in the Jews’ language, and said, “Hear the words of the great king, the king of Assyria! 14 Thus says the king, ‘Don’t let Hezekiah deceive you; for he will not be able to deliver you. 15 Don’t let Hezekiah make you trust in Yahweh, saying, “Yahweh will surely deliver us. This city won’t be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.”’ 16 Don’t listen to Hezekiah, for thus says the king of Assyria, ‘Make your peace with me, and come out to me; and each of you eat from his vine, and each one from his fig tree, and each one of you drink the waters of his own cistern; 17 until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards. 18 Beware lest Hezekiah persuade you, saying, “Yahweh will deliver us.” Have any of the gods of the nations delivered their lands from the hand of the king of Assyria? 19 Where are the gods of Hamath and Arpad? Where are the gods of Sepharvaim? Have they delivered Samaria from my hand? 20 Who are they among all the gods of these countries that have delivered their country out of my hand, that Yahweh should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?’”

21 But they remained silent, and said nothing in reply, for the king’s commandment was, “Don’t answer him.”

22 Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph, the recorder, came to Hezekiah with their clothes torn, and told him the words of Rabshakeh.

Isaiah 37

1 When king Hezekiah heard it, he tore his clothes, covered himself with sackcloth, and went into Yahweh’s house. 2 He sent Eliakim, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz. 3 They said to him, “Thus says Hezekiah, ‘Today is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of rejection; for the children have come to the birth, and there is no strength to give birth. 4 It may be Yahweh your God will hear the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of Assyria his master has sent to defy the living God, and will rebuke the words which Yahweh your God has heard. Therefore lift up your prayer for the remnant that is left.’” 5 So the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah.

6 Isaiah said to them, “Tell your master, ‘Yahweh says, “Don’t be afraid of the words that you have heard, with which the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me. 7 Behold, I will put a spirit in him and he will hear news, and will return to his own land. I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

8 So Rabshakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah, for he had heard that he was departed from Lachish. 9 He heard news concerning Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, “He has come out to fight against you.” When he heard it, he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying, 10 “Thus you shall speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, ‘Don’t let your God in whom you trust deceive you, saying, “Jerusalem won’t be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.” 11 Behold, you have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands, by destroying them utterly. Shall you be delivered? 12 Have the gods of the nations delivered them, which my fathers have destroyed, Gozan, Haran, Rezeph, and the children of Eden who were in Telassar? 13 Where is the king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah?’”

14 Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers and read it. Then Hezekiah went up to Yahweh’s house, and spread it before Yahweh. 15 Hezekiah prayed to Yahweh, saying, 16 “Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, who is enthroned among the cherubim, you are the God, even you alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth. You have made heaven and earth. 17 Turn your ear, Yahweh, and hear. Open your eyes, Yahweh, and behold. Hear all of the words of Sennacherib, who has sent to defy the living God. 18 Truly, Yahweh, the kings of Assyria have destroyed all the countries and their land, 19 and have cast their gods into the fire; for they were no gods, but the work of men’s hands, wood and stone; therefore they have destroyed them. 20 Now therefore, Yahweh our God, save us from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you are Yahweh, even you only.”

21 Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, “Yahweh, the God of Israel says, ‘Because you have prayed to me against Sennacherib king of Assyria, 22 this is the word which Yahweh has spoken concerning him. The virgin daughter of Zion has despised you and ridiculed you. The daughter of Jerusalem has shaken her head at you. 23 Whom have you defied and blasphemed? Against whom have you exalted your voice and lifted up your eyes on high? Against the Holy One of Israel. 24 By your servants, have you defied the Lord, and have said, “With the multitude of my chariots I have come up to the height of the mountains, to the innermost parts of Lebanon. I will cut down its tall cedars and its choice cypress trees. I will enter into its farthest height, the forest of its fruitful field. 25 I have dug and drunk water, and with the sole of my feet I will dry up all the rivers of Egypt.” 26 Have you not heard how I have done it long ago, and formed it in ancient times? Now I have brought it to pass, that it should be yours to destroy fortified cities, turning them into ruinous heaps. 27 Therefore their inhabitants had little power. They were dismayed and confounded. They were like the grass of the field, and like the green herb, like the grass on the housetops, and like a field before its crop has grown. 28 But I know your sitting down, your going out, your coming in, and your raging against me. 29 Because of your raging against me, and because your arrogance has come up into my ears, therefore will I put my hook in your nose and my bridle in your lips, and I will turn you back by the way by which you came. 30 This shall be the sign to you. You will eat this year that which grows of itself, and in the second year that which springs from the same; and in the third year sow and reap and plant vineyards, and eat their fruit. 31 The remnant that is escaped of the house of Judah will again take root downward, and bear fruit upward. 32 For out of Jerusalem a remnant will go out, and survivors will escape from Mount Zion. The zeal of Yahweh of Armies will perform this.’ 33 Therefore Yahweh says concerning the king of Assyria, ‘He will not come to this city, nor shoot an arrow there, neither will he come before it with shield, nor cast up a mound against it. 34 By the way that he came, by the same he shall return, and he shall not come to this city,’ says Yahweh. 35 ‘For I will defend this city to save it, for my own sake, and for my servant David’s sake.’”

36 Yahweh’s angel went out and struck one hundred and eighty-five thousand men in the camp of the Assyrians. When men arose early in the morning, behold, these were all dead bodies. 37 So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, went away, returned to Nineveh, and stayed there. 38 As he was worshiping in the house of Nisroch his god, Adrammelech and Sharezer his sons struck him with the sword; and they escaped into the land of Ararat. Esar Haddon his son reigned in his place.

Isaiah 38

1 In those days was Hezekiah sick and near death. Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, came to him, and said to him, “Yahweh says, ‘Set your house in order, for you will die, and not live.’”

2 Then Hezekiah turned his face to the wall and prayed to Yahweh, 3 and said, “Remember now, Yahweh, I beg you, how I have walked before you in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in your sight.” Hezekiah wept bitterly.

4 Then Yahweh’s word came to Isaiah, saying, 5 “Go, and tell Hezekiah, ‘Yahweh says, the God of David your father, “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears. Behold, I will add fifteen years to your life. 6 I will deliver you and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria, and I will defend this city. 7 This shall be the sign to you from Yahweh, that Yahweh will do this thing that he has spoken. 8 Behold, I will cause the shadow on the sundial, which has gone down on the sundial of Ahaz with the sun, to return backward ten steps. So the sun returned ten steps on the sundial on which it had gone down.”’”

9 The writing of Hezekiah king of Judah, when he had been sick, and had recovered of his sickness.

10 I said, “In the middle of my life I go into the gates of Sheol.[*]

I am deprived of the residue of my years.”

11 I said, “I won’t see Yah,

Yah in the land of the living.

I will see man no more with the inhabitants of the world.

12 My dwelling is removed,

and is carried away from me like a shepherd’s tent.

I have rolled up, like a weaver, my life.

He will cut me off from the loom.

From day even to night you will make an end of me.

13 I waited patiently until morning.

He breaks all my bones like a lion.

From day even to night you will make an end of me.

14 I chattered like a swallow or a crane.

I moaned like a dove.

My eyes weaken looking upward.

Lord, I am oppressed.

Be my security.”

15 What will I say?

He has both spoken to me, and himself has done it.

I will walk carefully all my years because of the anguish of my soul.

16 Lord, men live by these things;

and my spirit finds life in all of them:

you restore me, and cause me to live.

17 Behold, for peace I had great anguish,

but you have in love for my soul delivered it from the pit of corruption;

for you have cast all my sins behind your back.

18 For Sheol[*] can’t praise you.

Death can’t celebrate you.

Those who go down into the pit can’t hope for your truth.

19 The living, the living, he shall praise you, as I do today.

The father shall make known your truth to the children.

20 Yahweh will save me.

Therefore we will sing my songs with stringed instruments all the days of our life in Yahweh’s house.

21 Now Isaiah had said, “Let them take a cake of figs, and lay it for a poultice on the boil, and he shall recover.” 22 Hezekiah also had said, “What is the sign that I will go up to Yahweh’s house?”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Isaiah 40

1 “Comfort, comfort my people,” says your God. 2 “Speak comfortably to Jerusalem; and call out to her that her warfare is accomplished, that her iniquity is pardoned, that she has received of Yahweh’s hand double for all her sins.”

3 The voice of one who calls out,

“Prepare the way of Yahweh in the wilderness!

Make a level highway in the desert for our God.

4 Every valley shall be exalted,

and every mountain and hill shall be made low.

The uneven shall be made level,

and the rough places a plain.

5 Yahweh’s glory shall be revealed,

and all flesh shall see it together;

for the mouth of Yahweh has spoken it.” 6 The voice of one saying, “Cry!”

One said, “What shall I cry?”

“All flesh is like grass,

and all its glory is like the flower of the field.

7 The grass withers,

the flower fades,

because Yahweh’s breath blows on it.

Surely the people are like grass.

8 The grass withers,

the flower fades;

but the word of our God stands forever.”

9 You who tell good news to Zion, go up on a high mountain.

You who tell good news to Jerusalem, lift up your voice with strength.

Lift it up. Don’t be afraid.

Say to the cities of Judah, “Behold, your God!”

10 Behold, the Lord Yahweh will come as a mighty one,

and his arm will rule for him.

Behold, his reward is with him,

and his recompense before him.

11 He will feed his flock like a shepherd.

He will gather the lambs in his arm,

and carry them in his bosom.

He will gently lead those who have their young.

12 Who has measured the waters in the hollow of his hand,

and marked off the sky with his span,

and calculated the dust of the earth in a measuring basket,

and weighed the mountains in scales,

and the hills in a balance?

13 Who has directed Yahweh’s Spirit,

or has taught him as his counselor?

14 Who did he take counsel with,

and who instructed him,

and taught him in the path of justice,

and taught him knowledge,

and showed him the way of understanding?

15 Behold, the nations are like a drop in a bucket,

and are regarded as a speck of dust on a balance.

Behold, he lifts up the islands like a very little thing.

16 Lebanon is not sufficient to burn,

nor its animals sufficient for a burnt offering.

17 All the nations are like nothing before him.

They are regarded by him as less than nothing, and vanity.

18 To whom then will you liken God?

Or what likeness will you compare to him?

19 A workman has cast an image,

and the goldsmith overlays it with gold,

and casts silver chains for it.

20 He who is too impoverished for such an offering chooses a tree that will not rot.

He seeks a skillful workman to set up an engraved image for him that will not be moved.

21 Haven’t you known?

Haven’t you heard, yet?

Haven’t you been told from the beginning?

Haven’t you understood from the foundations of the earth?

22 It is he who sits above the circle of the earth,

and its inhabitants are like grasshoppers;

who stretches out the heavens like a curtain,

and spreads them out like a tent to dwell in;

23 who brings princes to nothing;

who makes the judges of the earth like meaningless.

24 They are planted scarcely.

They are sown scarcely.

Their stock has scarcely taken root in the ground.

He merely blows on them, and they wither,

and the whirlwind takes them away as stubble.

25 “To whom then will you liken me?

Who is my equal?” says the Holy One.

26 Lift up your eyes on high,

and see who has created these,

who brings out their army by number.

He calls them all by name.

by the greatness of his might,

and because he is strong in power,

Not one is lacking.

27 Why do you say, Jacob,

and speak, Israel,

“My way is hidden from Yahweh,

and the justice due me is disregarded by my God?”

28 Haven’t you known?

Haven’t you heard?

The everlasting God, Yahweh,

The Creator of the ends of the earth, doesn’t faint.

He isn’t weary.

His understanding is unsearchable.

29 He gives power to the weak.

He increases the strength of him who has no might.

30 Even the youths faint and get weary,

and the young men utterly fall;

31 But those who wait for Yahweh will renew their strength.

They will mount up with wings like eagles.

They will run, and not be weary.

They will walk, and not faint.

Isaiah 41

1 “Keep silent before me, islands,

and let the peoples renew their strength.

Let them come near,

then let them speak.

Let’s meet together for judgment.

2 Who has raised up one from the east?

Who called him to his foot in righteousness?

He hands over nations to him,

and makes him rule over kings.

He gives them like the dust to his sword,

like the driven stubble to his bow.

3 He pursues them,

and passes by safely,

Even by a way that he had not gone with his feet.

4 Who has worked and done it,

calling the generations from the beginning?

I, Yahweh, the first, and with the last, I am he.”

5 The islands have seen, and fear.

The ends of the earth tremble.

They approach, and come.

6 Everyone helps his neighbor.

They say to their brothers, “Be strong!”

7 So the carpenter encourages the goldsmith.

He who smoothes with the hammer encourages him who strikes the anvil,

saying of the soldering, “It is good”;

and he fastens it with nails, that it might not totter.

8 “But you, Israel, my servant,

Jacob whom I have chosen,

the offspring[*] of Abraham my friend,

9 You whom I have taken hold of from the ends of the earth,

and called from its corners,

and said to you, ‘You are my servant, I have chosen you and not cast you away;’

10 Don’t you be afraid, for I am with you.

Don’t be dismayed, for I am your God.

I will strengthen you.

Yes, I will help you.

Yes, I will uphold you with the right hand of my righteousness.

11 Behold, all those who are incensed against you will be disappointed and confounded.

Those who strive with you will be like nothing, and shall perish.

12 You will seek them, and won’t find them,

even those who contend with you.

Those who war against you will be as nothing,

as a non-existent thing.

13 For I, Yahweh your God, will hold your right hand,

saying to you, ‘Don’t be afraid.

I will help you.’

14 Don’t be afraid, you worm Jacob,

and you men of Israel.

I will help you,” says Yahweh,

“and your Redeemer is the Holy One of Israel.

15 Behold, I have made you into a new sharp threshing instrument with teeth.

You will thresh the mountains,

and beat them small,

and will make the hills like chaff.

16 You will winnow them,

and the wind will carry them away,

and the whirlwind will scatter them.

You will rejoice in Yahweh.

You will glory in the Holy One of Israel.

17 The poor and needy seek water, and there is none.

Their tongue fails for thirst.

I, Yahweh, will answer them.

I, the God of Israel, will not forsake them.

18 I will open rivers on the bare heights,

and springs in the middle of the valleys.

I will make the wilderness a pool of water,

and the dry land springs of water.

19 I will put cedar, acacia, myrtle, and oil trees in the wilderness.

I will set cypress trees, pine, and box trees together in the desert;

20 that they may see, know, consider, and understand together,

that Yahweh’s hand has done this,

and the Holy One of Israel has created it.

21 Produce your cause,” says Yahweh.

“Bring out your strong reasons,” says the King of Jacob.

22 “Let them announce, and declare to us what shall happen.

Declare the former things, what they are,

that we may consider them, and know the latter end of them;

or show us things to come.

23 Declare the things that are to come hereafter,

that we may know that you are gods.

Yes, do good, or do evil,

that we may be dismayed,

and see it together.

24 Behold, you are of nothing,

and your work is of nothing.

He who chooses you is an abomination.

25 “I have raised up one from the north, and he has come;

from the rising of the sun, one who calls on my name;

and he shall come on rulers as on mortar,

and as the potter treads clay.

26 Who has declared it from the beginning, that we may know?

And before, that we may say, ‘He is right?’

Surely, there is no one who declares.

Surely, there is no one who shows.

Surely, there is no one who hears your words.

27 I am the first to say to Zion, ‘Behold, look at them;’

and I will give one who brings good news to Jerusalem.

28 When I look, there is no man;

even among them there is no counselor who, when I ask of them, can answer a word.

29 Behold, all of them, their deeds are vanity and nothing.

Their molten images are wind and confusion.

or, seed

Isaiah 42

1 “Behold, my servant, whom I uphold;

my chosen, in whom my soul delights—

I have put my Spirit on him.

He will bring justice to the nations.

2 He will not shout,

nor raise his voice,

nor cause it to be heard in the street.

3 He won’t break a bruised reed.

He won’t quench a dimly burning wick.

He will faithfully bring justice.

4 He will not fail nor be discouraged,

until he has set justice in the earth,

and the islands will wait for his law.”

5 Thus says God Yahweh,

he who created the heavens and stretched them out,

he who spread out the earth and that which comes out of it,

he who gives breath to its people and spirit to those who walk in it.

6 “I, Yahweh, have called you in righteousness,

and will hold your hand,

and will keep you,

and make you a covenant for the people,

as a light for the nations;

7 to open the blind eyes,

to bring the prisoners out of the dungeon,

and those who sit in darkness out of the prison.

8 “I am Yahweh.

That is my name.

I will not give my glory to another,

nor my praise to engraved images.

9 Behold, the former things have happened,

and I declare new things.

I tell you about them before they come up.”

10 Sing to Yahweh a new song,

and his praise from the end of the earth,

you who go down to the sea,

and all that is therein,

the islands and their inhabitants.

11 Let the wilderness and its cities raise their voices,

with the villages that Kedar inhabits.

Let the inhabitants of Sela sing.

Let them shout from the top of the mountains!

12 Let them give glory to Yahweh,

and declare his praise in the islands.

13 Yahweh will go out like a mighty man.

He will stir up zeal like a man of war.

He will raise a war cry.

Yes, he will shout aloud.

He will triumph over his enemies.

14 “I have been silent a long time.

I have been quiet and restrained myself.

Now I will cry out like a travailing woman. I will both gasp and pant.

15 I will destroy mountains and hills,

and dry up all their herbs.

I will make the rivers islands,

and will dry up the pools.

16 I will bring the blind by a way that they don’t know.

I will lead them in paths that they don’t know.

I will make darkness light before them,

and crooked places straight.

I will do these things,

and I will not forsake them.

17 “Those who trust in engraved images,

who tell molten images,

‘You are our gods’

will be turned back.

They will be utterly disappointed.

18 “Hear, you deaf,

and look, you blind,

that you may see.

19 Who is blind, but my servant?

Or who is as deaf as my messenger whom I send?

Who is as blind as he who is at peace,

and as blind as Yahweh’s servant?

20 You see many things, but don’t observe.

His ears are open, but he doesn’t listen.

21 It pleased Yahweh, for his righteousness’ sake, to magnify the law,

and make it honorable.

22 But this is a robbed and plundered people.

All of them are snared in holes,

and they are hidden in prisons.

They have become captives, and no one delivers;

and a plunder, and no one says, ‘Restore them!’

23 Who is there among you who will give ear to this?

Who will listen and hear for the time to come?

24 Who gave Jacob as plunder,

and Israel to the robbers?

Didn’t Yahweh, he against whom we have sinned?

For they would not walk in his ways,

and they disobeyed his law.

25 Therefore he poured the fierceness of his anger on him,

and the strength of battle;

and it set him on fire all around, but he didn’t know;

and it burned him, but he didn’t take it to heart.”

Isaiah 43

1 But now Yahweh who created you, Jacob,

and he who formed you, Israel says:

“Don’t be afraid, for I have redeemed you.

I have called you by your name.

You are mine.

2 When you pass through the waters, I will be with you;

and through the rivers, they will not overflow you.

When you walk through the fire, you will not be burned,

and flame will not scorch you.

3 For I am Yahweh your God,

the Holy One of Israel,

your Savior.

I have given Egypt as your ransom,

Ethiopia and Seba in your place.

4 Since you have been precious and honored in my sight,

and I have loved you;

therefore I will give people in your place,

and nations instead of your life.

5 Don’t be afraid; for I am with you.

I will bring your offspring[*] from the east,

and gather you from the west.

6 I will tell the north, ‘Give them up!’

and tell the south, ‘Don’t hold them back!

Bring my sons from far,

and my daughters from the ends of the earth—

7 everyone who is called by my name,

and whom I have created for my glory,

whom I have formed,

yes, whom I have made.’”

8 Bring out the blind people who have eyes,

and the deaf who have ears.

9 Let all the nations be gathered together,

and let the peoples be assembled.

Who among them can declare this,

and show us former things?

Let them bring their witnesses, that they may be justified;

or let them hear, and say, “That is true.”

10 “You are my witnesses,” says Yahweh,

“With my servant whom I have chosen;

that you may know and believe me,

and understand that I am he.

Before me there was no God formed,

neither will there be after me.

11 I myself am Yahweh;

and besides me there is no savior.

12 I have declared, I have saved, and I have shown;

and there was no strange god among you.

Therefore you are my witnesses”,

says Yahweh, “and I am God.

13 Yes, since the day was I am he;

and there is no one who can deliver out of my hand.

I will work, and who can hinder it?”

14 Yahweh, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel says: “For your sake, I have sent to Babylon, and I will bring all of them down as fugitives, even the Chaldeans, in the ships of their rejoicing. 15 I am Yahweh, your Holy One, the Creator of Israel, your King.”

16 Yahweh, who makes a way in the sea,

and a path in the mighty waters says:

17 who brings out the chariot and horse,

the army and the mighty man

(they lie down together, they shall not rise;

they are extinct, they are quenched like a wick):

18 “Don’t remember the former things,

and don’t consider the things of old.

19 Behold, I will do a new thing.

It springs out now.

Don’t you know it?

I will even make a way in the wilderness,

and rivers in the desert.

20 The animals of the field shall honor me,

the jackals and the ostriches;

because I give water in the wilderness and rivers in the desert,

to give drink to my people, my chosen,

21 the people which I formed for myself,

that they might declare my praise.

22 Yet you have not called on me, Jacob;

but you have been weary of me, Israel.

23 You have not brought me of your sheep for burnt offerings;

neither have you honored me with your sacrifices.

I have not burdened you with offerings,

nor wearied you with frankincense.

24 You have bought me no sweet cane with money,

nor have you filled me with the fat of your sacrifices;

but you have burdened me with your sins.

You have wearied me with your iniquities.

25 I, even I, am he who blots out your transgressions for my own sake;

and I will not remember your sins.

26 Put me in remembrance.

Let us plead together.

Declare your case,

that you may be justified.

27 Your first father sinned,

and your teachers have transgressed against me.

28 Therefore I will profane the princes of the sanctuary;

and I will make Jacob a curse,

and Israel an insult.”

or, seed

Isaiah 44

1 Yet listen now, Jacob my servant,

and Israel, whom I have chosen.

2 This is what Yahweh who made you,

and formed you from the womb,

who will help you says:

“Don’t be afraid, Jacob my servant;

and you, Jeshurun, whom I have chosen.

3 For I will pour water on him who is thirsty,

and streams on the dry ground.

I will pour my Spirit on your descendants,[*]

and my blessing on your offspring:

4 and they will spring up among the grass,

as willows by the watercourses.

5 One will say, ‘I am Yahweh’s;’

and another will be called by the name of Jacob;

and another will write with his hand ‘to Yahweh,’

and honor the name of Israel.”

6 This is what Yahweh, the King of Israel,

and his Redeemer, Yahweh of Armies, says:

“I am the first, and I am the last;

and besides me there is no God.

7 Who is like me?

Who will call,

and will declare it,

and set it in order for me,

since I established the ancient people?

Let them declare the things that are coming,

and that will happen.

8 Don’t fear,

neither be afraid.

Haven’t I declared it to you long ago,

and shown it?

You are my witnesses.

Is there a God besides me?

Indeed, there is not.

I don’t know any other Rock.”

9 Everyone who makes an engraved image is vain.

The things that they delight in will not profit.

Their own witnesses don’t see, nor know, that they may be disappointed.

10 Who has fashioned a god,

or molds an image that is profitable for nothing?

11 Behold, all his fellows will be disappointed;

and the workmen are mere men.

Let them all be gathered together.

Let them stand up.

They will fear.

They will be put to shame together.

12 The blacksmith takes an ax,

works in the coals,

fashions it with hammers,

and works it with his strong arm.

He is hungry,

and his strength fails;

he drinks no water,

and is faint.

13 The carpenter stretches out a line.

He marks it out with a pencil.

He shapes it with planes.

He marks it out with compasses,

and shapes it like the figure of a man,

with the beauty of a man,

to reside in a house.

14 He cuts down cedars for himself,

and takes the cypress and the oak,

and strengthens for himself one among the trees of the forest.

He plants a cypress tree,

and the rain nourishes it.

15 Then it will be for a man to burn;

and he takes some of it, and warms himself.

Yes, he burns it, and bakes bread.

Yes, he makes a god, and worships it;

he makes it an engraved image, and falls down to it.

16 He burns part of it in the fire.

With part of it, he eats meat.

He roasts a roast, and is satisfied.

Yes, he warms himself,

and says, “Aha! I am warm. I have seen the fire.”

17 The rest of it he makes into a god,

even his engraved image.

He bows down to it and worships,

and prays to it, and says, “Deliver me; for you are my god!”

18 They don’t know, neither do they consider:

for he has shut their eyes, that they can’t see;

and their hearts, that they can’t understand.

19 No one thinks,

neither is there knowledge nor understanding to say,

“I have burned part of it in the fire.

Yes, I have also baked bread on its coals.

I have roasted meat and eaten it.

Shall I make the rest of it into an abomination?

Shall I bow down to a tree trunk?”

20 He feeds on ashes.

A deceived heart has turned him aside;

and he can’t deliver his soul,

nor say, “Isn’t there a lie in my right hand?”

21 Remember these things, Jacob and Israel;

for you are my servant.

I have formed you.

You are my servant.

Israel, you will not be forgotten by me.

22 I have blotted out, as a thick cloud, your transgressions,

and, as a cloud, your sins.

Return to me, for I have redeemed you.

23 Sing, you heavens, for Yahweh has done it!

Shout, you lower parts of the earth!

Break out into singing, you mountains, O forest, all of your trees,

for Yahweh has redeemed Jacob,

and will glorify himself in Israel.

24 Yahweh, your Redeemer,

and he who formed you from the womb says:

“I am Yahweh, who makes all things;

who alone stretches out the heavens;

who spreads out the earth by myself;

25 who frustrates the signs of the liars,

and makes diviners mad;

who turns wise men backward,

and makes their knowledge foolish;

26 who confirms the word of his servant,

and performs the counsel of his messengers;

who says of Jerusalem, ‘She will be inhabited;’

and of the cities of Judah, ‘They will be built,’

and ‘I will raise up its waste places;’

27 who says to the deep, ‘Be dry,’

and ‘I will dry up your rivers;’

28 Who says of Cyrus, ‘He is my shepherd, and shall perform all my pleasure,’

even saying of Jerusalem, ‘She will be built;’

and of the temple, ‘Your foundation will be laid.’”

or, seed

Isaiah 45

1 Yahweh says to his anointed, to Cyrus, whose right hand I have held, to subdue nations before him, and strip kings of their armor; to open the doors before him, and the gates shall not be shut:

2 “I will go before you,

and make the rough places smooth.

I will break the doors of brass in pieces,

and cut apart the bars of iron.

3 I will give you the treasures of darkness,

and hidden riches of secret places,

that you may know that it is I, Yahweh, who call you by your name,

even the God of Israel.

4 For Jacob my servant’s sake,

and Israel my chosen,

I have called you by your name.

I have given you a title,

though you have not known me.

5 I am Yahweh, and there is no one else.

Besides me, there is no God.

I will strengthen[*] you,

though you have not known me;

6 that they may know from the rising of the sun,

and from the west,

that there is no one besides me.

I am Yahweh, and there is no one else.

7 I form the light,

and create darkness.

I make peace,

and create calamity.

I am Yahweh,

who does all these things.

8 Rain, you heavens, from above,

and let the skies pour down righteousness.

Let the earth open, that it may produce salvation,

and let it cause righteousness to spring up with it.

I, Yahweh, have created it.

9 Woe to him who strives with his Maker—

a clay pot among the clay pots of the earth!

Shall the clay ask him who fashions it, ‘What are you making?’

or your work, ‘He has no hands?’

10 Woe to him who says to a father, ‘What have you become the father of?’

or to a mother, ‘To what have you given birth?’”

11 Yahweh, the Holy One of Israel,

and his Maker says:

“You ask me about the things that are to come, concerning my sons,

and you command me concerning the work of my hands!

12 I have made the earth, and created man on it.

I, even my hands, have stretched out the heavens;

and I have commanded all their army.

13 I have raised him up in righteousness,

and I will make straight all his ways.

He shall build my city,

and he shall let my exiles go free,

not for price nor reward,” says Yahweh of Armies.

14 Yahweh says: “The labor of Egypt,

and the merchandise of Ethiopia,

and the Sabeans, men of stature, shall come over to you,

and they shall be yours.

They will go after you.

They shall come over in chains;

and they will bow down to you.

They will make supplication to you:

‘Surely God is in you; and there is no one else.

There is no other god.

15 Most certainly you are a God who has hidden yourself,

God of Israel, the Savior.’”

16 They will be disappointed,

yes, confounded, all of them.

Those who are makers of idols will go into confusion together.

17 Israel will be saved by Yahweh with an everlasting salvation.

You will not be disappointed nor confounded to ages everlasting.

18 For Yahweh who created the heavens,

the God who formed the earth and made it,

who established it and didn’t create it a waste,

who formed it to be inhabited says:

“I am Yahweh;

and there is no other.

19 I have not spoken in secret,

in a place of the land of darkness.

I didn’t say to the offspring[*] of Jacob, ‘Seek me in vain.’

I, Yahweh, speak righteousness.

I declare things that are right.

20 “Assemble yourselves and come.

Draw near together, you who have escaped from the nations.

Those have no knowledge who carry the wood of their engraved image,

and pray to a god that can’t save.

21 Declare and present it.

Yes, let them take counsel together.

Who has shown this from ancient time?

Who has declared it of old?

Haven’t I, Yahweh?

There is no other God besides me, a just God and a Savior;

There is no one besides me.

22 “Look to me, and be saved, all the ends of the earth;

for I am God, and there is no other.

23 I have sworn by myself.

The word has gone out of my mouth in righteousness, and will not be revoked,

that to me every knee shall bow,

every tongue shall take an oath.

24 They will say of me,

‘There is righteousness and strength only in Yahweh.’”

Even to him shall men come;

and all those who raged against him shall be disappointed.

25 All the offspring[*] of Israel will be justified in Yahweh,

and will rejoice!

or, equip

or, seed

or, seed

Isaiah 46

1 Bel bows down.

Nebo stoops.

Their idols are carried by animals,

and on the livestock.

The things that you carried around are heavy loads,

a burden for the weary.

2 They stoop and they bow down together.

They could not deliver the burden,

but they have gone into captivity.

3 “Listen to me, house of Jacob,

and all the remnant of the house of Israel,

that have been carried from their birth,

that have been carried from the womb.

4 Even to old age I am he,

and even to gray hairs I will carry you.

I have made, and I will bear.

Yes, I will carry, and will deliver.

5 “To whom will you liken me, and consider my equal,

and compare me, that we may be equal?

6 Some pour out gold from the bag,

and weigh silver in the balance.

They hire a goldsmith,

and he makes it a god.

They fall down—

yes, they worship.

7 They bear it on their shoulder.

They carry it, and set it in its place, and it stands there.

It cannot move from its place.

Yes, one may cry to it, yet it can not answer.

It cannot save him out of his trouble.

8 “Remember this, and show yourselves men.

Bring it to mind again, you transgressors.

9 Remember the former things of old:

for I am God, and there is no other.

I am God, and there is none like me.

10 I declare the end from the beginning,

and from ancient times things that are not yet done.

I say: My counsel will stand,

and I will do all that I please.

11 I call a ravenous bird from the east,

the man of my counsel from a far country.

Yes, I have spoken.

I will also bring it to pass.

I have planned.

I will also do it.

12 Listen to me, you stubborn-hearted,

who are far from righteousness!

13 I bring my righteousness near.

It is not far off,

and my salvation will not wait.

I will grant salvation to Zion,

my glory to Israel.

Isaiah 47

1 “Come down, and sit in the dust, virgin daughter of Babylon.

Sit on the ground without a throne, daughter of the Chaldeans.

For you will no longer be called tender and delicate.

2 Take the millstones, and grind flour.

Remove your veil, lift up your skirt, uncover your legs,

and wade through the rivers.

3 Your nakedness will be uncovered.

Yes, your shame will be seen.

I will take vengeance,

and will spare no one.”

4 Our Redeemer, Yahweh of Armies is his name,

is the Holy One of Israel.

5 “Sit in silence, and go into darkness,

daughter of the Chaldeans.

For you shall no longer be called

the mistress of kingdoms.

6 I was angry with my people.

I profaned my inheritance,

and gave them into your hand.

You showed them no mercy.

You laid a very heavy yoke on the aged.

7 You said, ‘I will be a princess forever;’

so that you did not lay these things to your heart,

nor did you remember the results.

8 “Now therefore hear this, you who are given to pleasures,

who sit securely,

who say in your heart,

‘I am, and there is no one else besides me.

I shall not sit as a widow,

neither shall I know the loss of children.’

9 But these two things shall come to you in a moment in one day,

the loss of children and widowhood.

They will come on you in their full measure,

in the multitude of your sorceries,

and the great abundance of your enchantments.

10 For you have trusted in your wickedness.

You have said, ‘No one sees me.’

Your wisdom and your knowledge has perverted you.

You have said in your heart, ‘I am, and there is no one else besides me.’

11 Therefore disaster will come on you.

You won’t know when it dawns.

Mischief will fall on you.

You won’t be able to put it away.

Desolation will come on you suddenly,

which you don’t understand.

12 “Stand now with your enchantments,

and with the multitude of your sorceries,

in which you have labored from your youth;

as if you might profit;

as if you might prevail.

13 You are wearied in the multitude of your counsels.

Now let the astrologers, the stargazers, and the monthly prognosticators, stand up and save you from the things that will come on you.

14 Behold, they are like stubble.

The fire will burn them.

They won’t deliver themselves from the power of the flame.

It won’t be a coal to warm at

or a fire to sit by.

15 The things that you labored in will be like this:

those who have trafficked with you from your youth will each wander in his own way.

There will be no one to save you.

Isaiah 48

1 “Hear this, house of Jacob,

you who are called by the name of Israel,

and have come out of the waters of Judah.

You swear by Yahweh’s name,

and make mention of the God of Israel,

but not in truth, nor in righteousness

2 (for they call themselves citizens of the holy city,

and rely on the God of Israel;

Yahweh of Armies is his name):

3 I have declared the former things from of old;

yes, they went out of my mouth, and I revealed them.

I did them suddenly, and they happened.

4 Because I knew that you are obstinate,

and your neck is an iron sinew,

and your brow brass;

5 therefore I have declared it to you from of old;

before it came to pass I showed it to you;

lest you should say, ‘My idol has done them, and my engraved image, and my molten image, has commanded them.’

6 You have heard it;

see all this.

And you, won’t you declare it?

“I have shown you new things from this time,

even hidden things, which you have not known.

7 They are created now, and not from of old;

and before today you didn’t hear them;

lest you should say, ‘Behold, I knew them.’

8 Yes, you didn’t hear;

yes, you didn’t know;

yes, from of old your ear was not opened:

for I knew that you dealt very treacherously,

and were called a transgressor from the womb.

9 For my name’s sake, I will defer my anger,

and for my praise I hold it back for you,

so that I don’t cut you off.

10 Behold, I have refined you,

but not as silver.

I have chosen you in the furnace of affliction.

11 For my own sake,

for my own sake, I will do it;

for how would my name be profaned?

I will not give my glory to another.

12 “Listen to me, O Jacob,

and Israel my called:

I am he;

I am the first,

I am also the last.

13 Yes, my hand has laid the foundation of the earth,

and my right hand has spread out the heavens.

when I call to them, they stand up together.

14 “Assemble yourselves, all of you, and hear;

who among them has declared these things?

He whom Yahweh loves will do what he likes to Babylon,

and his arm will be against the Chaldeans.

15 I, even I, have spoken;

yes, I have called him.

I have brought him,

and he shall make his way prosperous.

16 “Come near to me and hear this:

“From the beginning I have not spoken in secret;

from the time that it happened, I was there.”

Now the Lord Yahweh has sent me,

with his Spirit.

17 Yahweh,

your Redeemer,

the Holy One of Israel says:

“I am Yahweh your God,

who teaches you to profit,

who leads you by the way that you should go.

18 Oh that you had listened to my commandments!

Then your peace would have been like a river,

and your righteousness like the waves of the sea.

19 Your offspring[*] also would have been as the sand,

and the descendants of your body like its grains.

His name would not be cut off nor destroyed from before me.”

20 Leave Babylon!

Flee from the Chaldeans!

With a voice of singing announce this,

tell it even to the end of the earth:

say, “Yahweh has redeemed his servant Jacob!”

21 They didn’t thirst when he led them through the deserts.

He caused the waters to flow out of the rock for them.

He split the rock also, and the waters gushed out.

22 “There is no peace”, says Yahweh, “for the wicked.”

or, seed

Isaiah 49

1 Listen, islands, to me.

Listen, you peoples, from afar:

Yahweh has called me from the womb;

from the inside of my mother he has mentioned my name.

2 He has made my mouth like a sharp sword.

He has hidden me in the shadow of his hand.

He has made me a polished shaft.

He has kept me close in his quiver.

3 He said to me, “You are my servant;

Israel, in whom I will be glorified.”

4 But I said, “I have labored in vain.

I have spent my strength in vain for nothing;

yet surely the justice due to me is with Yahweh,

and my reward with my God.”

5 Now Yahweh says, he who formed me from the womb to be his servant,

to bring Jacob again to him,

and to gather Israel to him,

for I am honorable in Yahweh’s eyes,

and my God has become my strength.

6 Indeed, he says, “It is too light a thing that you should be my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob,

and to restore the preserved of Israel?

I will also give you as a light to the nations,

that you may be my salvation to the end of the earth.”

7 Yahweh, the Redeemer of Israel, and his Holy One,

says to him whom man despises, to him whom the nation abhors, to a servant of rulers:

“Kings shall see and rise up;

princes, and they shall worship;

because of Yahweh who is faithful, even the Holy One of Israel, who has chosen you.”

8 Yahweh says, “In an acceptable time I have answered you,

and in a day of salvation I have helped you.

I will preserve you, and give you for a covenant of the people,

to raise up the land, to make them inherit the desolate heritage:

9 saying to those who are bound, ‘Come out!’;

to those who are in darkness, ‘Show yourselves!’

“They shall feed along the paths,

and their pasture shall be on all treeless heights.

10 They shall not hunger nor thirst;

neither shall the heat nor sun strike them:

for he who has mercy on them will lead them.

He will guide them by springs of water.

11 I will make all my mountains a road,

and my highways shall be exalted.

12 Behold, these shall come from afar;

and behold, these from the north and from the west;

and these from the land of Sinim.”

13 Sing, heavens; and be joyful, earth;

and break out into singing, mountains:

for Yahweh has comforted his people,

and will have compassion on his afflicted.

14 But Zion said, “Yahweh has forsaken me,

and the Lord has forgotten me.”

15 “Can a woman forget her nursing child,

that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb?

Yes, these may forget,

yet I will not forget you!

16 Behold, I have engraved you on the palms of my hands.

your walls are continually before me.

17 Your children hurry.

Your destroyers and those who devastated you will leave you.

18 Lift up your eyes all around, and see:

all these gather themselves together, and come to you.

As I live,” says Yahweh, “you shall surely clothe yourself with them all as with an ornament,

and dress yourself with them, like a bride.

19 “For, as for your waste and your desolate places,

and your land that has been destroyed,

surely now that land will be too small for the inhabitants,

and those who swallowed you up will be far away.

20 The children of your bereavement will say in your ears,

‘This place is too small for me.

Give me a place to live in.’

21 Then you will say in your heart, ‘Who has conceived these for me, since I have been bereaved of my children,

and am solitary, an exile, and wandering back and forth?

Who has brought these up?

Behold, I was left alone. Where were these?’”

22 Thus says the Lord Yahweh, “Behold, I will lift up my hand to the nations,

and lift up my banner to the peoples;

and they shall bring your sons in their bosom,

and your daughters shall be carried on their shoulders.

23 Kings shall be your foster fathers,

and their queens your nursing mothers.

They will bow down to you with their faces to the earth,

and lick the dust of your feet;

Then you will know that I am Yahweh;

and those who wait for me shall not be disappointed.”

24 Shall the plunder be taken from the mighty,

or the lawful captives be delivered?

25 But Yahweh says, “Even the captives of the mighty shall be taken away,

and the plunder retrieved from the fierce;

for I will contend with him who contends with you,

and I will save your children.

26 I will feed those who oppress you with their own flesh;

and they will be drunk on their own blood, as with sweet wine.

Then all flesh shall know that I, Yahweh, am your Savior,

and your Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob.”

Isaiah 50

1 Yahweh says, “Where is the bill of your mother’s divorce, with which I have put her away?

or to which of my creditors have I sold you?

Behold, you were sold for your iniquities,

and your mother was put away for your transgressions.

2 Why, when I came, was there no one?

when I called, why was there no one to answer?

Is my hand shortened at all, that it can’t redeem?

or have I no power to deliver?

Behold, at my rebuke I dry up the sea.

I make the rivers a wilderness:

their fish stink, because there is no water, and die for thirst.

3 I clothe the heavens with blackness,

and I make sackcloth their covering.”

4 The Lord Yahweh has given me the tongue of those who are taught,

that I may know how to sustain with words him who is weary.

He wakens morning by morning,

he wakens my ear to hear as those who are taught.

5 The Lord Yahweh has opened my ear,

and I was not rebellious.

I have not turned back.

6 I gave my back to those who beat me,

and my cheeks to those who plucked off the hair.

I didn’t hide my face from shame and spitting.

7 For the Lord Yahweh will help me.

Therefore I have not been confounded.

Therefore I have set my face like a flint,

and I know that I shall not be disappointed.

8 He who justifies me is near.

Who will bring charges against me?

Let us stand up together.

Who is my adversary?

Let him come near to me.

9 Behold, the Lord Yahweh will help me!

Who is he who will condemn me?

Behold, they will all grow old like a garment.

The moths will eat them up.

10 Who among you fears Yahweh,

and obeys the voice of his servant?

He who walks in darkness,

and has no light,

let him trust in Yahweh’s name,

and rely on his God.

11 Behold, all you who kindle a fire,

who adorn yourselves with torches around yourselves;

walk in the flame of your fire,

and among the torches that you have kindled.

You will have this from my hand:

You will lie down in sorrow.

Isaiah 51

1 “Listen to me, you who follow after righteousness,

you who seek Yahweh:

look to the rock you were cut from,

and to the quarry you were dug from.

2 Look to Abraham your father,

and to Sarah who bore you;

for when he was but one I called him,

and I blessed him,

and made him many.

3 For Yahweh has comforted Zion.

He has comforted all her waste places,

and has made her wilderness like Eden,

and her desert like the garden of Yahweh.

Joy and gladness will be found therein,

thanksgiving, and the voice of melody.

4 “Listen to me, my people;

and hear me, my nation:

for a law will go out from me,

and I will establish my justice for a light to the peoples.

5 My righteousness is near.

My salvation has gone out,

and my arms will judge the peoples.

The islands will wait for me,

and they will trust my arm.

6 Lift up your eyes to the heavens,

and look on the earth beneath;

for the heavens will vanish away like smoke,

and the earth will wear out like a garment;

and its inhabitants will die in the same way:

but my salvation will be forever,

and my righteousness will not be abolished.

7 “Listen to me, you who know righteousness,

the people in whose heart is my law:

Don’t fear the reproach of men,

and don’t be dismayed at their insults.

8 For the moth will eat them up like a garment,

and the worm will eat them like wool;

but my righteousness will be forever,

and my salvation to all generations.”

9 Awake, awake, put on strength, arm of Yahweh!

Awake, as in the days of old,

the generations of ancient times.

Isn’t it you who cut Rahab in pieces,

who pierced the monster?

10 Isn’t it you who dried up the sea,

the waters of the great deep;

who made the depths of the sea a way for the redeemed to pass over?

11 Those ransomed by Yahweh will return,

and come with singing to Zion;

and everlasting joy shall be on their heads.

They will obtain gladness and joy.

Sorrow and sighing shall flee away.

12 “I, even I, am he who comforts you.

Who are you, that you are afraid of man who shall die,

and of the son of man who will be made as grass?

13 Have you forgotten Yahweh your Maker,

who stretched out the heavens,

and laid the foundations of the earth?

Do you live in fear continually all day because of the fury of the oppressor,

when he prepares to destroy?

Where is the fury of the oppressor?

14 The captive exile will speedily be freed;

and he will not die and go down into the pit,

and his bread will not fail.

15 For I am Yahweh your God, who stirs up the sea,

so that its waves roar:

Yahweh of Armies is his name.

16 I have put my words in your mouth,

and have covered you in the shadow of my hand,

that I may plant the heavens,

and lay the foundations of the earth,

and tell Zion, ‘You are my people.’”

17 Awake, awake!

Stand up, Jerusalem,

you who have drunk from Yahweh’s hand the cup of his wrath.

You have drunken the bowl of the cup of staggering,

and drained it.

18 There is no one to guide her among all the sons to whom she has given birth;

and there is no one who takes her by the hand among all the sons who she has brought up.

19 These two things have happened to you—

who will grieve with you?—

desolation and destruction,

and famine and the sword.

How can I comfort you?

20 Your sons have fainted.

They lie at the head of all the streets,

like an antelope in a net.

They are full of the Yahweh’s wrath,

the rebuke of your God.

21 Therefore now hear this, you afflicted,

and drunken, but not with wine:

22 Thus says your Lord Yahweh,

your God who pleads the cause of his people,

“Behold, I have taken out of your hand the cup of staggering,

even the bowl of the cup of my wrath.

You will not drink it any more:

23 and I will put it into the hand of those who afflict you,

who have said to your soul, ‘Bow down, that we may walk over you;’

and you have laid your back as the ground,

like a street to those who walk over.”

Isaiah 52

1 Awake, awake! Put on your strength, Zion.

Put on your beautiful garments, Jerusalem, the holy city:

for from now on the uncircumcised and the unclean will no more come into you.

2 Shake yourself from the dust!

Arise, sit up, Jerusalem!

Release yourself from the bonds of your neck, captive daughter of Zion!

3 For Yahweh says, “You were sold for nothing;

and you will be redeemed without money.”

4 For thus says the Lord Yahweh:

“My people went down at the first into Egypt to live there:

and the Assyrian has oppressed them without cause.

5 “Now therefore, what do I do here,” says Yahweh,

“seeing that my people are taken away for nothing?

Those who rule over them mock,” says Yahweh,

“and my name is blasphemed continually all day long.

6 Therefore my people shall know my name.

Therefore they shall know in that day that I am he who speaks.

Behold, it is I.”

7 How beautiful on the mountains are the feet of him who brings good news,

who publishes peace,

who brings good news,

who proclaims salvation,

who says to Zion, “Your God reigns!”

8 Your watchmen lift up their voice,

together they sing;

for they shall see eye to eye, when Yahweh returns to Zion.

9 Break out into joy,

sing together, you waste places of Jerusalem;

for Yahweh has comforted his people.

He has redeemed Jerusalem.

10 Yahweh has made bare his holy arm in the eyes of all the nations;

and all the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God.

11 Depart, depart, go out from there; touch no unclean thing!

Go out from among her!

Cleanse yourselves, you who carry Yahweh’s vessels.

12 For you shall not go out in haste,

neither shall you go by flight:

for Yahweh will go before you;

and the God of Israel will be your rear guard.

13 Behold, my servant will deal wisely.

He will be exalted and lifted up,

and will be very high.

14 Just as many were astonished at you

(his appearance was marred more than any man, and his form more than the sons of men),

15 so he will cleanse[*] many nations.

Kings will shut their mouths at him:

for they will see that which had not been told them;

and they will understand that which they had not heard.

or, sprinkle

Isaiah 53

1 Who has believed our message?

To whom has the arm of Yahweh been revealed?

2 For he grew up before him as a tender plant,

and as a root out of dry ground.

He has no good looks or majesty.

When we see him, there is no beauty that we should desire him.

3 He was despised,

and rejected by men;

a man of suffering,

and acquainted with disease.

He was despised as one from whom men hide their face;

and we didn’t respect him.

4 Surely he has borne our sickness,

and carried our suffering;

yet we considered him plagued,

struck by God, and afflicted.

5 But he was pierced for our transgressions.

He was crushed for our iniquities.

The punishment that brought our peace was on him;

and by his wounds we are healed.

6 All we like sheep have gone astray.

Everyone has turned to his own way;

and Yahweh has laid on him the iniquity of us all.

7 He was oppressed,

yet when he was afflicted he didn’t open his mouth.

As a lamb that is led to the slaughter,

and as a sheep that before its shearers is silent,

so he didn’t open his mouth.

8 He was taken away by oppression and judgment;

and as for his generation,

who considered that he was cut off out of the land of the living

and stricken for the disobedience of my people?

9 They made his grave with the wicked,

and with a rich man in his death;

although he had done no violence,

nor was any deceit in his mouth.

10 Yet it pleased Yahweh to bruise him.

He has caused him to suffer.

When you make his soul an offering for sin,

he will see his offspring.[*]

He will prolong his days,

and Yahweh’s pleasure will prosper in his hand.

11 After the suffering of his soul,

he will see the light[*] and be satisfied.

My righteous servant will justify many by the knowledge of himself;

and he will bear their iniquities.

12 Therefore will I give him a portion with the great,

and he will divide the plunder with the strong;

because he poured out his soul to death,

and was counted with the transgressors;

yet he bore the sin of many,

and made intercession for the transgressors.

or, seed

So read the Dead Sea Scrolls and Septuagint. Masoretic Text omits “the light”.

Isaiah 54

1 “Sing, barren, you who didn’t give birth;

break out into singing, and cry aloud, you who did not travail with child:

for more are the children of the desolate than the children of the married wife,” says Yahweh.

2 “Enlarge the place of your tent,

and let them stretch out the curtains of your habitations;

don’t spare: lengthen your cords, and strengthen your stakes.

3 For you will spread out on the right hand and on the left;

and your offspring[*] will possess the nations,

and settle in desolate cities.

4 “Don’t be afraid; for you will not be ashamed.

Don’t be confounded; for you will not be disappointed.

For you will forget the shame of your youth;

and the reproach of your widowhood you shall remember no more.

5 For your Maker is your husband; Yahweh of Armies is his name.

The Holy One of Israel is your Redeemer.

He will be called the God of the whole earth.

6 For Yahweh has called you as a wife forsaken and grieved in spirit,

even a wife of youth, when she is cast off,” says your God.

7 “For a small moment I have forsaken you;

but with great mercies will I gather you.

8 In overflowing wrath I hid my face from you for a moment;

but with everlasting loving kindness I will have mercy on you,” says Yahweh your Redeemer.

9 “For this is like the waters of Noah to me;

for as I have sworn that the waters of Noah will no more go over the earth,

so I have sworn that I will not be angry with you, nor rebuke you.

10 For the mountains may depart,

and the hills be removed;

but my loving kindness will not depart from you,

and my covenant of peace will not be removed,”

says Yahweh who has mercy on you.

11 “You afflicted, tossed with storms, and not comforted,

behold, I will set your stones in beautiful colors,

and lay your foundations with sapphires.

12 I will make your pinnacles of rubies,

your gates of sparkling jewels,

and all your walls of precious stones.

13 All your children will be taught by Yahweh;

and your children’s peace will be great.

14 In righteousness you will be established.

You will be far from oppression,

for you will not be afraid;

and far from terror,

for it shall not come near you.

15 Behold, they may gather together, but not by me.

Whoever gathers together against you will fall because of you.

16 “Behold, I have created the blacksmith who fans the coals into flame,

and forges a weapon for his work;

and I have created the destroyer to destroy.

17 No weapon that is formed against you will prevail;

and you will condemn every tongue that rises against you in judgment.

This is the heritage of Yahweh’s servants,

and their righteousness is of me,” says Yahweh.

or, seed

Isaiah 55

1 “Hey! Come, everyone who thirsts, to the waters!

Come, he who has no money, buy, and eat!

Yes, come, buy wine and milk without money and without price.

2 Why do you spend money for that which is not bread,

and your labor for that which doesn’t satisfy?

Listen diligently to me, and eat that which is good,

and let your soul delight itself in richness.

3 Turn your ear, and come to me.

Hear, and your soul will live:

and I will make an everlasting covenant with you, even the sure mercies of David.

4 Behold, I have given him for a witness to the peoples,

a leader and commander to the peoples.

5 Behold, you shall call a nation that you don’t know;

and a nation that didn’t know you shall run to you,

because of Yahweh your God,

and for the Holy One of Israel;

for he has glorified you.”

6 Seek Yahweh while he may be found.

Call on him while he is near.

7 Let the wicked forsake his way,

and the unrighteous man his thoughts.

Let him return to Yahweh, and he will have mercy on him;

and to our God, for he will freely pardon.

8 “For my thoughts are not your thoughts,

and your ways are not my ways,” says Yahweh.

9 “For as the heavens are higher than the earth,

so are my ways higher than your ways,

and my thoughts than your thoughts.

10 For as the rain comes down and the snow from the sky,

and doesn’t return there, but waters the earth,

and makes it grow and bud,

and gives seed to the sower and bread to the eater;

11 so is my word that goes out of my mouth:

it will not return to me void,

but it will accomplish that which I please,

and it will prosper in the thing I sent it to do.

12 For you shall go out with joy,

and be led out with peace.

The mountains and the hills will break out before you into singing;

and all the trees of the fields will clap their hands.

13 Instead of the thorn the cypress tree will come up;

and instead of the brier the myrtle tree will come up:

and it will make a name for Yahweh,

for an everlasting sign that will not be cut off.”

Isaiah 56

1 Yahweh says,

“Maintain justice,

and do what is right;

for my salvation is near,

and my righteousness will soon be revealed.

2 Blessed is the man who does this,

and the son of man who holds it fast;

who keeps the Sabbath without profaning it,

and keeps his hand from doing any evil.”

3 Let no foreigner, who has joined himself to Yahweh, speak, saying,

“Yahweh will surely separate me from his people.”

Do not let the eunuch say, “Behold, I am a dry tree.”

4 For Yahweh says, “To the eunuchs who keep my Sabbaths,

and choose the things that please me,

and hold fast to my covenant:

5 I will give them in my house and within my walls a memorial and a name better than of sons and of daughters.

I will give them an everlasting name, that will not be cut off.

6 Also the foreigners who join themselves to Yahweh,

to serve him,

and to love Yahweh’s name,

to be his servants,

everyone who keeps the Sabbath from profaning it,

and holds fast my covenant;

7 I will bring these to my holy mountain,

and make them joyful in my house of prayer.

Their burnt offerings and their sacrifices will be accepted on my altar;

for my house will be called a house of prayer for all peoples.”

8 The Lord Yahweh, who gathers the outcasts of Israel, says,

“I will yet gather others to him,

besides his own who are gathered.”

9 All you animals of the field,

come to devour,

all you animals in the forest.

10 His watchmen are blind.

They are all without knowledge.

They are all mute dogs.

They can’t bark;

dreaming, lying down, loving to slumber.

11 Yes, the dogs are greedy.

They can never have enough.

They are shepherds who can’t understand.

They have all turned to their own way,

each one to his gain, from every quarter.

12 “Come,” say they, “I will get wine,

and we will fill ourselves with strong drink;

and tomorrow will be as today,

great beyond measure.”

Isaiah 57

1 The righteous perish,

and no one lays it to heart.

Merciful men are taken away,

and no one considers that the righteous is taken away from the evil.

2 He enters into peace.

They rest in their beds,

each one who walks in his uprightness.

3 “But draw near here, you sons of a sorceress,

you offspring[*] of adulterers and prostitutes.

4 Whom do you mock?

Against whom do you make a wide mouth,

and stick out your tongue?

Aren’t you children of disobedience,

and offspring[*] of falsehood,

5 you who inflame yourselves among the oaks,

under every green tree;

who kill the children in the valleys,

under the clefts of the rocks?

6 Among the smooth stones of the valley is your portion;

they, they are your lot.

You have even poured a drink offering to them.

You have offered an offering.

Shall I be appeased for these things?

7 On a high and lofty mountain you have set your bed.

You also went up there to offer sacrifice.

8 You have set up your memorial behind the doors and the posts;

for you have exposed yourself to someone besides me,

and have gone up;

you have enlarged your bed,

and made you a covenant with them.

You loved what you saw on their bed.

9 You went to the king with oil,

and increased your perfumes,

and sent your ambassadors far off,

and degraded yourself even to Sheol.[*]

10 You were wearied with the length of your ways;

yet you didn’t say, ‘It is in vain.’

You found a reviving of your strength;

therefore you weren’t faint.

11 “Whom have you dreaded and feared,

so that you lie,

and have not remembered me, nor laid it to your heart?

Haven’t I held my peace for a long time,

and you don’t fear me?

12 I will declare your righteousness;

and as for your works, they will not benefit you.

13 When you cry,

let those whom you have gathered deliver you;

but the wind will take them.

a breath will carry them all away:

but he who takes refuge in me will possess the land,

and will inherit my holy mountain.”

14 He will say, “Build up, build up, prepare the way!

Remove the stumbling-block out of the way of my people.”

15 For thus says the high and lofty One who inhabits eternity,

whose name is Holy:

“I dwell in the high and holy place, with him also who is of a contrite and humble spirit,

to revive the spirit of the humble,

and to revive the heart of the contrite.

16 For I will not contend forever, neither will I be always angry;

for the spirit would faint before me,

and the souls whom I have made.

17 I was angry because of the iniquity of his covetousness, and struck him;

I hid myself and was angry;

and he went on backsliding in the way of his heart.

18 I have seen his ways, and will heal him:

I will lead him also,

and restore comforts to him and to his mourners.

19 I create the fruit of the lips:

Peace, peace, to him who is far off and to him who is near,”

says Yahweh; “and I will heal them.”

20 But the wicked are like the troubled sea;

for it can’t rest, and its waters cast up mire and mud.

21 “There is no peace”, says my God,

“for the wicked.”

or, seed

or, seed

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Isaiah 58

1 “Cry aloud, don’t spare.

Lift up your voice like a trumpet.

Declare to my people their disobedience,

and to the house of Jacob their sins.

2 Yet they seek me daily,

and delight to know my ways.

As a nation that did righteousness,

and didn’t forsake the ordinance of their God,

they ask of me righteous judgments.

They delight to draw near to God.

3 ‘Why have we fasted,’ say they, ‘and you don’t see?

Why have we afflicted our soul, and you don’t notice?’

“Behold, in the day of your fast you find pleasure,

and oppress all your laborers.

4 Behold, you fast for strife and contention,

and to strike with the fist of wickedness.

You don’t fast today so as to make your voice to be heard on high.

5 Is this the fast that I have chosen?

A day for a man to humble his soul?

Is it to bow down his head like a reed,

and to spread sackcloth and ashes under himself?

Will you call this a fast,

and an acceptable day to Yahweh?

6 “Isn’t this the fast that I have chosen:

to release the bonds of wickedness,

to undo the straps of the yoke,

to let the oppressed go free,

and that you break every yoke?

7 Isn’t it to distribute your bread to the hungry,

and that you bring the poor who are cast out to your house?

When you see the naked,

that you cover him;

and that you not hide yourself from your own flesh?

8 Then your light will break out as the morning,

and your healing will appear quickly;

then your righteousness shall go before you;

and Yahweh’s glory will be your rear guard.

9 Then you will call, and Yahweh will answer;

you will cry for help, and he will say, ‘Here I am.’

“If you take away from among you the yoke,

finger pointing,

and speaking wickedly;

10 and if you pour out your soul to the hungry,

and satisfy the afflicted soul:

then your light will rise in darkness,

and your obscurity will be as the noonday;

11 and Yahweh will guide you continually,

and satisfy your soul in dry places,

and make your bones strong;

and you shall be like a watered garden,

and like a spring of water,

whose waters don’t fail.

12 Those who shall be of you shall build the old waste places;

you shall raise up the foundations of many generations;

and you shall be called Repairer of the Breach,

Restorer of Paths with Dwellings.

13 “If you turn away your foot from the Sabbath,

from doing your pleasure on my holy day;

and call the Sabbath a delight,

and the holy of Yahweh honorable;

and shall honor it,

not doing your own ways,

nor finding your own pleasure,

nor speaking your own words:

14 then you shall delight yourself in Yahweh;

and I will make you to ride on the high places of the earth;

and I will feed you with the heritage of Jacob your father:”

for Yahweh’s mouth has spoken it.

Isaiah 59

1 Behold, Yahweh’s hand is not shortened, that it can’t save;

nor his ear dull, that it can’t hear.

2 But your iniquities have separated you and your God,

and your sins have hidden his face from you,

so that he will not hear.

3 For your hands are defiled with blood,

and your fingers with iniquity.

Your lips have spoken lies.

Your tongue mutters wickedness.

4 No one sues in righteousness,

and no one pleads in truth.

They trust in vanity,

and speak lies.

They conceive mischief,

and give birth to iniquity.

5 They hatch adders’ eggs,

and weave the spider’s web.

He who eats of their eggs dies;

and that which is crushed breaks out into a viper.

6 Their webs won’t become garments.

They won’t cover themselves with their works.

Their works are works of iniquity,

and acts of violence are in their hands.

7 Their feet run to evil,

and they hurry to shed innocent blood.

Their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity.

desolation and destruction are in their paths.

8 They don’t know the way of peace;

and there is no justice in their ways.

They have made crooked paths for themselves;

whoever goes in them doesn’t know peace.

9 Therefore is justice far from us,

and righteousness doesn’t overtake us.

We look for light, but see darkness;

for brightness, but we walk in obscurity.

10 We grope for the wall like the blind.

Yes, we grope as those who have no eyes.

We stumble at noon as if it were twilight.

Among those who are strong, we are like dead men.

11 We all roar like bears,

and moan bitterly like doves.

We look for justice, but there is none;

for salvation, but it is far off from us.

12 For our transgressions are multiplied before you,

and our sins testify against us;

for our transgressions are with us,

and as for our iniquities, we know them:

13 transgressing and denying Yahweh,

and turning away from following our God,

speaking oppression and revolt,

conceiving and uttering from the heart words of falsehood.

14 Justice is turned away backward,

and righteousness stands far away;

for truth has fallen in the street,

and uprightness can’t enter.

15 Yes, truth is lacking;

and he who departs from evil makes himself a prey.

Yahweh saw it,

and it displeased him that there was no justice.

16 He saw that there was no man,

and wondered that there was no intercessor.

Therefore his own arm brought salvation to him;

and his righteousness sustained him.

17 He put on righteousness as a breastplate,

and a helmet of salvation on his head.

He put on garments of vengeance for clothing,

and was clad with zeal as a mantle.

18 According to their deeds,

he will repay as appropriate,

wrath to his adversaries,

recompense to his enemies;

he will repay the islands their due.

19 So shall they fear Yahweh’s name from the west,

and his glory from the rising of the sun;

for he will come as a rushing stream,

which Yahweh’s breath drives.

20 “A Redeemer will come to Zion,

and to those who turn from disobedience in Jacob,” says Yahweh.

21 “As for me, this is my covenant with them,” says Yahweh. “My Spirit who is on you, and my words which I have put in your mouth, shall not depart out of your mouth, nor out of the mouth of your offspring,[*] nor out of the mouth of your offspring’s offspring,” says Yahweh, “from henceforth and forever.”

or, seed

Isaiah 60

1 “Arise, shine; for your light has come,

and Yahweh’s glory has risen on you.

2 For, behold, darkness will cover the earth,

and thick darkness the peoples;

but Yahweh will arise on you,

and his glory shall be seen on you.

3 Nations will come to your light,

and kings to the brightness of your rising.

4 “Lift up your eyes all around, and see:

they all gather themselves together.

They come to you.

Your sons will come from far away,

and your daughters will be carried in arms.

5 Then you shall see and be radiant,

and your heart will thrill and be enlarged;

because the abundance of the sea will be turned to you.

The wealth of the nations will come to you.

6 A multitude of camels will cover you,

the dromedaries of Midian and Ephah.

All from Sheba will come.

They will bring gold and frankincense,

and will proclaim the praises of Yahweh.

7 All the flocks of Kedar will be gathered together to you.

The rams of Nebaioth will serve you.

They will be accepted as offerings on my altar;

and I will beautify my glorious house.

8 “Who are these who fly as a cloud,

and as the doves to their windows?

9 Surely the islands will wait for me,

and the ships of Tarshish first,

to bring your sons from far,

their silver and their gold with them,

for the name of Yahweh your God,

and for the Holy One of Israel,

because he has glorified you.

10 “Foreigners will build up your walls,

and their kings will serve you:

for in my wrath I struck you,

but in my favor I have had mercy on you.

11 Your gates also shall be open continually; they shall not be shut day nor night; that men may bring to you the wealth of the nations, and their kings led captive.

12 For that nation and kingdom that will not serve you shall perish; yes, those nations shall be utterly wasted.

13 “The glory of Lebanon shall come to you, the cypress tree, the pine, and the box tree together, to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I will make the place of my feet glorious.

14 The sons of those who afflicted you will come bowing to you;

and all those who despised you will bow themselves down at the soles of your feet.

They will call you Yahweh’s City,

The Zion of the Holy One of Israel.

15 “Whereas you have been forsaken and hated,

so that no one passed through you,

I will make you an eternal excellency,

a joy of many generations.

16 You will also drink the milk of the nations,

and will nurse from royal breasts.

Then you will know that I, Yahweh, am your Savior,

your Redeemer,

the Mighty One of Jacob.

17 For brass I will bring gold;

for iron I will bring silver;

for wood, brass,

and for stones, iron.

I will also make peace your governor,

and righteousness your ruler.

18 Violence shall no more be heard in your land,

nor desolation or destruction within your borders;

but you will call your walls Salvation,

and your gates Praise.

19 The sun will be no more your light by day;

nor will the brightness of the moon give light to you,

but Yahweh will be your everlasting light,

and your God will be your glory.

20 Your sun will not go down any more,

nor will your moon withdraw itself;

for Yahweh will be your everlasting light,

and the days of your mourning will end.

21 Then your people will all be righteous.

They will inherit the land forever,

the branch of my planting,

the work of my hands,

that I may be glorified.

22 The little one will become a thousand,

and the small one a strong nation.

I, Yahweh, will do this quickly in its time.”

Isaiah 61

1 The Lord Yahweh’s Spirit is on me;

because Yahweh has anointed me to preach good news to the humble.

He has sent me to bind up the broken hearted,

to proclaim liberty to the captives,

and release to those who are bound;

2 to proclaim the year of Yahweh’s favor,

and the day of vengeance of our God;

to comfort all who mourn;

3 to provide for those who mourn in Zion,

to give to them a garland for ashes,

the oil of joy for mourning,

the garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness;

that they may be called trees of righteousness,

the planting of Yahweh,

that he may be glorified.

4 They will rebuild the old ruins.

They will raise up the places long devastated.

They will repair the ruined cities,

that have been devastated for many generations.

5 Strangers will stand and feed your flocks,

and foreigners will work your fields and your vineyards.

6 But you will be called Yahweh’s priests.

Men will call you the servants of our God.

You will eat the wealth of the nations,

and you will boast in their glory.

7 Instead of your shame you will have double.

Instead of dishonor, they will rejoice in their portion.

Therefore in their land, they will possess double.

Everlasting joy will be to them.

8 “For I, Yahweh, love justice.

I hate robbery and iniquity.

I will give them their reward in truth,

and I will make an everlasting covenant with them.

9 Their offspring[*] will be known among the nations,

and their offspring among the peoples.

All who see them will acknowledge them,

that they are the offspring[*] which Yahweh has blessed.”

10 I will greatly rejoice in Yahweh!

My soul will be joyful in my God;

for he has clothed me with the garments of salvation.

He has covered me with the robe of righteousness,

as a bridegroom decks himself with a garland,

and as a bride adorns herself with her jewels.

11 For as the earth produces its bud,

and as the garden causes the things that are sown in it to spring up;

so the Lord Yahweh will cause righteousness and praise to spring up before all the nations.

or, seed

or, seed

Isaiah 62

1 For Zion’s sake will I not hold my peace,

and for Jerusalem’s sake I will not rest,

until her righteousness shines out like the dawn,

and her salvation like a burning lamp.

2 The nations will see your righteousness,

and all kings your glory,

and you will be called by a new name,

which Yahweh‘s mouth will name.

3 You will also be a crown of beauty in Yahweh‘s hand,

and a royal diadem in your God‘s hand.

4 You will not be called Forsaken any more;

nor will your land be called Desolate any more:

but you will be called Hephzibah,[*]

and your land Beulah;[*]

for Yahweh delights in you,

and your land will be married.

5 For as a young man marries a virgin,

so your sons will marry you.

As a bridegroom rejoices over his bride,

so your God will rejoice over you.

6 I have set watchmen on your walls, Jerusalem.

They will never be silent day nor night.

You who call on Yahweh, take no rest,

7 and give him no rest, until he establishes,

and until he makes Jerusalem a praise in the earth.

8 Yahweh has sworn by his right hand,

and by the arm of his strength,

“Surely I will no more give your grain to be food for your enemies;

and foreigners will not drink your new wine, for which you have labored;

9 but those who have harvested it will eat it, and praise Yahweh;

and those who have gathered it will drink it in the courts of my sanctuary.”

10 Go through, go through the gates!

Prepare the way of the people!

Build up, build up the highway!

Gather out the stones!

Lift up a banner for the peoples.

11 Behold, Yahweh has proclaimed to the end of the earth,

“Say to the daughter of Zion,

‘Behold, your salvation comes.

Behold, his reward is with him,

and his recompense before him.’”

12 They will call them The holy people,

Yahweh’s redeemed.

You will be called Sought out,

A city not forsaken.

Hephibah means “I delight in her”.

Beulah means “married”

Isaiah 63

1 Who is this who comes from Edom,

with dyed garments from Bozrah?

Who this who is glorious in his clothing,

marching in the greatness of his strength?

“It is I who speak in righteousness,

mighty to save.”

2 Why is your clothing red,

and your garments like him who treads in the wine vat?

3 “I have trodden the wine press alone;

and of the peoples, no one was with me:

Yes, I trod them in my anger,

and trampled them in my wrath.

Their lifeblood is sprinkled on my garments,

and I have stained all my clothing.

4 For the day of vengeance was in my heart,

and the year of my redeemed has come.

5 I looked, and there was no one to help;

and I wondered that there was no one to uphold:

therefore my own arm brought salvation to me;

and my own wrath upheld me.

6 I trod down the peoples in my anger,

and made them drunk in my wrath,

and I poured out their lifeblood on the earth.”

7 I will tell of the loving kindnesses of Yahweh

and the praises of Yahweh,

according to all that Yahweh has given to us,

and the great goodness toward the house of Israel,

which he has given to them according to his mercies,

and according to the multitude of his loving kindnesses.

8 For he said, “Surely, they are my people,

children who will not deal falsely;”

so he became their Savior.

9 In all their affliction he was afflicted,

and the angel of his presence saved them.

In his love and in his pity he redeemed them.

He bore them,

and carried them all the days of old.

10 But they rebelled,

and grieved his holy Spirit.

Therefore he turned and became their enemy,

and he himself fought against them.

11 Then he remembered the days of old,

Moses and his people, saying,

“Where is he who brought them up out of the sea with the shepherds of his flock?

Where is he who put his Holy Spirit among them?”

12 Who caused his glorious arm to be at Moses’ right hand?

Who divided the waters before them, to make himself an everlasting name?

13 Who led them through the depths,

like a horse in the wilderness,

so that they didn’t stumble?

14 As the livestock that go down into the valley,

Yahweh’s Spirit caused them to rest.

So you led your people, to make yourself a glorious name.

15 Look down from heaven,

and see from the habitation of your holiness and of your glory.

Where are your zeal and your mighty acts?

The yearning of your heart and your compassion is restrained toward me.

16 For you are our Father,

though Abraham doesn’t know us,

and Israel does not acknowledge us.

You, Yahweh, are our Father.

Our Redeemer from everlasting is your name.

17 O Yahweh, why do you make us wander from your ways,

and harden our heart from your fear?

Return for your servants’ sake,

the tribes of your inheritance.

18 Your holy people possessed it but a little while.

Our adversaries have trodden down your sanctuary.

19 We have become like those over whom you never ruled,

like those who were not called by your name.

Isaiah 64

1 Oh that you would tear the heavens,

that you would come down,

that the mountains might quake at your presence.

2 As when fire kindles the brushwood,

and the fire causes the water to boil;

Make your name known to your adversaries,

that the nations may tremble at your presence!

3 When you did awesome things which we didn’t look for,

you came down, and the mountains quaked at your presence.

4 For from of old men have not heard,

nor perceived by the ear,

nor has the eye seen a God besides you,

who works for him who waits for him.

5 You meet him who rejoices and does righteousness,

those who remember you in your ways.

Behold, you were angry, and we sinned.

We have been in sin for a long time.

Shall we be saved?

6 For we have all become like one who is unclean,

and all our righteousness is like a polluted garment.

We all fade like a leaf;

and our iniquities, like the wind, take us away.

7 There is no one who calls on your name,

who stirs himself up to take hold of you;

for you have hidden your face from us,

and have consumed us by means of our iniquities.

8 But now, Yahweh, you are our Father.

We are the clay, and you our potter.

We all are the work of your hand.

9 Don’t be furious, Yahweh,

and don’t remember iniquity forever.

Look and see, we beg you,

we are all your people.

10 Your holy cities have become a wilderness.

Zion has become a wilderness,

Jerusalem a desolation.

11 Our holy and our beautiful house, where our fathers praised you,

is burned with fire;

and all our pleasant places are laid waste.

12 Will you hold yourself back for these things, Yahweh?

Will you keep silent, and punish us very severely?

Isaiah 65

1 “I am inquired of by those who didn’t ask.

I am found by those who didn’t seek me.

I said, ‘See me, see me,’ to a nation that was not called by my name.

2 I have spread out my hands all day to a rebellious people,

who walk in a way that is not good,

after their own thoughts;

3 a people who provoke me to my face continually,

sacrificing in gardens,

and burning incense on bricks;

4 who sit among the graves,

and spend nights in secret places;

who eat pig’s meat,

and broth of abominable things is in their vessels;

5 who say, ‘Stay by yourself,

don’t come near to me,

for I am holier than you.’

These are smoke in my nose,

a fire that burns all day.

6 “Behold, it is written before me:

I will not keep silence,

but will repay,

yes, I will repay into their bosom,

7 your own iniquities, and the iniquities of your fathers together”, says Yahweh,

“who have burned incense on the mountains,

and blasphemed me on the hills.

Therefore I will first measure their work into their bosom.”

8 Yahweh says,

“As the new wine is found in the cluster,

and one says, ‘Don’t destroy it, for a blessing is in it:’

so will I do for my servants’ sake,

that I may not destroy them all.

9 I will bring offspring[*] out of Jacob,

and out of Judah an inheritor of my mountains.

My chosen will inherit it,

and my servants will dwell there.

10 Sharon will be a fold of flocks,

and the valley of Achor a place for herds to lie down in,

for my people who have sought me.

11 “But you who forsake Yahweh,

who forget my holy mountain,

who prepare a table for Fortune,

and who fill up mixed wine to Destiny;

12 I will destine you to the sword,

and you will all bow down to the slaughter;

because when I called, you didn’t answer.

When I spoke, you didn’t listen;

but you did that which was evil in my eyes,

and chose that in which I didn’t delight.”

13 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh,

“Behold, my servants will eat,

but you will be hungry;

behold, my servants will drink,

but you will be thirsty.

Behold, my servants will rejoice,

but you will be disappointed;

14 Behold, my servants will sing for joy of heart,

but you will cry for sorrow of heart,

and will wail for anguish of spirit.

15 You will leave your name for a curse to my chosen;

and the Lord Yahweh will kill you.

He will call his servants by another name,

16 so that he who blesses himself in the earth will bless himself in the God of truth;

and he who swears in the earth will swear by the God of truth;

because the former troubles are forgotten,

and because they are hidden from my eyes.

17 “For, behold, I create new heavens and a new earth;

and the former things will not be remembered,

nor come into mind.

18 But be glad and rejoice forever in that which I create;

for, behold, I create Jerusalem to be a delight,

and her people a joy.

19 I will rejoice in Jerusalem,

and delight in my people;

and the voice of weeping and the voice of crying

will be heard in her no more.

20 “No more will there be an infant who only lives a few days,

nor an old man who has not filled his days;

for the child will die one hundred years old,

and the sinner being one hundred years old will be accursed.

21 They will build houses, and inhabit them.

They will plant vineyards, and eat their fruit.

22 They will not build, and another inhabit.

They will not plant, and another eat:

for the days of my people will be like the days of a tree,

and my chosen will long enjoy the work of their hands.

23 They will not labor in vain,

nor give birth for calamity;

for they are the offspring[*] of Yahweh’s blessed,

and their descendants with them.

24 It will happen that, before they call, I will answer;

and while they are yet speaking, I will hear.

25 The wolf and the lamb will feed together,

and the lion will eat straw like the ox.

Dust will be the serpent’s food.

They will not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain,”

says Yahweh.

or, seed

or, seed

Isaiah 66

1 Yahweh says,

“Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool.

What kind of house will you build to me?

Where will I rest?

2 For my hand has made all these things,

and so all these things came to be,” says Yahweh:

“but to this man will I look,

even to he who is poor and of a contrite spirit,

and who trembles at my word.

3 He who kills an ox is as he who kills a man;

he who sacrifices a lamb, as he who breaks a dog’s neck;

he who offers an offering, as he who offers pig’s blood;

he who burns frankincense, as he who blesses an idol.

Yes, they have chosen their own ways,

and their soul delights in their abominations:

4 I also will choose their delusions,

and will bring their fears on them;

because when I called, no one answered;

when I spoke, they didn’t listen;

but they did that which was evil in my eyes,

and chose that in which I didn’t delight.”

5 Hear Yahweh’s word,

you who tremble at his word:

“Your brothers who hate you,

who cast you out for my name’s sake, have said,

‘Let Yahweh be glorified,

that we may see your joy;’

but it is those who shall be disappointed.

6 A voice of tumult from the city,

a voice from the temple,

a voice of Yahweh that repays his enemies what they deserve.

7 “Before she travailed, she gave birth.

Before her pain came, she delivered a son.

8 Who has heard of such a thing?

Who has seen such things?

Shall a land be born in one day?

Shall a nation be born at once?

For as soon as Zion travailed,

she gave birth to her children.

9 Shall I bring to the birth, and not cause to be delivered?” says Yahweh.

“Shall I who cause to give birth shut the womb?” says your God.

10 “Rejoice with Jerusalem, and be glad for her, all you who love her.

Rejoice for joy with her, all you who mourn over her;

11 that you may nurse and be satisfied at the comforting breasts;

that you may drink deeply,

and be delighted with the abundance of her glory.”

12 For Yahweh says, “Behold, I will extend peace to her like a river,

and the glory of the nations like an overflowing stream;

and you will nurse.

You will be carried on her side,

and will be dandled on her knees.

13 As one whom his mother comforts,

so will I comfort you.

You will be comforted in Jerusalem.”

14 You will see it, and your heart shall rejoice,

and your bones will flourish like the tender grass.

Yahweh’s hand will be known among his servants;

and he will have indignation against his enemies.

15 For, behold, Yahweh will come with fire,

and his chariots will be like the whirlwind;

to render his anger with fierceness,

and his rebuke with flames of fire.

16 For Yahweh will execute judgment by fire and by his sword on all flesh;

and those slain by Yahweh will be many.

17 “Those who sanctify themselves and purify themselves to go to the gardens, behind one in the middle, eating pig’s meat, abominable things, and the mouse, they shall come to an end together,” says Yahweh.

18 “For I know their works and their thoughts. The time comes that I will gather all nations and languages, and they will come, and will see my glory.

19 “I will set a sign among them, and I will send those who escape of them to the nations, to Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, who draw the bow, to Tubal and Javan, to far-away islands, who have not heard my fame, nor have seen my glory; and they shall declare my glory among the nations. 20 They shall bring all your brothers out of all the nations for an offering to Yahweh, on horses, in chariots, in litters, on mules, and on camels, to my holy mountain Jerusalem, says Yahweh, as the children of Israel bring their offering in a clean vessel into Yahweh’s house. 21 Of them I will also select priests and Levites,” says Yahweh.

22 “For as the new heavens and the new earth, which I will make, shall remain before me,” says Yahweh, “so your offspring[*] and your name shall remain. 23 It shall happen that from one new moon to another, and from one Sabbath to another, all flesh will come to worship before me,” says Yahweh. 24 “They will go out, and look at the dead bodies of the men who have transgressed against me; for their worm will not die, nor will their fire be quenched, and they will be loathsome to all mankind.”

or, seed

Jeremiah 1

1 The words of Jeremiah the son of Hilkiah, one of the priests who were in Anathoth in the land of Benjamin. 2 Yahweh’s word[*] came to him in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reign. 3 It came also in the days of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, to the end of the eleventh year of Zedekiah, the son of Josiah, king of Judah, to the carrying away of Jerusalem captive in the fifth month. 4 Now Yahweh’s word came to me, saying,

5 “Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you.

Before you were born, I sanctified you.

I have appointed you a prophet to the nations.”

6 Then I said, “Ah, Lord[*] Yahweh! Behold,[*] I don’t know how to speak; for I am a child.”

7 But Yahweh said to me, “Don’t say, ‘I am a child;’ for you must go to whomever I send you, and you must say whatever I command you. 8 Don’t be afraid because of them, for I am with you to rescue you,” says Yahweh.

9 Then Yahweh stretched out his hand, and touched my mouth. Then Yahweh said to me, “Behold, I have put my words in your mouth. 10 Behold, I have today set you over the nations and over the kingdoms, to uproot and to tear down, to destroy and to overthrow, to build and to plant.”

11 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, “Jeremiah, what do you see?”

I said, “I see a branch of an almond tree.”

12 Then Yahweh said to me, “You have seen well; for I watch over my word to perform it.”

13 Yahweh’s word came to me the second time, saying, “What do you see?”

I said, “I see a boiling cauldron; and it is tipping away from the north.”

14 Then Yahweh said to me, “Out of the north, evil will break out on all the inhabitants of the land. 15 For, behold, I will call all the families of the kingdoms of the north,” says Yahweh.

“They will come, and they will each set his throne at the entrance of the gates of Jerusalem,

and against all its walls all around, and against all the cities of Judah.

16 I will utter my judgments against them concerning all their wickedness,

in that they have forsaken me,

and have burned incense to other gods,

and worshiped the works of their own hands.

17 “You therefore put your belt on your waist, arise, and say to them all that I command you. Don’t be dismayed at them, lest I dismay you before them. 18 For, behold, I have made you today a fortified city, an iron pillar, and bronze walls, against the whole land, against the kings of Judah, against its princes, against its priests, and against the people of the land. 19 They will fight against you, but they will not prevail against you; for I am with you”, says Yahweh, “to rescue you.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Jeremiah 2

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Go, and proclaim in the ears of Jerusalem, saying, ‘Yahweh says,

“I remember for you the kindness of your youth,

the love of your weddings;

how you went after me in the wilderness,

in a land that was not sown.

3 Israel was holiness to Yahweh,

the first fruits of his increase.

All who devour him shall be held guilty.

Evil shall come on them,”’ says Yahweh.”

4 Hear Yahweh’s word, O house of Jacob, and all the families of the house of Israel! 5 Yahweh says,

“What unrighteousness have your fathers found in me,

that they have gone far from me,

and have walked after worthless vanity,

and have become worthless?

6 They didn’t say, ‘Where is Yahweh who brought us up out of the land of Egypt,

who led us through the wilderness,

through a land of deserts and of pits,

through a land of drought and of the shadow of death,

through a land that no one passed through,

and where no man lived?’

7 I brought you into a plentiful land,

to eat its fruit and its goodness;

but when you entered, you defiled my land,

and made my heritage an abomination.

8 The priests didn’t say, ‘Where is Yahweh?’

and those who handle the law didn’t know me.

The rulers also transgressed against me,

and the prophets prophesied by Baal,

and followed things that do not profit.

9 “Therefore I will yet contend with you,” says Yahweh,

“and I will contend with your children’s children.

10 For pass over to the islands of Kittim, and see;

and send to Kedar, and consider diligently;

and see if there has been such a thing.

11 Has a nation changed its gods,

which really are no gods?

But my people have changed their glory for that which does not profit.

12 “Be astonished, you heavens, at this,

and be horribly afraid.

Be very desolate,” says Yahweh.

13 “For my people have committed two evils:

they have forsaken me, the spring of living waters,

and cut them out cisterns, broken cisterns, that can hold no water.

14 Is Israel a slave?

Is he born into slavery?

Why has he become a captive?

15 The young lions have roared at him, and yelled.

They have made his land waste.

His cities are burned up, without inhabitant.

16 The children also of Memphis and Tahpanhes have broken the crown of your head.

17 “Haven’t you brought this on yourself,

in that you have forsaken Yahweh your God,[*] when he led you by the way?

18 Now what do you gain by going to Egypt, to drink the waters of the Shihor?

Or why do you to go on the way to Assyria, to drink the waters of the River?[*]

19 “Your own wickedness will correct you,

and your backsliding will rebuke you.

Know therefore and see that it is an evil and bitter thing,

that you have forsaken Yahweh your God,

and that my fear is not in you,” says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies.

20 “For long ago I broke off your yoke,

and burst your bonds.

You said, ‘I will not serve;’

for on every high hill and under every green tree you bowed yourself,

playing the prostitute.

21 Yet I had planted you a noble vine,

a pure and faithful seed.

How then have you turned into the degenerate branches of a foreign vine to me?

22 For though you wash yourself with lye,

and use much soap,

yet your iniquity is marked before me,” says the Lord Yahweh.

23 “How can you say, ‘I am not defiled.

I have not gone after the Baals’?

See your way in the valley.

Know what you have done.

You are a swift dromedary traversing her ways; 24 a wild donkey used to the wilderness, that sniffs the wind in her craving.

When she is in heat, who can turn her away?

All those who seek her will not weary themselves. In her month, they will find her.

25 “Keep your feet from being bare,

and your throat from thirst.

But you said, ‘It is in vain.

No, for I have loved strangers,

and I will go after them.’

26 As the thief is ashamed when he is found,

so is the house of Israel ashamed;

they, their kings, their princes, and their priests, and their prophets;

27 who tell wood, ‘You are my father;’

and a stone, ‘You have given birth to me:’

for they have turned their back to me,

and not their face;

but in the time of their trouble they will say, ‘Arise, and save us.’

28 “But where are your gods that you have made for yourselves?

Let them arise, if they can save you in the time of your trouble:

for you have as many gods as you have towns, O Judah.

29 “Why will you contend with me?

You all have transgressed against me,” says Yahweh.

30 “I have struck your children in vain.

They received no correction.

Your own sword has devoured your prophets,

like a destroying lion.

31 Generation, consider Yahweh’s word.

Have I been a wilderness to Israel?

Or a land of thick darkness?

Why do my people say, ‘We have broken loose.

We will come to you no more?’

32 “Can a virgin forget her ornaments,

or a bride her attire?

Yet my people have forgotten me for days without number.

33 How well you prepare your way to seek love!

Therefore you have even taught the wicked women your ways.

34 Also the blood of the souls of the innocent poor is found in your skirts.

You did not find them breaking in;

but it is because of all these things.

35 “Yet you said, ‘I am innocent.

Surely his anger has turned away from me.’

“Behold, I will judge you,

because you say, ‘I have not sinned.’

36 Why do you go about so much to change your ways?

You will be ashamed of Egypt also,

as you were ashamed of Assyria.

37 You will also leave that place with your hands on your head;

for Yahweh has rejected those in whom you trust,

and you won’t prosper with them.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

i.e., the Euphrates River

Jeremiah 3

1 “They say, ‘If a man puts away his wife, and she goes from him, and becomes another man’s, should he return to her again?’ Wouldn’t that land be greatly polluted? But you have played the prostitute with many lovers; yet return again to me,” says Yahweh.

2 “Lift up your eyes to the bare heights, and see! Where have you not been lain with? You have sat waiting for them by the road, as an Arabian in the wilderness. You have polluted the land with your prostitution and with your wickedness. 3 Therefore the showers have been withheld, and there has been no latter rain; yet you have a prostitute’s forehead. You refused to be ashamed. 4 Will you not from this time cry to me, ‘My Father, you are the guide of my youth?’

5 “‘Will he retain his anger forever? Will he keep it to the end?’ Behold, you have spoken and have done evil things, and have had your way.”

6 Moreover, Yahweh said to me in the days of Josiah the king, “Have you seen that which backsliding Israel has done? She has gone up on every high mountain and under every green tree, and has played the prostitute there. 7 I said after she had done all these things, ‘She will return to me;’ but she didn’t return; and her treacherous sister Judah saw it. 8 I saw when, for this very cause, that backsliding Israel had committed adultery, I had put her away and given her a bill of divorce, yet treacherous Judah, her sister, had no fear; but she also went and played the prostitute. 9 Because she took her prostitution lightly, the land was polluted, and she committed adultery with stones and with wood. 10 Yet for all this her treacherous sister, Judah, has not returned to me with her whole heart, but only in pretense,” says Yahweh.

11 Yahweh said to me, “Backsliding Israel has shown herself more righteous than treacherous Judah. 12 Go, and proclaim these words toward the north, and say, ‘Return, you backsliding Israel,’ says Yahweh; ‘I will not look in anger on you; for I am merciful,’ says Yahweh. ‘I will not keep anger forever. 13 Only acknowledge your iniquity, that you have transgressed against Yahweh your God, and have scattered your ways to the strangers under every green tree, and you have not obeyed my voice,’ says Yahweh.” 14 “Return, backsliding children,” says Yahweh; “for I am a husband to you. I will take one of you from a city, and two from a family, and I will bring you to Zion. 15 I will give you shepherds according to my heart, who will feed you with knowledge and understanding. 16 It will come to pass, when you are multiplied and increased in the land, in those days,” says Yahweh, “they will no longer say, ‘the ark of Yahweh’s covenant!’ It will not come to mind. They won’t remember it. They won’t miss it, nor will another be made. 17 At that time they will call Jerusalem ‘Yahweh’s Throne;’ and all the nations will be gathered to it, to Yahweh’s name, to Jerusalem. They will no longer walk after the stubbornness of their evil heart. 18 In those days the house of Judah will walk with the house of Israel, and they will come together out of the land of the north to the land that I gave for an inheritance to your fathers.

19 “But I said, ‘How I desire to put you among the children, and give you a pleasant land, a goodly heritage of the armies of the nations!’ and I said, ‘You shall call me “My Father”, and shall not turn away from following me.’

20 “Surely as a wife treacherously departs from her husband, so you have dealt treacherously with me, house of Israel,” says Yahweh. 21 A voice is heard on the bare heights, the weeping and the petitions of the children of Israel; because they have perverted their way, they have forgotten Yahweh their God. 22 Return, you backsliding children, and I will heal your backsliding.

“Behold, we have come to you; for you are Yahweh our God. 23 Truly in vain is help from the hills, the tumult on the mountains. Truly the salvation of Israel is in Yahweh our God. 24 But the shameful thing has devoured the labor of our fathers from our youth, their flocks and their herds, their sons and their daughters. 25 Let us lie down in our shame, and let our confusion cover us; for we have sinned against Yahweh our God, we and our fathers, from our youth even to this day. We have not obeyed Yahweh our God’s voice.”

Jeremiah 4

1 “If you will return, Israel,” says Yahweh, “if you will return to me, and if you will put away your abominations out of my sight; then you shall not be removed; 2 and you shall swear, ‘As Yahweh lives,’ in truth, in justice, and in righteousness. The nations shall bless themselves in him, and in him shall they glory.”

3 For Yahweh says to the men of Judah and to Jerusalem, “Break up your fallow ground, and don’t sow among thorns. 4 Circumcise yourselves to Yahweh, and take away the foreskins of your heart, you men of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem; lest my wrath go out like fire, and burn so that no one can quench it, because of the evil of your doings. 5 Declare in Judah, and publish in Jerusalem; and say, ‘Blow the trumpet in the land!’ Cry aloud and say, ‘Assemble yourselves! Let us go into the fortified cities!’ 6 Set up a standard toward Zion. Flee for safety! Don’t wait; for I will bring evil from the north, and a great destruction.”

7 A lion has gone up from his thicket, and a destroyer of nations; he is on his way, he has gone out from his place, to make your land desolate, that your cities be laid waste, without inhabitant. 8 For this clothe yourself with sackcloth, lament and wail; for the fierce anger of Yahweh hasn’t turned back from us. 9 “It shall happen at that day,” says Yahweh, “that the heart of the king shall perish, and the heart of the princes; and the priests shall be astonished, and the prophets shall wonder.”

10 Then I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh! Surely you have greatly deceived this people and Jerusalem, saying, ‘You shall have peace;’ whereas the sword reaches to the heart.”

11 At that time it will be said to this people and to Jerusalem, “A hot wind from the bare heights in the wilderness toward the daughter of my people, not to winnow, nor to cleanse; 12 a full wind from these shall come for me. Now I will also utter judgments against them.”

13 Behold, he shall come up as clouds, and his chariots shall be as the whirlwind: his horses are swifter than eagles. Woe to us! For we are ruined. 14 Jerusalem, wash your heart from wickedness, that you may be saved. How long shall your evil thoughts lodge within you? 15 For a voice declares from Dan, and publishes evil from the hills of Ephraim: 16 “Tell the nations; behold, publish against Jerusalem, ‘Watchers come from a far country, and raise their voice against the cities of Judah. 17 As keepers of a field, they are against her all around, because she has been rebellious against me,’” says Yahweh. 18 “Your way and your doings have brought these things to you. This is your wickedness; for it is bitter, for it reaches to your heart.”

19 My anguish, my anguish! I am pained at my very heart; my heart is disquieted in me; I can’t hold my peace; because you have heard, O my soul, the sound of the trumpet, the alarm of war. 20 Destruction on destruction is cried; for the whole land is laid waste: suddenly are my tents destroyed, and my curtains in a moment. 21 How long shall I see the standard, and hear the sound of the trumpet?

22 “For my people are foolish, they don’t know me. They are foolish children, and they have no understanding. They are skillful in doing evil, but to do good they have no knowledge.” 23 I saw the earth, and, behold, it was waste and void; and the heavens, and they had no light. 24 I saw the mountains, and behold, they trembled, and all the hills moved back and forth. 25 I saw, and behold, there was no man, and all the birds of the sky had fled. 26 I saw, and behold, the fruitful field was a wilderness, and all its cities were broken down at the presence of Yahweh, before his fierce anger. 27 For Yahweh says, “The whole land shall be a desolation; yet will I not make a full end. 28 For this the earth will mourn, and the heavens above be black; because I have spoken it, I have purposed it, and I have not repented, neither will I turn back from it.”

29 Every city flees for the noise of the horsemen and archers; they go into the thickets, and climb up on the rocks: every city is forsaken, and not a man dwells therein. 30 You, when you are made desolate, what will you do? Though you clothe yourself with scarlet, though you deck yourself with ornaments of gold, though you enlarge your eyes with makeup, you make yourself beautiful in vain. Your lovers despise you. They seek your life. 31 For I have heard a voice as of a woman in travail, the anguish as of her who gives birth to her first child, the voice of the daughter of Zion, who gasps for breath, who spreads her hands, saying, “Woe is me now! For my soul faints before the murderers.”

Jeremiah 5

1 “Run back and forth through the streets of Jerusalem, and see now, and know, and seek in its wide places, if you can find a man, if there are any who does justly, who seeks truth; and I will pardon her. 2 Though they say, ‘As Yahweh lives;’ surely they swear falsely.”

3 O Yahweh, don’t your eyes look on truth? You have stricken them, but they were not grieved. You have consumed them, but they have refused to receive correction. They have made their faces harder than a rock. They have refused to return.

4 Then I said, “Surely these are poor. They are foolish; for they don’t know the way of Yahweh, nor the law of their God. 5 I will go to the great men, and will speak to them; for they know the way of Yahweh, and the law of their God.” But these with one accord have broken the yoke, and burst the bonds. 6 Therefore a lion out of the forest shall kill them, a wolf of the evenings shall destroy them, a leopard shall watch against their cities; everyone who goes out there shall be torn in pieces; because their transgressions are many, and their backsliding is increased.

7 “How can I pardon you? Your children have forsaken me, and sworn by what are no gods. When I had fed them to the full, they committed adultery, and assembled themselves in troops at the prostitutes’ houses. 8 They were as fed horses roaming at large: everyone neighed after his neighbor’s wife. 9 Shouldn’t I punish them for these things?” says Yahweh; “and shouldn’t my soul be avenged on such a nation as this?

10 “Go up on her walls, and destroy; but don’t make a full end. Take away her branches; for they are not Yahweh’s. 11 For the house of Israel and the house of Judah have dealt very treacherously against me,” says Yahweh.

12 They have denied Yahweh, and said, “It is not he; neither shall evil come on us; neither shall we see sword nor famine. 13 The prophets shall become wind, and the word is not in them. Thus shall it be done to them.”

14 Therefore Yahweh, the God of Armies says, “Because you speak this word, behold, I will make my words in your mouth fire, and this people wood, and it shall devour them. 15 Behold, I will bring a nation on you from far, house of Israel,” says Yahweh. “It is a mighty nation. It is an ancient nation, a nation whose language you don’t know, neither understand what they say. 16 Their quiver is an open tomb, they are all mighty men. 17 They shall eat up your harvest, and your bread, which your sons and your daughters should eat. They shall eat up your flocks and your herds. They shall eat up your vines and your fig trees. They shall beat down your fortified cities, in which you trust, with the sword.

18 “But even in those days,” says Yahweh, “I will not make a full end with you. 19 It will happen, when you say, ‘Why has Yahweh our God done all these things to us?’ Then you shall say to them, ‘Just like you have forsaken me, and served foreign gods in your land, so you shall serve strangers in a land that is not yours.’

20 “Declare this in the house of Jacob, and publish it in Judah, saying, 21 ‘Hear now this, foolish people, and without understanding; who have eyes, and don’t see; who have ears, and don’t hear: 22 Don’t you fear me?’ says Yahweh ‘Won’t you tremble at my presence, who have placed the sand for the bound of the sea, by a perpetual decree, that it can’t pass it? and though its waves toss themselves, yet they can’t prevail; though they roar, yet they can’t pass over it.’

23 “But this people has a revolting and a rebellious heart; they have revolted and gone. 24 Neither do they say in their heart, ‘Let us now fear Yahweh our God, who gives rain, both the former and the latter, in its season; who preserves to us the appointed weeks of the harvest.’

25 “Your iniquities have turned away these things, and your sins have withheld good from you. 26 For among my people are found wicked men. They watch, as fowlers lie in wait. They set a trap. They catch men. 27 As a cage is full of birds, so are their houses full of deceit. Therefore they have become great, and grew rich. 28 They have grown fat. They shine; yes, they excel in deeds of wickedness. They don’t plead the cause, the cause of the fatherless, that they may prosper; and they don’t judge the right of the needy.

29 “Shall I not punish for these things?” says Yahweh. “Shall not my soul be avenged on such a nation as this?

30 “An astonishing and horrible thing has happened in the land. 31 The prophets prophesy falsely, and the priests rule by their own authority; and my people love to have it so. What will you do in the end of it?

Jeremiah 6

1 “Flee for safety, you children of Benjamin, out of the middle of Jerusalem, and blow the trumpet in Tekoa, and raise up a signal on Beth Haccherem; for evil looks out from the north, and a great destruction. 2 I will cut off the comely and delicate one, the daughter of Zion. 3 Shepherds with their flocks shall come to her; they shall pitch their tents against her all around; they shall feed everyone in his place.”

4 “Prepare war against her; arise, and let us go up at noon. Woe to us! For the day declines, for the shadows of the evening are stretched out. 5 Arise, and let us go up by night, and let us destroy her palaces.” 6 For Yahweh of Armies said, “Cut down trees, and cast up a mound against Jerusalem: this is the city to be visited; she is wholly oppression within her. 7 As a well produces its waters, so she produces her wickedness: violence and destruction is heard in her; before me continually is sickness and wounds. 8 Be instructed, Jerusalem, lest my soul be alienated from you; lest I make you a desolation, a land not inhabited.”

9 Yahweh of Armies says, “They shall thoroughly glean the remnant of Israel like a vine. Turn again your hand as a grape gatherer into the baskets.”

10 To whom shall I speak and testify, that they may hear? Behold, their ear is uncircumcised, and they can’t listen. Behold, Yahweh’s word has become a reproach to them. They have no delight in it. 11 Therefore I am full of Yahweh’s wrath. I am weary with holding in.

“Pour it out on the children in the street,

and on the assembly of young men together;

for even the husband with the wife shall be taken,

the aged with him who is full of days.

12 Their houses shall be turned to others,

their fields and their wives together;

for I will stretch out my hand on the inhabitants of the land, says Yahweh.”

13 “For from their least even to their greatest, everyone is given to covetousness;

and from the prophet even to the priest, everyone deals falsely.

14 They have healed also the hurt of my people superficially,

saying, ‘Peace, peace!’ when there is no peace.

15 Were they ashamed when they had committed abomination?

No, they were not at all ashamed, neither could they blush.

Therefore they shall fall among those who fall;

at the time that I visit them, they shall be cast down,” says Yahweh.

16 Yahweh says, “Stand in the ways and see, and ask for the old paths, ‘Where is the good way?’ and walk in it, and you will find rest for your souls. But they said, ‘We will not walk in it.’ 17 I set watchmen over you, saying, ‘Listen to the sound of the trumpet!’ But they said, ‘We will not listen!’ 18 Therefore hear, you nations, and know, congregation, what is among them. 19 Hear, earth! Behold, I will bring evil on this people, even the fruit of their thoughts, because they have not listened to my words; and as for my law, they have rejected it. 20 To what purpose comes there to me frankincense from Sheba, and the sweet cane from a far country? your burnt offerings are not acceptable, nor your sacrifices pleasing to me.”

21 Therefore Yahweh says, “Behold, I will lay stumbling blocks before this people. The fathers and the sons together shall stumble against them. The neighbor and his friend shall perish.” 22 Yahweh says, “Behold, a people comes from the north country. A great nation shall be stirred up from the uttermost parts of the earth. 23 They take hold of bow and spear. They are cruel, and have no mercy. Their voice roars like the sea, and they ride on horses, everyone set in array, as a man to the battle, against you, daughter of Zion.”

24 We have heard its report; our hands become feeble: anguish has taken hold of us, and pains as of a woman in labor. 25 Don’t go out into the field, nor walk by the way; for the sword of the enemy and terror, are on every side. 26 Daughter of my people, clothe yourself with sackcloth, and wallow in ashes! Mourn, as for an only son, most bitter lamentation; for the destroyer shall suddenly come on us.

27 “I have made you a tester of metals and a fortress among my people; that you may know and try their way. 28 They are all grievous rebels, going about with slanders; they are brass and iron: they all of them deal corruptly. 29 The bellows blow fiercely; the lead is consumed of the fire: in vain do they go on refining; for the wicked are not plucked away. 30 Men will call them rejected silver, because Yahweh has rejected them.”

Jeremiah 7

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, saying, 2 “Stand in the gate of Yahweh’s house, and proclaim there this word, and say, ‘Hear Yahweh’s word, all you of Judah, who enter in at these gates to worship Yahweh.’”

3 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says, “Amend your ways and your doings, and I will cause you to dwell in this place. 4 Don’t trust in lying words, saying, ‘Yahweh’s temple, Yahweh’s temple, Yahweh’s temple, are these.’ 5 For if you thoroughly amend your ways and your doings; if you thoroughly execute justice between a man and his neighbor; 6 if you don’t oppress the foreigner, the fatherless, and the widow, and don’t shed innocent blood in this place, neither walk after other gods to your own hurt: 7 then I will cause you to dwell in this place, in the land that I gave to your fathers, from of old even forever more. 8 Behold, you trust in lying words, that can’t profit. 9 Will you steal, murder, and commit adultery, and swear falsely, and burn incense to Baal, and walk after other gods that you have not known, 10 and come and stand before me in this house, which is called by my name, and say, ‘We are delivered;’ that you may do all these abominations? 11 Has this house, which is called by my name, become a den of robbers in your eyes? Behold, I, even I, have seen it,” says Yahweh.

12 “But go now to my place which was in Shiloh, where I caused my name to dwell at the first, and see what I did to it for the wickedness of my people Israel. 13 Now, because you have done all these works,” says Yahweh, “and I spoke to you, rising up early and speaking, but you didn’t hear; and I called you, but you didn’t answer: 14 therefore will I do to the house which is called by my name, in which you trust, and to the place which I gave to you and to your fathers, as I did to Shiloh. 15 I will cast you out of my sight, as I have cast out all your brothers, even the whole offspring[*] of Ephraim.

16 “Therefore don’t pray for this people, neither lift up a cry nor prayer for them, neither make intercession to me; for I will not hear you. 17 Don’t you see what they do in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem? 18 The children gather wood, and the fathers kindle the fire, and the women knead the dough, to make cakes to the queen of the sky, and to pour out drink offerings to other gods, that they may provoke me to anger. 19 Do they provoke me to anger? says Yahweh. “Don’t they provoke themselves, to the confusion of their own faces?”

20 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Behold, my anger and my wrath shall be poured out on this place, on man, and on animal, and on the trees of the field, and on the fruit of the ground; and it shall burn, and shall not be quenched.”

21 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says: “Add your burnt offerings to your sacrifices, and eat meat. 22 For I didn’t speak to your fathers, nor command them in the day that I brought them out of the land of Egypt, concerning burnt offerings or sacrifices: 23 but this thing I commanded them, saying, ‘Listen to my voice, and I will be your God, and you shall be my people; and walk in all the way that I command you, that it may be well with you.’ 24 But they didn’t listen nor turn their ear, but walked in their own counsels and in the stubbornness of their evil heart, and went backward, and not forward. 25 Since the day that your fathers came out of the land of Egypt to this day, I have sent to you all my servants the prophets, daily rising up early and sending them: 26 yet they didn’t listen to me, nor did they incline their ear, but made their neck stiff. They did worse than their fathers.

27 “You shall speak all these words to them; but they will not listen to you: you shall also call to them; but they will not answer you. 28 You shall tell them, ‘This is the nation that has not listened to Yahweh their God’s voice, nor received instruction. Truth has perished, and is cut off from their mouth.’ 29 Cut off your hair, and throw it away, and take up a lamentation on the bare heights; for Yahweh has rejected and forsaken the generation of his wrath.

30 “For the children of Judah have done that which is evil in my sight,” says Yahweh. “They have set their abominations in the house which is called by my name, to defile it. 31 They have built the high places of Topheth, which is in the valley of the son of Hinnom, to burn their sons and their daughters in the fire; which I didn’t command, nor did it come into my mind. 32 Therefore behold, the days come”, says Yahweh, “that it shall no more be called Topheth, nor The valley of the son of Hinnom, but The valley of Slaughter; for they shall bury in Topheth, until there is no place to bury. 33 The dead bodies of this people shall be food for the birds of the sky, and for the animals of the earth; and no one shall frighten them away. 34 Then I will cause to cease from the cities of Judah, and from the streets of Jerusalem, the voice of mirth and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride; for the land shall become a waste.”

or, seed

Jeremiah 8

1 “At that time,” says Yahweh, “they shall bring out the bones of the kings of Judah, and the bones of his princes, and the bones of the priests, and the bones of the prophets, and the bones of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, out of their graves; 2 and they shall spread them before the sun, and the moon, and all the army of the sky, which they have loved, and which they have served, and after which they have walked, and which they have sought, and which they have worshiped: they shall not be gathered, nor be buried, they shall be for dung on the surface of the earth. 3 Death shall be chosen rather than life by all the residue that remain of this evil family, that remain in all the places where I have driven them,” says Yahweh of Armies. 4 “Moreover you shall tell them, ‘Yahweh says:

“‘Shall men fall, and not rise up again?

Shall one turn away, and not return?

5 Why then have the people of Jerusalem fallen back by a perpetual backsliding?

They cling to deceit, they refuse to return.

6 I listened and heard, but they didn’t say what is right.

No one repents of his wickedness, saying, “What have I done?”

Everyone turns to his course,

as a horse that rushes headlong in the battle.

7 Yes, the stork in the sky knows her appointed times;

and the turtledove, the swallow, and the crane observe the time of their coming;

but my people don’t know Yahweh’s law.

8 “‘How do you say, “We are wise, and Yahweh’s law is with us?”

But, behold, the false pen of the scribes has worked falsely.

9 The wise men are disappointed.

They are dismayed and trapped.

Behold, they have rejected Yahweh’s word.

What kind of wisdom is in them?

10 Therefore will I give their wives to others,

and their fields to those who shall possess them.

For everyone from the least even to the greatest is given to covetousness;

from the prophet even to the priest everyone deals falsely.

11 They have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people slightly, saying,

“Peace, peace,” when there is no peace.

12 Were they ashamed when they had committed abomination?

No, they were not at all ashamed,

neither could they blush:

therefore they shall fall among those who fall;

in the time of their visitation they shall be cast down, says Yahweh.

13 “‘I will utterly consume them, says Yahweh:

no grapes shall be on the vine,

nor figs on the fig tree,

and the leaf shall fade;

and the things that I have given them

shall pass away from them.’”

14 “Why do we sit still?

Assemble yourselves,

and let us enter into the fortified cities,

and let us be silent there;

for Yahweh our God has put us to silence,

and given us water of gall to drink,

because we have sinned against Yahweh.

15 We looked for peace, but no good came;

and for a time of healing, and behold, dismay!

16 The snorting of his horses is heard from Dan:

at the sound of the neighing of his strong ones the whole land trembles;

for they have come, and have devoured the land and all that is in it;

the city and those who dwell therein.”

17 “For, behold, I will send serpents,

adders among you,

which will not be charmed;

and they shall bite you,” says Yahweh.

18 Oh that I could comfort myself against sorrow!

My heart is faint within me.

19 Behold, the voice of the cry of the daughter of my people from a land that is very far off:

“Isn’t Yahweh in Zion?

Isn’t her King in her?”

“Why have they provoked me to anger with their engraved images,

and with foreign vanities?”

20 “The harvest is past,

the summer is ended,

and we are not saved.”

21 For the hurt of the daughter of my people am I hurt:

I mourn; dismay has taken hold on me.

22 Is there no balm in Gilead?

is there no physician there?

Why then isn’t the health of the daughter of my people recovered?

Jeremiah 9

1 Oh that my head were waters,

and my eyes a spring of tears,

that I might weep day and night

for the slain of the daughter of my people!

2 Oh that I had in the wilderness

a lodging place of wayfaring men;

that I might leave my people,

and go from them!

For they are all adulterers,

an assembly of treacherous men.

3 “They bend their tongue,

as their bow, for falsehood;

and they have grown strong in the land,

but not for truth:

for they proceed from evil to evil,

and they don’t know me,” says Yahweh.

4 “Everyone beware of his neighbor,

and don’t trust in any brother;

for every brother will utterly supplant,

and every neighbor will go about with slanders.

5 Everyone will deceive their neighbors,

and will not speak the truth.

They have taught their tongue to speak lies.

They weary themselves commiting iniquity.

6 Your habitation is in the middle of deceit;

through deceit they refuse to know me,” says Yahweh.

7 Therefore Yahweh of Armies says,

“Behold, I will melt them, and try them;

for how should I deal with the daughter of my people?

8 Their tongue is a deadly arrow.

It speaks deceit.

One speaks peaceably to his neighbor with his mouth,

but in his heart, he lays wait for him.

9 Shall I not punish them for these things?” says Yahweh.

“Shouldn’t my soul be avenged on a nation such as this?

10 I will weep and wail for the mountains,

and lament for the pastures of the wilderness,

because they are burned up, so that no one passes through;

neither can men hear the voice of the livestock.

Both the birds of the sky and the animals have fled.

They are gone.

11 “I will make Jerusalem heaps,

a dwelling place of jackals.

I will make the cities of Judah a desolation,

without inhabitant.”

12 Who is wise enough to understand this? Who is he to whom the mouth of Yahweh has spoken, that he may declare it? Why is the land perished and burned up like a wilderness, so that no one passes through?

13 Yahweh says, “Because they have forsaken my law which I set before them, and have not obeyed my voice, neither walked therein, 14 but have walked after the stubbornness of their own heart, and after the Baals, which their fathers taught them.” 15 therefore Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says, “Behold, I will feed them, even this people, with wormwood, and give them water of gall to drink. 16 I will scatter them also among the nations, whom neither they nor their fathers have known; and I will send the sword after them, until I have consumed them.”

17 Yahweh of Armies says,

“Consider, and call for the mourning women, that they may come;

and send for the skillful women, that they may come.

18 Let them make haste,

and take up a wailing for us,

that our eyes may run down with tears,

and our eyelids gush out with waters.

19 For a voice of wailing is heard out of Zion,

‘How are we ruined!

We are greatly confounded,

because we have forsaken the land,

because they have cast down our dwellings.’”

20 Yet hear Yahweh’s word, you women,

and let your ear receive the word of his mouth.

Teach your daughters wailing,

and everyone her neighbor lamentation.

21 For death has come up into our windows.

It has entered into our palaces;

to cut off the children from outside,

and the young men from the streets.

22 Speak, “Yahweh says,

“‘The dead bodies of men will fall as dung on the open field,

and as the handful after the harvester;

and no one will gather them.’”

23 Yahweh says,

“Don’t let the wise man glory in his wisdom,

neither let the mighty man glory in his might.

Don’t let the rich man glory in his riches.

24 But let him who glories glory in this,

that he has understanding, and knows me,

that I am Yahweh who exercises loving kindness, justice, and righteousness, in the earth:

for in these things I delight,” says Yahweh.

25 “Behold, the days come,” says Yahweh, “that I will punish all those who are circumcised only in their flesh: 26 Egypt, and Judah, and Edom, and the children of Ammon, and Moab, and all that have the corners of their hair cut off, who dwell in the wilderness; for all the nations are uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in heart.”

Jeremiah 10

1 Hear the word which Yahweh speaks to you, house of Israel! 2 Yahweh says,

“Don’t learn the way of the nations,

and don’t be dismayed at the signs of the sky;

for the nations are dismayed at them.

3 For the customs of the peoples are vanity;

for one cuts a tree out of the forest,

the work of the hands of the workman with the ax.

4 They deck it with silver and with gold;

they fasten it with nails and with hammers,

that it not move.

5 They are like a palm tree, of turned work,

and don’t speak:

they must be carried,

because they can’t move.

Don’t be afraid of them;

for they can’t do evil,

neither is it in them to do good.”

6 There is no one like you, Yahweh.

you are great,

and your name is great in might.

7 Who should not fear you,

King of the nations?

For it belongs to you.

Because among all the wise men of the nations,

and in all their royal estate,

there is no one like you.

8 But they are together brutish and foolish,

instructed by idols!

It is just wood.

9 There is silver beaten into plates, which is brought from Tarshish,

and gold from Uphaz,

the work of the artificer and of the hands of the goldsmith;

Blue and purple are their clothing;

they are all the work of skillful men.

10 But Yahweh is the true God;

he is the living God,

and an everlasting King.

At his wrath, the earth trembles,

and the nations are not able to withstand his indignation.

11 “You shall say this to them: ‘The gods that have not made the heavens and the earth, these shall perish from the earth, and from under the heavens.’”

12 He has made the earth by his power.

he has established the world by his wisdom,

and by his understanding has he stretched out the heavens.

13 when he utters his voice,

there is a tumult of waters in the heavens,

and he causes the vapors to ascend from the ends of the earth.

He makes lightnings for the rain,

and brings the wind out of his treasuries.

14 Every man has become brutish and without knowledge;

every goldsmith is disappointed by his engraved image;

for his molten image is falsehood,

and there is no breath in them.

15 They are vanity, a work of delusion.

In the time of their visitation they will perish.

16 The portion of Jacob is not like these;

for he is the former of all things;

and Israel is the tribe of his inheritance:

Yahweh of Armies is his name.

17 Gather up your wares out of the land,

you who live under siege.

18 For Yahweh says,

“Behold, I will sling out the inhabitants of the land at this time,

and will distress them, that they may feel it.”

19 Woe is me because of my injury!

My wound is serious:

but I said,

“Truly this is my grief, and I must bear it.”

20 My tent is destroyed,

and all my cords are broken.

My children have gone away from me, and they are no more.

There is no one to spread my tent any more,

and to set up my curtains.

21 For the shepherds have become brutish,

and have not inquired of Yahweh.

Therefore they have not prospered,

and all their flocks are scattered.

22 The voice of news, behold, it comes,

and a great commotion out of the north country,

to make the cities of Judah a desolation,

a dwelling place of jackals.

23 Yahweh, I know that the way of man is not in himself:

it is not in man who walks to direct his steps.

24 Yahweh, correct me, but in measure:

not in your anger,

lest you bring me to nothing.

25 Pour out your wrath on the nations that don’t know you,

and on the families that don’t call on your name:

for they have devoured Jacob.

Yes, they have devoured him and consumed him,

and have laid waste his habitation.

Jeremiah 12

1 You are righteous, Yahweh,

when I contend with you;

yet I would reason the cause with you:

why does the way of the wicked prosper?

why are all they at ease who deal very treacherously?

2 You have planted them, yes, they have taken root;

they grow, yes, they produce fruit.

You are near in their mouth,

and far from their heart.

3 But you, Yahweh, know me;

you see me, and try my heart toward you.

Pull them out like sheep for the slaughter,

and prepare them for the day of slaughter.

4 How long shall the land mourn,

and the herbs of the whole country wither?

For the wickedness of those who dwell therein,

the animals are consumed, and the birds;

because they said,

“He shall not see our latter end.”

5 “If you have run with the footmen,

and they have wearied you,

then how can you contend with horses?

Though in a land of peace you are secure,

yet how will you do in the pride of the Jordan?

6 For even your brothers, and the house of your father,

even they have dealt treacherously with you;

even they have cried aloud after you!

Don’t believe them,

though they speak beautiful words to you.

7 “I have forsaken my house.

I have cast off my heritage.

I have given the dearly beloved of my soul into the hand of her enemies.

8 My heritage has become to me as a lion in the forest.

She has uttered her voice against me;

therefore I have hated her.

9 Is my heritage to me as a speckled bird of prey?

Are the birds of prey against her all around?

Go, assemble all the animals of the field,

bring them to devour.

10 Many shepherds have destroyed my vineyard.

They have trodden my portion under foot.

They have made my pleasant portion a desolate wilderness.

11 They have made it a desolation.

It mourns to me, being desolate.

The whole land is made desolate,

because no man lays it to heart.

12 Destroyers have come on all the bare heights in the wilderness;

for the sword of Yahweh devours from the one end of the land even to the other end of the land.

No flesh has peace.

13 They have sown wheat,

and have reaped thorns.

They have put themselves to pain,

and profit nothing.

You shall be ashamed of your fruits,

because of the fierce anger of Yahweh.”

14 Yahweh says, “Concerning all my evil neighbors, who touch the inheritance which I have caused my people Israel to inherit: behold, I will pluck them up from off their land, and will pluck up the house of Judah from among them. 15 It shall happen, after that I have plucked them up, I will return and have compassion on them; and I will bring them again, every man to his heritage, and every man to his land. 16 It shall happen, if they will diligently learn the ways of my people, to swear by my name, ‘As Yahweh lives;’ even as they taught my people to swear by Baal; then shall they be built up in the middle of my people. 17 But if they will not hear, then I will pluck up that nation, plucking up and destroying it,” says Yahweh.

Jeremiah 13

1 Yahweh says to me, “Go, and buy yourself a linen belt, and put it on your waist, and don’t put it in water.”

2 So I bought a belt according to Yahweh’s word, and put it on my waist.

3 Yahweh’s word came to me the second time, saying, 4 “Take the belt that you have bought, which is on your waist, and arise, go to the Euphrates, and hide it there in a cleft of the rock.”

5 So I went, and hid it by the Euphrates, as Yahweh commanded me.

6 After many days, Yahweh said to me, “Arise, go to the Euphrates, and take the belt from there, which I commanded you to hide there.”

7 Then I went to the Euphrates, and dug, and took the belt from the place where I had hidden it; and behold, the belt was ruined. It was profitable for nothing.

8 Then Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 9 “Yahweh says, ‘In this way I, will ruin the pride of Judah, and the great pride of Jerusalem. 10 This evil people, who refuse to hear my words, who walk in the stubbornness of their heart, and are gone after other gods to serve them, and to worship them, shall even be as this belt, which is profitable for nothing. 11 For as the belt clings to the waist of a man, so I have caused to cling to me the whole house of Israel and the whole house of Judah,’ says Yahweh; ‘that they may be to me for a people, and for a name, and for a praise, and for a glory: but they would not hear.’

12 “Therefore you shall speak to them this word: ‘Yahweh, the God of Israel says, “Every bottle shall be filled with wine.”’ They will tell you, ‘Do we not certainly know that every bottle shall be filled with wine?’ 13 Then tell them, ‘Yahweh says, “Behold, I will fill all the inhabitants of this land, even the kings who sit on David’s throne, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, with drunkenness. 14 I will dash them one against another, even the fathers and the sons together,” says Yahweh: “I will not pity, nor spare, nor have compassion, that I should not destroy them.”’”

15 Hear, and give ear.

Don’t be proud;

for Yahweh has spoken.

16 Give glory to Yahweh your God,

before he causes darkness,

and before your feet stumble on the dark mountains,

and, while you look for light,

he turns it into the shadow of death,

and makes it gross darkness.

17 But if you will not hear it,

my soul shall weep in secret for your pride;

and my eye shall weep bitterly,

and run down with tears,

because Yahweh’s flock is taken captive.

18 Say to the king and to the queen mother,

“Humble yourselves, sit down;

for your headdresses have come down,

even the crown of your glory.

19 The cities of the South are shut up,

and there is no one to open them.

Judah is carried away captive, all of it;

it is wholly carried away captive.

20 Lift up your eyes,

and see those who come from the north.

where is the flock that was given you,

your beautiful flock?

21 What will you say, when he shall set over you as head those whom you have yourself taught to be friends to you?

Shall not sorrows take hold of you, as of a woman in travail?

22 If you say in your heart,

“Why are these things come on me?”

For the greatness of your iniquity your skirts are uncovered,

and your heels suffer violence.

23 Can the Ethiopian change his skin,

or the leopard his spots?

Then may you also do good,

who are accustomed to do evil.

24 “Therefore I will scatter them,

as the stubble that passes away,

by the wind of the wilderness.

25 This is your lot,

the portion measured to you from me,” says Yahweh;

“because you have forgotten me,

and trusted in falsehood.”

26 Therefore will I also uncover your skirts on your face,

and your shame shall appear.

27 I have seen your abominations, even your adulteries,

and your neighing, the lewdness of your prostitution,

on the hills in the field.

Woe to you, Jerusalem!

You will not be made clean; how long shall it yet be?”

Jeremiah 14

1 This is Yahweh’s word that came to Jeremiah concerning the drought.

2 “Judah mourns,

and its gates languish,

they sit in black on the ground;

and the cry of Jerusalem goes up.

3 Their nobles send their little ones to the waters.

They come to the cisterns,

and find no water.

They return with their vessels empty.

They are disappointed and confounded,

and cover their heads.

4 Because of the ground which is cracked,

because no rain has been in the land.

The plowmen are disappointed.

They cover their heads.

5 Yes, the hind also in the field calves, and forsakes her young,

because there is no grass.

6 The wild donkeys stand on the bare heights.

They pant for air like jackals.

Their eyes fail,

because there is no vegetation.

7 Though our iniquities testify against us,

work for your name’s sake, Yahweh;

for our rebellions are many.

We have sinned against you.

8 You hope of Israel,

its Savior in the time of trouble,

why should you be as a foreigner in the land,

and as a wayfaring man who turns aside to stay for a night?

9 Why should you be like a scared man,

as a mighty man who can’t save?

Yet you, Yahweh, are in the middle of us,

and we are called by your name.

Don’t leave us.

10 Yahweh says to this people,

“Even so they have loved to wander.

They have not restrained their feet.

Therefore Yahweh does not accept them.

Now he will remember their iniquity,

and punish them for their sins.”

11 Yahweh said to me, “Don’t pray for this people for their good. 12 When they fast, I will not hear their cry; and when they offer burnt offering and meal offering, I will not accept them; but I will consume them by the sword, and by the famine, and by the pestilence.”

13 Then I said, “Ah, Lord Yahweh! Behold, the prophets tell them, ‘You will not see the sword, neither shall you have famine; but I will give you assured peace in this place.’”

14 Then Yahweh said to me, “The prophets prophesy lies in my name. I didn’t send them, neither have I commanded them, neither did I speak to them. They prophesy to you a lying vision, divination, and a thing of nothing, and the deceit of their own heart. 15 Therefore Yahweh says concerning the prophets who prophesy in my name, and I didn’t send them, yet they say, ‘Sword and famine will not be in this land.’ Those prophets will be consumed by sword and famine. 16 The people to whom they prophesy shall be cast out in the streets of Jerusalem because of the famine and the sword. They shall have no one to bury them—them, their wives, nor their sons, nor their daughters: for I will pour their wickedness on them.

17 “You shall say this word to them,

“‘Let my eyes run down with tears night and day,

and let them not cease;

for the virgin daughter of my people is broken with a great breach,

with a very grievous wound.

18 If I go out into the field,

then, behold, the slain with the sword!

If I enter into the city,

then, behold, those who are sick with famine!

For both the prophet and the priest go about in the land,

and have no knowledge.’”

19 Have you utterly rejected Judah?

Has your soul loathed Zion?

Why have you struck us, and there is no healing for us?

We looked for peace, but no good came;

and for a time of healing, and behold, dismay!

20 We acknowledge, Yahweh, our wickedness,

and the iniquity of our fathers;

for we have sinned against you.

21 Do not abhor us, for your name’s sake.

Do not disgrace the throne of your glory.

Remember, and don’t break your covenant with us.

22 Are there any among the vanities of the nations that can cause rain?

Or can the sky give showers?

Aren’t you he, Yahweh our God?

Therefore we will wait for you;

for you have made all these things.

Jeremiah 15

1 Then Yahweh said to me, “Though Moses and Samuel stood before me, yet my mind would not be toward this people. Cast them out of my sight, and let them go out! 2 It shall happen, when they tell you, ‘Where shall we go out?’ Then you shall tell them, ‘Yahweh says:

“Such as are for death, to death;

and such as are for the sword, to the sword;

and such as are for the famine, to the famine;

and such as are for captivity, to captivity.”’

3 “I will appoint over them four kinds,” says Yahweh: “the sword to kill, and the dogs to tear, and the birds of the sky, and the animals of the earth, to devour and to destroy. 4 I will cause them to be tossed back and forth among all the kingdoms of the earth, because of Manasseh, the son of Hezekiah, king of Judah, for that which he did in Jerusalem.

5 For who will have pity on you, Jerusalem?

or who will bemoan you?

or who will turn aside to ask of your welfare?

6 You have rejected me,” says Yahweh.

“You have gone backward:

therefore I have stretched out my hand against you,

and destroyed you;

I am weary with repenting.

7 I have winnowed them with a fan in the gates of the land;

I have bereaved them of children.

I have destroyed my people.

They didn’t return from their ways.

8 Their widows are increased to me above the sand of the seas;

I have brought on them against the mother of the young men a destroyer at noonday.

I have caused anguish and terrors to fall on her suddenly.

9 She who has borne seven languishes;

she has given up the spirit.

Her sun has gone down while it was yet day.

She has been disappointed and confounded:

and their residue will I deliver to the sword before their enemies,” says Yahweh.

10 Woe is me, my mother, that you have borne me a man of strife

and a man of contention to the whole earth!

I have not lent, neither have men lent to me;

yet everyone of them curses me.

11 Yahweh said,

“Most certainly I will strengthen you for good.

Most certainly I will cause the enemy to make supplication to you in the time of evil

and in the time of affliction.

12 Can one break iron,

even iron from the north, and brass?

13 Your substance and your treasures will I give for a plunder without price,

and that for all your sins,

even in all your borders.

14 I will make them to pass with your enemies into a land which you don’t know;

for a fire is kindled in my anger,

which shall burn on you.”

15 Yahweh, you know;

remember me, and visit me,

and avenge me of my persecutors.

You are patient, so don’t take me away.

Know that for your sake I have suffered reproach.

16 Your words were found,

and I ate them.

Your words were to me a joy and the rejoicing of my heart,

for I am called by your name, Yahweh, God of Armies.

17 I didn’t sit in the assembly of those who make merry, nor rejoiced;

I sat alone because of your hand;

for you have filled me with indignation.

18 Why is my pain perpetual,

and my wound incurable,

which refuses to be healed?

Will you indeed be to me as a deceitful brook,

like waters that fail?

19 Therefore Yahweh says,

“If you return, then I will bring you again,

that you may stand before me;

and if you take out the precious from the vile,

you shall be as my mouth.

They shall return to you,

but you shall not return to them.

20 I will make you to this people a fortified bronze wall;

and they shall fight against you,

but they shall not prevail against you;

for I am with you to save you

and to deliver you,” says Yahweh.

21 “I will deliver you out of the hand of the wicked,

and I will redeem you out of the hand of the terrible.”

Jeremiah 17

1 “The sin of Judah is written with a pen of iron,

and with the point of a diamond.

It is engraved on the tablet of their heart,

and on the horns of your altars.

2 Even their children remember their altars

and their Asherah poles by the green trees on the high hills.

3 My mountain in the field,

I will give your substance and all your treasures for a plunder,

and your high places, because of sin, throughout all your borders.

4 You, even of yourself, shall discontinue from your heritage that I gave you.

I will cause you to serve your enemies in the land which you don’t know,

for you have kindled a fire in my anger which shall burn forever.”

5 Yahweh says:

“Cursed is the man who trusts in man,

and makes flesh his arm,

and whose heart departs from Yahweh.

6 For he shall be like a bush in the desert,

and shall not see when good comes,

but shall inhabit the parched places in the wilderness,

a salt land and not inhabited.

7 “Blessed is the man who trusts in Yahweh,

and whose confidence is in Yahweh.

8 For he shall be as a tree planted by the waters,

who spreads out its roots by the river,

and shall not fear when heat comes,

but its leaf shall be green;

and shall not be careful in the year of drought,

neither shall cease from yielding fruit.

9 The heart is deceitful above all things,

and it is exceedingly corrupt.

Who can know it?

10 “I, Yahweh, search the mind,

I try the heart,

even to give every man according to his ways,

according to the fruit of his doings.”

11 As the partridge that sits on eggs which she has not laid,

so is he who gets riches, and not by right;

in the middle of his days they shall leave him,

and at his end he shall be a fool.

12 A glorious throne, set on high from the beginning,

is the place of our sanctuary.

13 Yahweh, the hope of Israel,

all who forsake you shall be disappointed.

Those who depart from me shall be written in the earth,

because they have forsaken Yahweh,

the spring of living waters.

14 Heal me, O Yahweh, and I shall be healed;

save me, and I shall be saved:

for you are my praise.

15 Behold, they tell me,

“Where is Yahweh’s word?

Let it be fulfilled now.”

16 As for me, I have not hurried from being a shepherd after you;

neither have I desired the woeful day; you know.

That which came out of my lips was before your face.

17 Don’t be a terror to me:

you are my refuge in the day of evil.

18 Let them be disappointed who persecute me,

but let not me be disappointed;

let them be dismayed,

but don’t let me be dismayed;

bring on them the day of evil,

and destroy them with double destruction.

19 Thus said Yahweh to me: “Go, and stand in the gate of the children of the people, through which the kings of Judah come in, and by which they go out, and in all the gates of Jerusalem; 20 and tell them, ‘Hear Yahweh’s word, you kings of Judah, and all Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, that enter in by these gates: 21 Yahweh says, “Be careful, and bear no burden on the Sabbath day, nor bring it in by the gates of Jerusalem; 22 neither carry a burden out of your houses on the Sabbath day, neither do any work: but make the Sabbath day holy, as I commanded your fathers. 23 But they didn’t listen, neither turn their ear, but made their neck stiff, that they might not hear, and might not receive instruction. 24 It shall happen, if you diligently listen to me,” says Yahweh, “to bring in no burden through the gates of this city on the Sabbath day, but to make the Sabbath day holy, to do no work therein; 25 then shall there enter in by the gates of this city kings and princes sitting on David’s throne, riding in chariots and on horses, they, and their princes, the men of Judah, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and this city shall remain forever. 26 They shall come from the cities of Judah, and from the places around Jerusalem, and from the land of Benjamin, and from the lowland, and from the hill country, and from the South, bringing burnt offerings, and sacrifices, and meal offerings, and frankincense, and bringing sacrifices of thanksgiving, to Yahweh’s house. 27 But if you will not listen to me to make the Sabbath day holy, and not to bear a burden and enter in at the gates of Jerusalem on the Sabbath day; then I will kindle a fire in its gates, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem, and it shall not be quenched.”’”

Jeremiah 18

1 The word which came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, saying, 2 “Arise, and go down to the potter’s house, and there I will cause you to hear my words.”

3 Then I went down to the potter’s house, and behold, he was making a work on the wheels. 4 When the vessel that he made of the clay was marred in the hand of the potter, he made it again another vessel, as seemed good to the potter to make it.

5 Then Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 6 “House of Israel, can’t I do with you as this potter?” says Yahweh. “Behold, as the clay in the potter’s hand, so are you in my hand, house of Israel. 7 At what instant I shall speak concerning a nation, and concerning a kingdom, to pluck up and to break down and to destroy it; 8 if that nation, concerning which I have spoken, turn from their evil, I will repent of the evil that I thought to do to them. 9 At what instant I shall speak concerning a nation, and concerning a kingdom, to build and to plant it; 10 if they do that which is evil in my sight, that they not obey my voice, then I will repent of the good, with which I said I would benefit them.

11 “Now therefore, speak to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying, ‘Yahweh says: “Behold, I frame evil against you, and devise a device against you. Everyone return from his evil way now, and amend your ways and your doings.”’ 12 But they say, ‘It is in vain; for we will walk after our own devices, and we will do everyone after the stubbornness of his evil heart.’”

13 Therefore Yahweh says:

“Ask now among the nations,

who has heard such things.

The virgin of Israel has done a very horrible thing.

14 Shall the snow of Lebanon fail from the rock of the field?

Shall the cold waters that flow down from afar be dried up?

15 For my people have forgotten me.

They have burned incense to false gods.

They have been made to stumble in their ways,

in the ancient paths,

to walk in byways, in a way not built up;

16 to make their land an astonishment,

and a perpetual hissing.

Everyone who passes thereby shall be astonished,

and shake his head.

17 I will scatter them as with an east wind before the enemy.

I will show them the back, and not the face,

in the day of their calamity.

18 Then they said, “Come, and let us devise devices against Jeremiah; for the law shall not perish from the priest, nor counsel from the wise, nor the word from the prophet. Come, and let us strike him with the tongue, and let us not give heed to any of his words.”

19 Give heed to me, Yahweh,

and listen to the voice of those who contend with me.

20 Shall evil be recompensed for good?

For they have dug a pit for my soul.

Remember how I stood before you to speak good for them,

to turn away your wrath from them.

21 Therefore deliver up their children to the famine,

and give them over to the power of the sword.

Let their wives become childless, and widows;

and let their men be slain of death,

and their young men struck by the sword in battle.

22 Let a cry be heard from their houses,

when you shall bring a troop suddenly on them;

for they have dug a pit to take me,

and hidden snares for my feet.

23 Yet, Yahweh, you know all their counsel against me to kill me.

Don’t forgive their iniquity,

neither blot out their sin from your sight;

but let them be overthrown before you.

Deal you with them in the time of your anger.

Jeremiah 20

1 Now Pashhur, the son of Immer the priest, who was chief officer in Yahweh’s house, heard Jeremiah prophesying these things. 2 Then Pashhur struck Jeremiah the prophet, and put him in the stocks that were in the upper gate of Benjamin, which was in Yahweh’s house. 3 On the next day, Pashhur released Jeremiah out of the stocks. Then Jeremiah said to him, “Yahweh has not called your name Pashhur, but Magormissabib. 4 For Yahweh says, ‘Behold, I will make you a terror to yourself, and to all your friends; and they shall fall by the sword of their enemies, and your eyes shall see it; and I will give all Judah into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall carry them captive to Babylon, and shall kill them with the sword. 5 Moreover I will give all the riches of this city, and all its gains, and all the precious things of it, yes, all the treasures of the kings of Judah will I give into the hand of their enemies; and they shall make them captives, and take them, and carry them to Babylon. 6 You, Pashhur, and all who dwell in your house shall go into captivity; and you shall come to Babylon, and there you shall die, and there you shall be buried, you, and all your friends, to whom you have prophesied falsely.’”

7 Yahweh, you have persuaded me, and I was persuaded;

you are stronger than I, and have prevailed.

I have become a laughing-stock all day.

Every one mocks me.

8 For as often as I speak, I cry out;

I cry, Violence and destruction!

because Yahweh’s word has been made a reproach to me,

and a derision, all day.

9 If I say, I will not make mention of him,

nor speak any more in his name,

then there is in my heart as it were a burning fire shut up in my bones,

and I am weary with holding it in,

and I can’t.

10 For I have heard the defaming of many,

“Terror on every side!

Denounce, and we will denounce him!”

say all my familiar friends,

those who watch for my fall.

“Perhaps he will be persuaded,

and we shall prevail against him,

and we shall take our revenge on him.”

11 But Yahweh is with me as an awesome mighty one.

Therefore my persecutors shall stumble,

and they shall not prevail.

They shall be utterly disappointed,

because they have not dealt wisely,

even with an everlasting dishonor which shall never be forgotten.

12 But, Yahweh of Armies, who tests the righteous,

who sees the heart and the mind,

let me see your vengeance on them;

for to you I have revealed my cause.

13 Sing to Yahweh,

praise Yahweh;

for he has delivered the soul of the needy from the hand of evildoers.

14 Cursed is the day in which I was born.

Don’t let the day in which my mother bore me be blessed.

15 Cursed is the man who brought news to my father, saying,

“A boy is born to you,” making him very glad.

16 Let that man be as the cities which Yahweh overthrew,

and didn’t repent.

Let him hear a cry in the morning,

and shouting at noontime;

17 because he didn’t kill me from the womb;

and so my mother would have been my grave,

and her womb always great.

18 Why did I come out of the womb to see labor and sorrow,

that my days should be consumed with shame?

Jeremiah 21

1 The word which came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, when king Zedekiah sent to him Pashhur the son of Malchijah, and Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, saying, 2 “Please inquire of Yahweh for us; for Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon makes war against us. Perhaps Yahweh will deal with us according to all his wondrous works, that he may withdraw from us.”

3 Then Jeremiah said to them, “Tell Zedekiah: 4 ‘Yahweh, the God of Israel says, “Behold, I will turn back the weapons of war that are in your hands, with which you fight against the king of Babylon, and against the Chaldeans who besiege you, without the walls; and I will gather them into the middle of this city. 5 I myself will fight against you with an outstretched hand and with a strong arm, even in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation. 6 I will strike the inhabitants of this city, both man and animal. They will die of a great pestilence. 7 Afterward,” says Yahweh, “I will deliver Zedekiah king of Judah, and his servants, and the people, even those who are left in this city from the pestilence, from the sword, and from the famine, into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of those who seek their life. He will strike them with the edge of the sword. He will not spare them, neither have pity, nor have mercy.”’

8 “To this people you shall say, ‘Yahweh says: “Behold, I set before you the way of life and the way of death. 9 He who remains in this city will die by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence; but he who goes out, and passes over to the Chaldeans who besiege you, he shall live, and he will escape with his life. 10 For I have set my face on this city for evil, and not for good,” says Yahweh. “It will be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall burn it with fire.”’

11 “Concerning the house of the king of Judah, hear Yahweh’s word. 12 House of David, Yahweh says,

‘Execute justice in the morning,

and deliver him who is robbed out of the hand of the oppressor,

lest my wrath go out like fire,

and burn so that no one can quench it,

because of the evil of your doings.

13 Behold, I am against you, O inhabitant of the valley,

and of the rock of the plain,’ says Yahweh.

‘You that say, “Who would come down against us?”

or “Who would enter into our homes?”

14 I will punish you according to the fruit of your doings, says Yahweh;

and I will kindle a fire in her forest,

and it shall devour all that is around her.’”

Jeremiah 22

1 Thus said Yahweh: “Go down to the house of the king of Judah, and speak there this word, 2 ‘Hear Yahweh’s word, king of Judah, who sits on David’s throne, you, and your servants, and your people who enter in by these gates. 3 Yahweh says: “Execute justice and righteousness, and deliver him who is robbed out of the hand of the oppressor. Do no wrong. Do no violence, to the foreigner, the fatherless, nor the widow; neither shed innocent blood in this place. 4 For if you do this thing indeed, then shall there enter in by the gates of this house kings sitting on David’s throne, riding in chariots and on horses, he, and his servants, and his people. 5 But if you will not hear these words, I swear by myself,” says Yahweh, “that this house shall become a desolation.”’”

6 For Yahweh says concerning the house of the king of Judah:

“You are Gilead to me,

the head of Lebanon.

Yet surely I will make you a wilderness,

cities which are not inhabited.

7 I will prepare destroyers against you,

everyone with his weapons,

and they will cut down your choice cedars,

and cast them into the fire.

8 “Many nations will pass by this city, and they will each ask his neighbor, ‘Why has Yahweh done this to this great city?’ 9 Then they shall answer, ‘Because they abandoned the covenant of Yahweh their God, and worshiped other gods, and served them.’”

10 Don’t weep for the dead,

neither bemoan him;

but weep bitterly for him who goes away;

for he shall return no more,

nor see his native country.

11 For Yahweh says touching Shallum the son of Josiah, king of Judah, who reigned instead of Josiah his father, and who went out of this place: “He shall not return there any more. 12 But in the place where they have led him captive, there shall he die, and he shall see this land no more.”

13 “Woe to him who builds his house by unrighteousness,

and his rooms by injustice;

who uses his neighbor’s service without wages,

and doesn’t give him his hire;

14 who says, ‘I will build me a wide house and spacious rooms,’

and cuts out windows for himself;

and it is ceiling with cedar,

and painted with vermilion.

15 “Shall you reign, because you strive to excel in cedar?

Didn’t your father eat and drink,

and do justice and righteousness?

Then it was well with him.

16 He judged the cause of the poor and needy;

then it was well.

Wasn’t this to know me?”

says Yahweh.

17 But your eyes and your heart are not but for your covetousness,

and for shedding innocent blood,

for oppression, and for doing violence.”

18 Therefore Yahweh says concerning Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah:

“They shall not lament for him,

saying, ‘Ah my brother!’ or, ‘Ah sister!’

They shall not lament for him,

saying ‘Ah lord!’ or, ‘Ah his glory!’

19 He shall be buried with the burial of a donkey,

drawn and cast out beyond the gates of Jerusalem.”

20 “Go up to Lebanon, and cry;

and lift up your voice in Bashan,

and cry from Abarim;

for all your lovers are destroyed.

21 I spoke to you in your prosperity;

but you said, ‘I will not listen.’

This has been your way from your youth,

that you didn’t obey my voice.

22 The wind shall feed all your shepherds,

and your lovers shall go into captivity.

Surely then you will be ashamed

and confounded for all your wickedness.

23 Inhabitant of Lebanon,

who makes your nest in the cedars,

how greatly to be pitied you will be when pangs come on you,

the pain as of a woman in travail!

24 “As I live,” says Yahweh, “though Coniah the son of Jehoiakim king of Judah were the signet on my right hand, yet would I pluck you from there; 25 and I would give you into the hand of those who seek your life, and into the hand of them of whom you are afraid, even into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of the Chaldeans. 26 I will cast you out with your mother who bore you, into another country, where you were not born; and there you will die. 27 But to the land to which their soul longs to return, there shall they not return.”

28 Is this man Coniah a despised broken vessel?

Is he a vessel in which no one delights?

Why are they cast out, he and his offspring,[*]

and cast into a land which they don’t know?

29 O earth, earth, earth,

hear Yahweh’s word!

30 Yahweh says,

“Record this man as childless,

a man who will not prosper in his days;

for no more shall a man of his offspring[*] prosper,

sitting on David’s throne,

and ruling in Judah.”

or, seed

or, seed

Jeremiah 23

1 “Woe to the shepherds who destroy and scatter the sheep of my pasture!” says Yahweh. 2 Therefore Yahweh, the God of Israel, says against the shepherds who feed my people: “You have scattered my flock, and driven them away, and have not visited them; behold, I will visit on you the evil of your doings,” says Yahweh. 3 “I will gather the remnant of my flock out of all the countries where I have driven them, and will bring them again to their folds; and they shall be fruitful and multiply. 4 I will set up shepherds over them, who shall feed them; and they shall fear no more, nor be dismayed, neither shall any be lacking,” says Yahweh.

5 “Behold, the days come,” says Yahweh,

“that I will raise to David a righteous Branch,

and he shall reign as king and deal wisely,

and shall execute justice and righteousness in the land.

6 In his days Judah shall be saved,

and Israel shall dwell safely.

This is his name by which he shall be called:

Yahweh our righteousness.

7 “Therefore behold, the days come,” says Yahweh, “that they shall no more say, ‘As Yahweh lives, who brought up the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt;’ 8 but, ‘As Yahweh lives, who brought up and who led the offspring[*] of the house of Israel out of the north country, and from all the countries where I had driven them.’ Then they will dwell in their own land.”

9 Concerning the prophets:

My heart within me is broken.

All my bones shake.

I am like a drunken man,

and like a man whom wine has overcome,

because of Yahweh,

and because of his holy words.

10 For the land is full of adulterers;

for because of the curse the land mourns.

The pastures of the wilderness are dried up.

Their course is evil,

and their might is not right;

11 for both prophet and priest are profane;

yes, in my house I have found their wickedness,” says Yahweh.

12 Therefore their way shall be to them as slippery places in the darkness.

They shall be driven on,

and fall therein;

for I will bring evil on them,

even the year of their visitation,” says Yahweh.

13 “I have seen folly in the prophets of Samaria.

They prophesied by Baal,

and caused my people Israel to err.

14 In the prophets of Jerusalem also I have seen a horrible thing:

they commit adultery,

and walk in lies.

They strengthen the hands of evildoers,

so that no one returns from his wickedness.

They have all become to me as Sodom,

and its inhabitants as Gomorrah.”

15 Therefore Yahweh of Armies says concerning the prophets:

“Behold, I will feed them with wormwood,

and make them drink the water of gall;

for from the prophets of Jerusalem ungodliness has gone out into all the land.”

16 Yahweh of Armies says,

“Don’t listen to the words of the prophets who prophesy to you.

They teach you vanity.

They speak a vision of their own heart,

and not out of the mouth of Yahweh.

17 They say continually to those who despise me,

‘Yahweh has said, “You shall have peace;”’

and to everyone who walks in the stubbornness of his own heart they say,

‘No evil shall come on you.’

18 For who has stood in the council of Yahweh,

that he should perceive and hear his word?

Who has listend to my word, and heard it?

19 Behold, Yahweh’s storm, his wrath, has gone out.

Yes, a whirling storm.

It shall burst on the head of the wicked.

20 Yahweh’s anger shall not return, until he has executed,

and until he has performed the intents of his heart.

In the latter days, you will understand it perfectly.

21 I didn’t send these prophets, yet they ran.

I didn’t speak to them, yet they prophesied.

22 But if they had stood in my council,

then they would have caused my people to hear my words,

and would have turned them from their evil way,

and from the evil of their doings.

23 “Am I a God at hand,” says Yahweh,

“and not a God afar off?

24 Can anyone hide himself in secret places

so that I can’t see him?” says Yahweh.

“Don’t I fill heaven and earth?” says Yahweh.

25 “I have heard what the prophets have said, who prophesy lies in my name, saying, ‘I had a dream! I had a dream!’ 26 How long shall this be in the heart of the prophets who prophesy lies, even the prophets of the deceit of their own heart? 27 They intend to cause my people to forget my name by their dreams which they each tell his neighbor, as their fathers forgot my name because of Baal. 28 The prophet who has a dream, let him tell a dream; and he who has my word, let him speak my word faithfully. What is the straw to the wheat?” says Yahweh. 29 “Isn’t my word like fire?” says Yahweh; “and like a hammer that breaks the rock in pieces?

30 “Therefore behold, I am against the prophets,” says Yahweh, “who each steal my words from his neighbor. 31 Behold, I am against the prophets,” says Yahweh, “who use their tongues, and say, ‘He says.’ 32 Behold, I am against those who prophesy lying dreams,” says Yahweh, “who tell them, and cause my people to err by their lies, and by their vain boasting; yet I didn’t send them, nor command them; neither do they profit this people at all,” says Yahweh.

33 “When this people, or the prophet, or a priest, shall ask you, saying, ‘What is the message from Yahweh?’ Then you shall tell them, ‘“What message? I will cast you off,” says Yahweh.’ 34 As for the prophet, and the priest, and the people, who say, ‘The message from Yahweh,’ I will even punish that man and his household. 35 You shall say everyone to his neighbor, and everyone to his brother, ‘What has Yahweh answered?’ and, ‘What has Yahweh spoken?’ 36 You shall mention the message from Yahweh no more: for every man’s own word has become his message; for you have perverted the words of the living God, of Yahweh of Armies, our God. 37 You shall say to the prophet, ‘What has Yahweh answered you?’ and, ‘What has Yahweh spoken?’ 38 Although you say, ‘The message from Yahweh;’ therefore Yahweh says: ‘Because you say this word, “The message from Yahweh,” and I have sent to you, telling you not to say, “The message from Yahweh;” 39 therefore, behold, I will utterly forget you, and I will cast you off, and the city that I gave to you and to your fathers, away from my presence. 40 I will bring an everlasting reproach on you, and a perpetual shame, which shall not be forgotten.’”

or, seed

Jeremiah 24

1 Yahweh showed me, and behold, two baskets of figs set before Yahweh’s temple, after that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had carried away captive Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, and the princes of Judah, with the craftsmen and smiths, from Jerusalem, and had brought them to Babylon. 2 One basket had very good figs, like the figs that are first-ripe; and the other basket had very bad figs, which could not be eaten, they were so bad.

3 Then Yahweh asked me, “What do you see, Jeremiah?”

I said, “Figs. The good figs are very good, and the bad are very bad, so bad that can’t be eaten.”

4 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 5 “Yahweh, the God of Israel says: ‘Like these good figs, so will I regard the captives of Judah, whom I have sent out of this place into the land of the Chaldeans, for good. 6 For I will set my eyes on them for good, and I will bring them again to this land. I will build them, and not pull them down. I will plant them, and not pluck them up. 7 I will give them a heart to know me, that I am Yahweh: and they shall be my people, and I will be their God; for they shall return to me with their whole heart.

8 “‘As the bad figs, which can’t be eaten, they are so bad,’ surely Yahweh says, ‘So I will give up Zedekiah the king of Judah, and his princes, and the remnant of Jerusalem, who remain in this land, and those who dwell in the land of Egypt. 9 I will even give them up to be tossed back and forth among all the kingdoms of the earth for evil; to be a reproach and a proverb, a taunt and a curse, in all places where I shall drive them. 10 I will send the sword, the famine, and the pestilence, among them, until they be consumed from off the land that I gave to them and to their fathers.’”

Jeremiah 25

1 The word that came to Jeremiah concerning all the people of Judah, in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah (the same was the first year of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon), 2 which Jeremiah the prophet spoke to all the people of Judah, and to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying: 3 From the thirteenth year of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah, even to this day, these twenty-three years, Yahweh’s word has come to me, and I have spoken to you, rising up early and speaking; but you have not listened.

4 Yahweh has sent to you all his servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them (but you have not listened, nor inclined your ear to hear) 5 saying, “Return now everyone from his evil way, and from the evil of your doings, and dwell in the land that Yahweh has given to you and to your fathers, from of old and even forever more. 6 Don’t go after other gods to serve them or worship them, and don’t provoke me to anger with the work of your hands; and I will do you no harm.”

7 “Yet you have not listened to me,” says Yahweh; “that you may provoke me to anger with the work of your hands to your own hurt.”

8 Therefore Yahweh of Armies says: “Because you have not heard my words, 9 behold, I will send and take all the families of the north,” says Yahweh, “and I will send to Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, my servant, and will bring them against this land, and against its inhabitants, and against all these nations around. I will utterly destroy them, and make them an astonishment, and a hissing, and perpetual desolations. 10 Moreover I will take from them the voice of mirth and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the sound of the millstones, and the light of the lamp. 11 This whole land shall be a desolation, and an astonishment; and these nations shall serve the king of Babylon seventy years.

12 “It shall happen, when seventy years are accomplished, that I will punish the king of Babylon, and that nation,” says Yahweh, “for their iniquity, and the land of the Chaldeans; and I will make it desolate forever. 13 I will bring on that land all my words which I have pronounced against it, even all that is written in this book, which Jeremiah has prophesied against all the nations. 14 For many nations and great kings shall make bondservants of them, even of them; and I will recompense them according to their deeds, and according to the work of their hands.”

15 For Yahweh, the God of Israel, says to me: “take this cup of the wine of wrath at my hand, and cause all the nations, to whom I send you, to drink it. 16 They shall drink, and reel back and forth, and be mad, because of the sword that I will send among them.”

17 Then took I the cup at Yahweh’s hand, and made all the nations to drink, to whom Yahweh had sent me: 18 Jerusalem, and the cities of Judah, and its kings, and its princes, to make them a desolation, an astonishment, a hissing, and a curse, as it is today; 19 Pharaoh king of Egypt, and his servants, and his princes, and all his people; 20 and all the mixed people, and all the kings of the land of the Uz, and all the kings of the Philistines, and Ashkelon, and Gaza, and Ekron, and the remnant of Ashdod; 21 Edom, and Moab, and the children of Ammon; 22 and all the kings of Tyre, and all the kings of Sidon, and the kings of the isle which is beyond the sea; 23 Dedan, and Tema, and Buz, and all who have the corners of their beard cut off; 24 and all the kings of Arabia, and all the kings of the mixed people who dwell in the wilderness; 25 and all the kings of Zimri, and all the kings of Elam, and all the kings of the Medes; 26 and all the kings of the north, far and near, one with another; and all the kingdoms of the world, which are on the surface of the earth: and the king of Sheshach shall drink after them.

27 “You shall tell them, ‘Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says: “Drink, and be drunk, vomit, fall, and rise no more, because of the sword which I will send among you.”’ 28 It shall be, if they refuse to take the cup at your hand to drink, then you shall tell them, ‘Yahweh of Armies says: “You shall surely drink. 29 For, behold, I begin to work evil at the city which is called by my name; and should you be utterly unpunished? You shall not be unpunished; for I will call for a sword on all the inhabitants of the earth, says Yahweh of Armies.”’

30 “Therefore prophesy you against them all these words, and tell them,

“‘Yahweh will roar from on high,

and utter his voice from his holy habitation;

he will mightily roar against his fold.

He will give a shout, as those who tread grapes,

against all the inhabitants of the earth.

31 A noise shall come even to the end of the earth;

for Yahweh has a controversy with the nations;

he will enter into judgment with all flesh:

as for the wicked, he will give them to the sword,”’ says Yahweh.”

32 Yahweh of Armies says,

“Behold, evil shall go out from nation to nation,

and a great storm shall be raised up from the uttermost parts of the earth.”

33 The slain of Yahweh shall be at that day from one end of the earth even to the other end of the earth: they shall not be lamented, neither gathered, nor buried; they shall be dung on the surface of the ground.

34 Wail, you shepherds, and cry;

and wallow in dust, you leader of the flock;

for the days of your slaughter and of your dispersions are fully come,

and you shall fall like a goodly vessel.

35 The shepherds shall have no way to flee,

nor the leader of the flock to escape.

36 A voice of the cry of the shepherds,

and the wailing of the leader of the flock,

for Yahweh lays waste their pasture.

37 The peaceable folds are brought to silence

because of the fierce anger of Yahweh.

38 He has left his covert, as the lion;

for their land has become an astonishment because of the fierceness of the oppression,

and because of his fierce anger.

Jeremiah 26

1 In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, this word came from Yahweh: 2 “Yahweh says: ‘Stand in the court of Yahweh’s house, and speak to all the cities of Judah, which come to worship in Yahweh’s house, all the words that I command you to speak to them. Don’t omit a word. 3 It may be they will listen, and turn every man from his evil way; that I may relent from the evil which I intend to do to them because of the evil of their doings.’ 4 You shall tell them, “Yahweh says: ‘If you will not listen to me, to walk in my law, which I have set before you, 5 to listen to the words of my servants the prophets, whom I send to you, even rising up early and sending them, but you have not listened; 6 then I will make this house like Shiloh, and will make this city a curse to all the nations of the earth.”’”

7 The priests and the prophets and all the people heard Jeremiah speaking these words in Yahweh’s house. 8 When Jeremiah had finished speaking all that Yahweh had commanded him to speak to all the people, the priests and the prophets and all the people seized him, saying, “You shall surely die! 9 Why have you prophesied in Yahweh’s name, saying, ‘This house shall be like Shiloh, and this city shall be desolate, without inhabitant?’” All the people were crowded around Jeremiah in Yahweh’s house.

10 When the princes of Judah heard these things, they came up from the king’s house to Yahweh’s house; and they sat in the entry of the new gate of Yahweh’s house. 11 Then spoke the priests and the prophets to the princes and to all the people, saying, “This man is worthy of death; for he has prophesied against this city, as you have heard with your ears.”

12 Then Jeremiah spoke to all the princes and to all the people, saying, “Yahweh sent me to prophesy against this house and against this city all the words that you have heard. 13 Now therefore amend your ways and your doings, and obey Yahweh your God’s voice; and Yahweh will relent from the evil that he has pronounced against you. 14 But as for me, behold, I am in your hand. Do with me what is good and right in your eyes. 15 Only know for certain that, if you put me to death, you will bring innocent blood on yourselves, and on this city, and on its inhabitants; for in truth Yahweh has sent me to you to speak all these words in your ears.”

16 Then the princes and all the people said to the priests and to the prophets: “This man is not worthy of death; for he has spoken to us in the name of Yahweh our God.”

17 Then certain of the elders of the land rose up, and spoke to all the assembly of the people, saying, 18 “Micah the Morashtite prophesied in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah; and he spoke to all the people of Judah, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says:

“‘Zion will be plowed as a field,

and Jerusalem shall become heaps,

and the mountain of the house as the high places of a forest.’

19 Did Hezekiah king of Judah and all Judah put him to death? Didn’t he fear Yahweh, and entreat the favor of Yahweh, and Yahweh relented of the disaster which he had pronounced against them? We would commit great evil against our own souls that way!”

20 There was also a man who prophesied in Yahweh’s name, Uriah the son of Shemaiah of Kiriath Jearim; and he prophesied against this city and against this land according to all the words of Jeremiah. 21 When Jehoiakim the king, with all his mighty men, and all the princes, heard his words, the king sought to put him to death; but when Uriah heard it, he was afraid, and fled, and went into Egypt: 22 and Jehoiakim the king sent men into Egypt, Elnathan the son of Achbor, and certain men with him, into Egypt; 23 and they fetched Uriah out of Egypt, and brought him to Jehoiakim the king, who killed him with the sword, and cast his dead body into the graves of the common people.

24 But the hand of Ahikam the son of Shaphan was with Jeremiah, that they should not give him into the hand of the people to put him to death.

Jeremiah 27

1 In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, came this word to Jeremiah from Yahweh, saying, 2 Yahweh says to me: “Make bonds and bars, and put them on your neck. 3 Then send them to the king of Edom, and to the king of Moab, and to the king of the children of Ammon, and to the king of Tyre, and to the king of Sidon, by the hand of the messengers who come to Jerusalem to Zedekiah king of Judah. 4 Give them a command to their masters, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says, “You shall tell your masters: 5 ‘I have made the earth, the men and the animals that are on the surface of the earth, by my great power and by my outstretched arm; and I give it to whom it seems right to me. 6 Now I have given all these lands into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon, my servant; and I have also given the animals of the field to him to serve him. 7 All the nations will serve him, and his son, and his son’s son, until the time of his own land comes. Then many nations and great kings will make him their bondservant.

8 “‘“‘It will happen that the nation and the kingdom which will not serve the same Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and that will not put their neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, that nation will I punish,’ says Yahweh, ‘with the sword, and with the famine, and with the pestilence, until I have consumed them by his hand. 9 But as for you, don’t you listen to your prophets, nor to your diviners, nor to your dreams, nor to your soothsayers, nor to your sorcerers, who speak to you, saying, “You shall not serve the king of Babylon;” 10 for they prophesy a lie to you, to remove you far from your land, and that I should drive you out, and you should perish. 11 But the nation that shall bring their neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, and serve him, that nation will I let remain in their own land,’ says Yahweh; ‘and they shall till it, and dwell therein.’”’”

12 I spoke to Zedekiah king of Judah according to all these words, saying, “Bring your necks under the yoke of the king of Babylon, and serve him and his people, and live. 13 Why will you die, you and your people, by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence, as Yahweh has spoken concerning the nation that will not serve the king of Babylon? 14 Don’t listen to the words of the prophets who speak to you, saying, ‘You shall not serve the king of Babylon;’ for they prophesy a lie to you. 15 For I have not sent them,” says Yahweh, “but they prophesy falsely in my name; that I may drive you out, and that you may perish, you, and the prophets who prophesy to you.”

16 Also I spoke to the priests and to all this people, saying, Yahweh says, “Don’t listen to the words of your prophets who prophesy to you, saying, ‘Behold, the vessels of Yahweh’s house shall now shortly be brought again from Babylon;’ for they prophesy a lie to you. 17 Don’t listen to them. Serve the king of Babylon, and live. Why should this city become a desolation? 18 But if they are prophets, and if Yahweh’s word is with them, let them now make intercession to Yahweh of Armies, that the vessels which are left in Yahweh’s house, and in the house of the king of Judah, and at Jerusalem, don’t go to Babylon. 19 For Yahweh of Armies says concerning the pillars, and concerning the sea, and concerning the bases, and concerning the residue of the vessels that are left in this city, 20 which Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon didn’t take, when he carried away captive Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, from Jerusalem to Babylon, and all the nobles of Judah and Jerusalem; 21 yes, Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says concerning the vessels that are left in Yahweh’s house, and in the house of the king of Judah, and at Jerusalem: 22 ‘They shall be carried to Babylon, and there shall they be, until the day that I visit them,’ says Yahweh; ‘then I will bring them up, and restore them to this place.’”

Jeremiah 28

1 That same year, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah king of Judah, in the fourth year, in the fifth month, Hananiah the son of Azzur, the prophet, who was of Gibeon, spoke to me in Yahweh’s house, in the presence of the priests and of all the people, saying, 2 “Thus speaks Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, saying, ‘I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon. 3 Within two full years will I bring again into this place all the vessels of Yahweh’s house, that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon took away from this place, and carried to Babylon. 4 I will bring again to this place Jeconiah the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, with all the captives of Judah, who went to Babylon,’ says Yahweh; ‘for I will break the yoke of the king of Babylon.’”

5 Then the prophet Jeremiah said to the prophet Hananiah in the presence of the priests, and in the presence of all the people who stood in Yahweh’s house, 6 even the prophet Jeremiah said, “Amen! May Yahweh do so. May Yahweh perform your words which you have prophesied, to bring again the vessels of Yahweh’s house, and all them of the captivity, from Babylon to this place. 7 Nevertheless listen now to this word that I speak in your ears, and in the ears of all the people: 8 The prophets who have been before me and before you of old prophesied against many countries, and against great kingdoms, of war, and of evil, and of pestilence. 9 The prophet who prophesies of peace, when the word of the prophet shall happen, then shall the prophet be known, that Yahweh has truly sent him.”

10 Then Hananiah the prophet took the bar from off the prophet Jeremiah’s neck, and broke it. 11 Hananiah spoke in the presence of all the people, saying, “Yahweh says: ‘Even so I will break the yoke of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon within two full years from off the neck of all the nations.’” Then the prophet Jeremiah went his way.

12 Then Yahweh’s word came to Jeremiah, after that Hananiah the prophet had broken the bar from off the neck of the prophet Jeremiah, saying, 13 “Go, and tell Hananiah, saying, ‘Yahweh says, “You have broken the bars of wood, but you have made in their place bars of iron.” 14 For Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says, “I have put a yoke of iron on the neck of all these nations, that they may serve Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon; and they will serve him. I have also given him the animals of the field.”’”

15 Then the prophet Jeremiah said to Hananiah the prophet, “Listen, Hananiah! Yahweh has not sent you, but you make this people trust in a lie. 16 Therefore Yahweh says, ‘Behold, I will send you away from off the surface of the earth. This year you will die, because you have spoken rebellion against Yahweh.’”

17 So Hananiah the prophet died the same year in the seventh month.

Jeremiah 29

1 Now these are the words of the letter that Jeremiah the prophet sent from Jerusalem to the residue of the elders of the captivity, and to the priests, to the prophets, and to all the people, whom Nebuchadnezzar had carried away captive from Jerusalem to Babylon, 2 (after that Jeconiah the king, the queen mother, the eunuchs, the princes of Judah and Jerusalem, the craftsmen, and the smiths, had departed from Jerusalem), 3 by the hand of Elasah the son of Shaphan, and Gemariah the son of Hilkiah, (whom Zedekiah king of Judah sent to Babylon to Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon), saying,

4 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says to all the captivity, whom I have caused to be carried away captive from Jerusalem to Babylon: 5 “Build houses, and dwell in them; and plant gardens, and eat their fruit. 6 Take wives, and father sons and daughters; and take wives for your sons, and give your daughters to husbands, that they may bear sons and daughters; and multiply there, and don’t be diminished. 7 Seek the peace of the city where I have caused you to be carried away captive, and pray to Yahweh for it; for in its peace you shall have peace.” 8 For Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says: “Don’t let your prophets who are among you, and your diviners, deceive you; neither listen to your dreams which you cause to be dreamed. 9 For they prophesy falsely to you in my name. I have not sent them,” says Yahweh. 10 For Yahweh says, “After seventy years are accomplished for Babylon, I will visit you, and perform my good word toward you, in causing you to return to this place. 11 For I know the thoughts that I think toward you,” says Yahweh, “thoughts of peace, and not of evil, to give you hope and a future. 12 You shall call on me, and you shall go and pray to me, and I will listen to you. 13 You shall seek me, and find me, when you shall search for me with all your heart. 14 I will be found by you,” says Yahweh, “and I will turn again your captivity, and I will gather you from all the nations, and from all the places where I have driven you, says Yahweh; and I will bring you again to the place from where I caused you to be carried away captive.”

15 Because you have said, “Yahweh has raised us up prophets in Babylon;” 16 Yahweh says concerning the king who sits on David’s throne, and concerning all the people who dwell in this city, your brothers who haven’t gone with you into captivity; 17 Yahweh of Armies says: “Behold, I will send on them the sword, the famine, and the pestilence, and will make them like vile figs, that can’t be eaten, they are so bad. 18 I will pursue after them with the sword, with the famine, and with the pestilence, and will deliver them to be tossed back and forth among all the kingdoms of the earth, to be an object of horror, and an astonishment, and a hissing, and a reproach, among all the nations where I have driven them; 19 because they have not listened to my words,” says Yahweh, “with which I sent to them my servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them; but you would not hear,” says Yahweh.

20 Hear therefore Yahweh’s word, all you of the captivity, whom I have sent away from Jerusalem to Babylon. 21 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says concerning Ahab the son of Kolaiah, and concerning Zedekiah the son of Maaseiah, who prophesy a lie to you in my name: “Behold, I will deliver them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon; and he shall kill them before your eyes. 22 A curse shall be taken up about them by all the captives of Judah who are in Babylon, saying, ‘Yahweh make you like Zedekiah and like Ahab, whom the king of Babylon roasted in the fire;’ 23 because they have done foolish things in Israel, and have committed adultery with their neighbors’ wives, and have spoken words in my name falsely, which I didn’t command them. I am he who knows, and am witness,” says Yahweh.

24 Concerning Shemaiah the Nehelamite you shall speak, saying, 25 “Thus speaks Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, saying, ‘Because you have sent letters in your own name to all the people who are at Jerusalem, and to Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, and to all the priests, saying, 26 “Yahweh has made you priest in the place of Jehoiada the priest, that there may be officers in Yahweh’s house, for every man who is mad, and makes himself a prophet, that you should put him in the stocks and in shackles. 27 Now therefore, why have you not rebuked Jeremiah of Anathoth, who makes himself a prophet to you, 28 because he has sent to us in Babylon, saying, The captivity is long: build houses, and dwell in them; and plant gardens, and eat their fruit?”’”

29 Zephaniah the priest read this letter in the ears of Jeremiah the prophet. 30 Then Yahweh’s word came to Jeremiah, saying, 31 “Send to all them of the captivity, saying, ‘Yahweh says concerning Shemaiah the Nehelamite: “Because Shemaiah has prophesied to you, and I didn’t send him, and he has caused you to trust in a lie;” 32 therefore Yahweh says, “Behold, I will punish Shemaiah the Nehelamite, and his offspring.[*] He shall not have a man to dwell among this people, neither shall he see the good that I will do to my people,” says Yahweh, “because he has spoken rebellion against Yahweh.”’”

or, seed

Jeremiah 30

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, saying, 2 “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, ‘Write all the words that I have spoken to you in a book. 3 For, behold, the days come,’ says Yahweh, ‘that I will turn again the captivity of my people Israel and Judah,’ says Yahweh. ‘I will cause them to return to the land that I gave to their fathers, and they shall possess it.’”

4 These are the words that Yahweh spoke concerning Israel and concerning Judah. 5 For Yahweh says:

“We have heard a voice of trembling,

of fear, and not of peace.

6 Ask now, and see whether a man travails with child.

Why do I see every man with his hands on his waist, as a woman in travail,

and all faces are turned pale?

7 Alas! for that day is great, so that none is like it.

It is even the time of Jacob’s trouble;

but he shall be saved out of it.

8 It shall come to pass in that day, says Yahweh of Armies, that I will break his yoke from off your neck,

and will burst your bonds;

and strangers shall no more make them their bondservants;

9 but they will serve Yahweh their God,

and David their king,

whom I will raise up to them.

10 Therefore don’t you be afraid, O Jacob my servant, says Yahweh;

neither be dismayed, Israel:

for, behold, I will save you from afar,

and your offspring[*] from the land of their captivity.

Jacob shall return,

and shall be quiet and at ease,

and no one shall make him afraid.

11 For I am with you, says Yahweh, to save you;

for I will make a full end of all the nations where I have scattered you,

but I will not make a full end of you;

but I will correct you in measure,

and will in no way leave you unpunished.”

12 For Yahweh says,

“Your hurt is incurable,

and your wound grievous.

13 There is no one to plead your cause,

that you may be bound up.

You have no healing medicines.

14 All your lovers have forgotten you.

They don’t seek you:

for I have wounded you with the wound of an enemy,

with the chastisement of a cruel one,

for the greatness of your iniquity,

because your sins were increased.

15 Why do you cry for your hurt?

Your pain is incurable:

for the greatness of your iniquity,

because your sins were increased,

I have done these things to you.

16 Therefore all those who devour you shall be devoured;

and all your adversaries, everyone of them, shall go into captivity;

and those who plunder you shall be plunder,

and all who prey on you will I give for a prey.

17 For I will restore health to you,

and I will heal you of your wounds,” says Yahweh;

“because they have called you an outcast,

saying, ‘It is Zion, whom no man seeks after.’”

18 Yahweh says:

“Behold, I will turn again the captivity of Jacob’s tents,

and have compassion on his dwelling places.

The city shall be built on its own hill,

and the palace shall be inhabited in its own place.

19 Out of them shall proceed thanksgiving

and the voice of those who make merry.

I will multiply them,

and they shall not be few;

I will also glorify them,

and they will not be small.

20 Their children also shall be as before,

and their congregation shall be established before me.

I will punish all who oppress them.

21 Their prince shall be of themselves,

and their ruler shall proceed from among them.

I will cause him to draw near,

and he shall approach to me;

for who is he who has had boldness to approach to me?” says Yahweh.

22 “You shall be my people,

and I will be your God.

23 Behold, Yahweh’s storm, his wrath, has gone out,

a sweeping storm:

it shall burst on the head of the wicked.

24 The fierce anger of Yahweh will not return, until he has executed,

and until he has performed the intentions of his heart.

In the latter days you will understand it.”

or, seed

Jeremiah 31

1 “At that time,” says Yahweh, “I will be the God of all the families of Israel, and they will be my people.”

2 Yahweh says, “The people who survive the sword found favor in the wilderness; even Israel, when I went to cause him to rest.”

3 Yahweh appeared of old to me, saying,

“Yes, I have loved you with an everlasting love.

Therefore I have drawn you with loving kindness.

4 I will build you again,

and you will be built, O virgin of Israel.

You will again be adorned with your tambourines,

and will go out in the dances of those who make merry.

5 Again you will plant vineyards on the mountains of Samaria.

The planters will plant,

and will enjoy its fruit.

6 For there will be a day that the watchmen on the hills of Ephraim cry,

‘Arise, and let us go up to Zion to Yahweh our God.’”

7 For Yahweh says,

“Sing with gladness for Jacob,

and shout for the chief of the nations.

Publish, praise, and say,

‘Yahweh, save your people,

the remnant of Israel!’

8 Behold, I will bring them from the north country,

and gather them from the uttermost parts of the earth,

along with the blind and the lame,

the woman with child and her who travails with child together.

They will return as a great company.

9 They shall come with weeping;

and with petitions will I lead them:

I will cause them to walk by rivers of waters,

in a straight way in which they shall not stumble;

for I am a father to Israel,

and Ephraim is my firstborn.

10 “Hear Yahweh’s word, you nations,

and declare it in the islands afar off; and say,

‘He who scattered Israel will gather him,

and keep him, as a shepherd does his flock.’

11 For Yahweh has ransomed Jacob,

and redeemed him from the hand of him who was stronger than he.

12 They shall come and sing in the height of Zion,

and shall flow to the goodness of Yahweh,

to the grain, and to the new wine, and to the oil,

and to the young of the flock and of the herd:

and their soul shall be as a watered garden;

and they shall not sorrow any more at all.

13 Then the virgin will rejoice in the dance,

and the young men and the old together;

for I will turn their mourning into joy,

and will comfort them, and make them rejoice from their sorrow.

14 I will satiate the soul of the priests with fatness,

and my people shall be satisfied with my goodness,” says Yahweh.

15 Yahweh says:

“A voice is heard in Ramah,

lamentation, and bitter weeping,

Rachel weeping for her children;

she refuses to be comforted for her children,

because they are no more.”

16 Yahweh says:

“Refrain your voice from weeping,

and your eyes from tears;

for your work shall be rewarded,” says Yahweh;

“and they shall come again from the land of the enemy.

17 There is hope for your latter end,” says Yahweh;

“and your children shall come again to their own border.

18 “I have surely heard Ephraim bemoaning himself thus,

‘You have chastised me,

and I was chastised, as an untrained calf:

turn me, and I shall be turned;

for you are Yahweh my God.

19 Surely after that I was turned,

I repented;

and after that I was instructed,

I struck on my thigh:

I was ashamed, yes, even confounded,

because I bore the reproach of my youth.’

20 Is Ephraim my dear son?

is he a darling child?

for as often as I speak against him,

I do earnestly remember him still:

therefore my heart yearns for him;

I will surely have mercy on him,” says Yahweh.

21 “Set up road signs,

make guideposts;

set your heart toward the highway,

even the way by which you went:

turn again, virgin of Israel,

turn again to these your cities.

22 How long will you go here and there,

you backsliding daughter?

for Yahweh has created a new thing in the earth:

a woman shall encompass a man.”

23 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says: “Yet again shall they use this speech in the land of Judah and in its cities, when I shall bring again their captivity: ‘Yahweh bless you, habitation of righteousness, mountain of holiness.’ 24 Judah and all its cities shall dwell therein together, the farmers, and those who go about with flocks. 25 For I have satiated the weary soul, and every sorrowful soul I have replenished.”

26 On this I awakened, and saw; and my sleep was sweet to me.

27 “Behold, the days come,” says Yahweh, “that I will sow the house of Israel and the house of Judah with the seed of man, and with the seed of animal. 28 It shall happen that, like as I have watched over them to pluck up and to break down and to overthrow and to destroy and to afflict, so will I watch over them to build and to plant,” says Yahweh. 29 “In those days they shall say no more,

“‘The fathers have eaten sour grapes,

and the children’s teeth are set on edge.’

30 But everyone shall die for his own iniquity: every man who eats the sour grapes, his teeth shall be set on edge.

31 “Behold, the days come,” says Yahweh,

“that I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel,

and with the house of Judah:

32 not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day that I took them by the hand to bring them out of the land of Egypt;

which my covenant they broke,

although I was a husband to them,” says Yahweh.

33 “But this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days,”

says Yahweh:

I will put my law in their inward parts,

and in their heart will I write it;

and I will be their God,

and they shall be my people:

34 and they shall teach no more every man his neighbor,

and every man his brother, saying, ‘Know Yahweh;’

for they shall all know me,

from their least to their greatest,” says Yahweh:

“for I will forgive their iniquity,

and their sin will I remember no more.”

35 Yahweh, who gives the sun for a light by day,

and the ordinances of the moon and of the stars for a light by night,

who stirs up the sea, so that its waves roar;

Yahweh of Armies is his name, says:

36 “If these ordinances depart from before me,” says Yahweh,

“then the offspring[*] of Israel also shall cease from being a nation before me forever.”

37 Yahweh says: “If heaven above can be measured,

and the foundations of the earth searched out beneath,

then I will also cast off all the offspring[*] of Israel for all that they have done,” says Yahweh.

38 “Behold, the days come,” says Yahweh, “that the city shall be built to Yahweh from the tower of Hananel to the gate of the corner. 39 The measuring line shall go out further straight onward to the hill Gareb, and shall turn about to Goah. 40 The whole valley of the dead bodies and of the ashes, and all the fields to the brook Kidron, to the corner of the horse gate toward the east, shall be holy to Yahweh; it shall not be plucked up, nor thrown down any more forever.”

or, seed

or, seed

Jeremiah 34

1 The word which came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, when Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and all his army, and all the kingdoms of the earth that were under his dominion, and all the peoples, were fighting against Jerusalem, and against all the cities of it, saying: 2 “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, ‘Go, and speak to Zedekiah king of Judah, and tell him, Yahweh says, “Behold, I will give this city into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will burn it with fire. 3 You won’t escape out of his hand, but will surely be taken, and delivered into his hand. Your eyes will see the eyes of the king of Babylon, and he will speak with you mouth to mouth. You will go to Babylon.”’

4 “Yet hear Yahweh’s word, O Zedekiah king of Judah: Yahweh says concerning you, ‘You won’t die by the sword. 5 You will die in peace; and with the burnings of your fathers, the former kings who were before you, so they will make a burning for you. They shall lament you, saying, “Ah Lord!” for I have spoken the word,’ says Yahweh.”

6 Then Jeremiah the prophet spoke all these words to Zedekiah king of Judah in Jerusalem, 7 when the king of Babylon’s army was fighting against Jerusalem, and against all the cities of Judah that were left, against Lachish and against Azekah; for these alone remained of the cities of Judah as fortified cities.

8 The word came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, after king Zedekiah had made a covenant with all the people who were at Jerusalem, to proclaim liberty to them; 9 that every man should let his male servant, and every man his female servant, who is a Hebrew or a Hebrewess, go free; that no one should make bondservants of them, of a Jew his brother. 10 All the princes and all the people obeyed, who had entered into the covenant, that everyone should let his male servant, and everyone his female servant, go free, that no one should make bondservants of them any more; they obeyed, and let them go: 11 but afterwards they turned, and caused the servants and the handmaids, whom they had let go free, to return, and brought them into subjection for servants and for handmaids.

12 Therefore Yahweh’s word came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, saying, 13 “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says: ‘I made a covenant with your fathers in the day that I brought them out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage, saying, 14 At the end of seven years, every man of you shall release his brother who is a Hebrew, who has been sold to you, and has served you six years. You shall let him go free from you; but your fathers didn’t listen to me, and didn’t incline their ear. 15 You had now turned, and had done that which is right in my eyes, in every man proclaiming liberty to his neighbor; and you had made a covenant before me in the house which is called by my name; 16 but you turned and profaned my name, and every man caused his servant, and every man his handmaid, whom you had let go free at their pleasure, to return; and you brought them into subjection, to be to you for servants and for handmaids.’”

17 Therefore Yahweh says: “You have not listened to me, to proclaim liberty, every man to his brother, and every man to his neighbor. Behold, I proclaim to you a liberty,” says Yahweh, “to the sword, to the pestilence, and to the famine. I will make you be tossed back and forth among all the kingdoms of the earth. 18 I will give the men who have transgressed my covenant, who have not performed the words of the covenant which they made before me, when they cut the calf in two and passed between its parts: 19 the princes of Judah, the princes of Jerusalem, the eunuchs, the priests, and all the people of the land, who passed between the parts of the calf; 20 I will even give them into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of those who seek their life. Their dead bodies will be food for the birds of the sky, and for the animals of the earth.

21 “I will give Zedekiah king of Judah and his princes into the hands of their enemies, into the hands of those who seek their life, and into the hands of the king of Babylon’s army, who has gone away from you. 22 Behold, I will command,” says Yahweh, “and cause them to return to this city; and they shall fight against it, take it, and burn it with fire. I will make the cities of Judah a desolation, without inhabitant.”

Jeremiah 36

1 In the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, this word came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, saying, 2 “Take a scroll of a book, and write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel, and against Judah, and against all the nations, from the day I spoke to you, from the days of Josiah, even to this day. 3 It may be that the house of Judah will hear all the evil which I purpose to do to them; that they may each return from his evil way; that I may forgive their iniquity and their sin.”

4 Then Jeremiah called Baruch the son of Neriah; and Baruch wrote from the mouth of Jeremiah all Yahweh’s words, which he had spoken to him, on a scroll of a book. 5 Jeremiah commanded Baruch, saying, “I am restricted. I can’t go into Yahweh’s house. 6 Therefore you go, and read from the scroll, which you have written from my mouth, Yahweh’s words in the ears of the people in Yahweh’s house on the fast day. Also you shall read them in the ears of all Judah who come out of their cities. 7 It may be they will present their supplication before Yahweh, and will each return from his evil way; for Yahweh has pronounced great anger and wrath against this people.”

8 Baruch the son of Neriah did according to all that Jeremiah the prophet commanded him, reading in the book Yahweh’s words in Yahweh’s house. 9 Now in the fifth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah, in the ninth month, all the people in Jerusalem, and all the people who came from the cities of Judah to Jerusalem, proclaimed a fast before Yahweh. 10 Then Baruch read the words of Jeremiah from the book in Yahweh’s house, in the room of Gemariah the son of Shaphan, the scribe, in the upper court, at the entry of the new gate of Yahweh’s house, in the ears of all the people.

11 When Micaiah the son of Gemariah, the son of Shaphan, had heard out of the book all Yahweh’s words, 12 he went down into the king’s house, into the scribe’s room: and behold, all the princes were sitting there, Elishama the scribe, Delaiah the son of Shemaiah, Elnathan the son of Achbor, Gemariah the son of Shaphan, Zedekiah the son of Hananiah, and all the princes. 13 Then Micaiah declared to them all the words that he had heard, when Baruch read the book in the ears of the people. 14 Therefore all the princes sent Jehudi the son of Nethaniah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Cushi, to Baruch, saying, “Take in your hand the scroll in which you have read in the ears of the people, and come.”

So Baruch the son of Neriah took the scroll in his hand, and came to them. 15 They said to him, “Sit down now, and read it in our hearing.”

So Baruch read it in their hearing.

16 Now when they had heard all the words, they turned in fear one toward another, and said to Baruch, “We will surely tell the king of all these words.” 17 They asked Baruch, saying, “Tell us now, How did you write all these words at his mouth?”

18 Then Baruch answered them, “He dictated all these words to me with his mouth, and I wrote them with ink in the book.”

19 Then the princes said to Baruch, “You and Jeremiah go hide. Don’t let anyone know where you are.”

20 They went in to the king into the court; but they had laid up the scroll in the room of Elishama the scribe; and they told all the words in the ears of the king. 21 So the king sent Jehudi to get the scroll; and he took it out of the room of Elishama the scribe. Jehudi read it in the ears of the king, and in the ears of all the princes who stood beside the king. 22 Now the king was sitting in the winter house in the ninth month: and there was a fire in the brazier burning before him. 23 When Jehudi had read three or four leaves, the king cut it with the penknife, and cast it into the fire that was in the brazier, until all the scroll was consumed in the fire that was in the brazier. 24 The king and his servants who heard all these words were not afraid, and didn’t tear their garments. 25 Moreover Elnathan and Delaiah and Gemariah had made intercession to the king that he would not burn the scroll; but he would not listen to them. 26 The king commanded Jerahmeel the king’s son, and Seraiah the son of Azriel, and Shelemiah the son of Abdeel, to arrest Baruch the scribe and Jeremiah the prophet; but Yahweh hid them.

27 Then Yahweh’s word came to Jeremiah, after the king had burned the scroll, and the words which Baruch wrote at the mouth of Jeremiah, saying, 28 “Take again another scroll, and write in it all the former words that were in the first scroll, which Jehoiakim the king of Judah has burned. 29 Concerning Jehoiakim king of Judah you shall say, ‘Yahweh says: “You have burned this scroll, saying, “Why have you written therein, saying, ‘The king of Babylon shall certainly come and destroy this land, and shall cause to cease from there man and animal?’”’ 30 Therefore Yahweh says concerning Jehoiakim king of Judah: “He will have no one to sit on David’s throne. His dead body will be cast out in the day to the heat, and in the night to the frost. 31 I will punish him and his offspring[*] and his servants for their iniquity; and I will bring on them, on the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and on the men of Judah, all the evil that I have pronounced against them, but they didn’t listen.”’”

32 Then took Jeremiah another scroll, and gave it to Baruch the scribe, the son of Neriah, who wrote therein from the mouth of Jeremiah all the words of the book which Jehoiakim king of Judah had burned in the fire; and many similar words were added to them.

or, seed

Jeremiah 37

1 Zedekiah the son of Josiah reigned as king, instead of Coniah the son of Jehoiakim, whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon made king in the land of Judah. 2 But neither he, nor his servants, nor the people of the land, listened to Yahweh’s words, which he spoke by the prophet Jeremiah.

3 Zedekiah the king sent Jehucal the son of Shelemiah, and Zephaniah the son of Maaseiah, the priest, to the prophet Jeremiah, saying, “Pray now to Yahweh our God for us.”

4 Now Jeremiah came in and went out among the people; for they had not put him into prison. 5 Pharaoh’s army had come out of Egypt; and when the Chaldeans who were besieging Jerusalem heard news of them, they broke up from Jerusalem.

6 Then came Yahweh’s word to the prophet Jeremiah, saying, 7 “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, ‘You shall tell the king of Judah, who sent you to me to inquire of me: “Behold, Pharaoh’s army, which has come out to help you, shall return to Egypt into their own land. 8 The Chaldeans shall come again, and fight against this city; and they shall take it, and burn it with fire.”’

9 “Yahweh says, ‘Don’t deceive yourselves, saying, “The Chaldeans shall surely depart from us;” for they shall not depart. 10 For though you had struck the whole army of the Chaldeans who fight against you, and there remained but wounded men among them, yes they would each rise up in his tent and burn this city with fire.’”

11 When the army of the Chaldeans had broken up from Jerusalem for fear of Pharaoh’s army, 12 then Jeremiah went out of Jerusalem to go into the land of Benjamin, to receive his portion there, in the middle of the people. 13 When he was in the gate of Benjamin, a captain of the guard was there, whose name was Irijah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Hananiah; and he laid hold on Jeremiah the prophet, saying, “You are defecting to the Chaldeans!”

14 Then Jeremiah said, “That is false! I am not falling away to the Chaldeans.”

But he didn’t listen to him; so Irijah siezed Jeremiah, and brought him to the princes. 15 The princes were angry with Jeremiah, and struck him, and put him in prison in the house of Jonathan the scribe; for they had made that the prison.

16 When Jeremiah had come into the dungeon house, and into the cells, and Jeremiah had remained there many days, 17 then Zedekiah the king sent, and fetched him. The king asked him secretly in his house, and said, “Is there any word from Yahweh?”

Jeremiah said, “There is.” He said also, “You will be delivered into the hand of the king of Babylon.”

18 Moreover Jeremiah said to king Zedekiah, “How have I sinned against you, against your servants, or against this people, that you have put me in prison? 19 Now where are your prophets who prophesied to you, saying, ‘The king of Babylon will not come against you, nor against this land?’ 20 Now please hear, my lord the king: please let my supplication be presented before you, that you not cause me to return to the house of Jonathan the scribe, lest I die there.”

21 Then Zedekiah the king commanded, and they committed Jeremiah into the court of the guard. They gave him daily a loaf of bread out of the bakers’ street, until all the bread in the city was gone. Thus Jeremiah remained in the court of the guard.

Jeremiah 38

1 Shephatiah the son of Mattan, and Gedaliah the son of Pashhur, and Jucal the son of Shelemiah, and Pashhur the son of Malchijah, heard the words that Jeremiah spoke to all the people, saying, 2 “Yahweh says, ‘He who remains in this city shall die by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence; but he who goes out to the Chaldeans shall live, and his life shall be to him for a prey, and he shall live.’ 3 Yahweh says, ‘This city will surely be given into the hand of the army of the king of Babylon, and he will take it.’”

4 Then the princes said to the king, “Please let this man be put to death; because he weakens the hands of the men of war who remain in this city, and the hands of all the people, in speaking such words to them: for this man doesn’t seek the welfare of this people, but harm.”

5 Zedekiah the king said, “Behold, he is in your hand; for the king can’t do anything to oppose you.”

6 Then took they Jeremiah, and cast him into the dungeon of Malchijah the king’s son, that was in the court of the guard. They let down Jeremiah with cords. In the dungeon there was no water, but mire; and Jeremiah sank in the mire.

7 Now when Ebedmelech the Ethiopian, a eunuch, who was in the king’s house, heard that they had put Jeremiah in the dungeon (the king was then sitting in the gate of Benjamin), 8 Ebedmelech went out of the king’s house, and spoke to the king, saying, 9 “My lord the king, these men have done evil in all that they have done to Jeremiah the prophet, whom they have cast into the dungeon. He is likely to die in the place where he is, because of the famine; for there is no more bread in the city.”

10 Then the king commanded Ebedmelech the Ethiopian, saying, “Take from here thirty men with you, and take up Jeremiah the prophet out of the dungeon, before he dies.”

11 So Ebedmelech took the men with him, and went into the house of the king under the treasury, and took there rags and worn-out garments, and let them down by cords into the dungeon to Jeremiah. 12 Ebedmelech the Ethiopian said to Jeremiah, “Now put these rags and worn-out garments under your armpits under the cords.”

Jeremiah did so. 13 So they drew up Jeremiah with the cords, and took him up out of the dungeon; and Jeremiah remained in the court of the guard.

14 Then Zedekiah the king sent, and took Jeremiah the prophet to himself into the third entry that is in Yahweh’s house. Then the king said to Jeremiah, “I will ask you something. Hide nothing from me.”

15 Then Jeremiah said to Zedekiah, “If I declare it to you, will you not surely put me to death? If I give you counsel, you will not listen to me.”

16 So Zedekiah the king swore secretly to Jeremiah, saying, “As Yahweh lives, who made us this soul, I will not put you to death, neither will I give you into the hand of these men who seek your life.”

17 Then Jeremiah said to Zedekiah, “Yahweh, the God of Armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘If you will go out to the king of Babylon’s princes, then your soul will live, and this city will not be burned with fire. You will live, along with your house. 18 But if you will not go out to the king of Babylon’s princes, then this city will be given into the hand of the Chaldeans, and they will burn it with fire, and you won’t escape out of their hand.’”

19 Zedekiah the king said to Jeremiah, “I am afraid of the Jews who have defected to the Chaldeans, lest they deliver me into their hand, and they mock me.”

20 But Jeremiah said, “They won’t deliver you. Obey, I beg you, Yahweh’s voice, in that which I speak to you; so it will be well with you, and your soul shall live. 21 But if you refuse to go out, this is the word that Yahweh has shown me: 22 ‘Behold, all the women who are left in the king of Judah’s house will be brought out to the king of Babylon’s princes, and those women will say,

“Your familiar friends have turned on you,

and have prevailed over you.

Your feet are sunk in the mire,

they have turned away from you.”

23 They will bring out all your wives and your children to the Chaldeans. You won’t escape out of their hand, but will be taken by the hand of the king of Babylon. You will cause this city to be burned with fire.’”

24 Then Zedekiah said to Jeremiah, “Let no man know of these words, and you won’t die. 25 But if the princes hear that I have talked with you, and they come to you, and tell you, ‘Declare to us now what you have said to the king; don’t hide it from us, and we will not put you to death; also what the king said to you;’ 26 then you shall tell them, ‘I presented my supplication before the king, that he would not cause me to return to Jonathan’s house, to die there.’”

27 Then came all the princes to Jeremiah, and asked him; and he told them according to all these words that the king had commanded. So they stopped speaking with him; for the matter was not perceived.

28 So Jeremiah stayed in the court of the guard until the day that Jerusalem was taken.

Jeremiah 39

1 When Jerusalem was taken, (in the ninth year of Zedekiah king of Judah, in the tenth month, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon and all his army came against Jerusalem, and besieged it. 2 In the eleventh year of Zedekiah, in the fourth month, the ninth day of the month, a breach was made in the city), 3 all the princes of the king of Babylon came in, and sat in the middle gate, Nergal Sharezer, Samgarnebo, Sarsechim, Rabsaris, Nergal Sharezer, Rabmag, with all the rest of the princes of the king of Babylon. 4 When Zedekiah the king of Judah and all the men of war saw them, then they fled, and went out of the city by night, by the way of the king’s garden, through the gate between the two walls; and he went out toward the Arabah.

5 But the army of the Chaldeans pursued them, and overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho: and when they had taken him, they brought him up to Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon to Riblah in the land of Hamath; and he gave judgment on him. 6 Then the king of Babylon killed the sons of Zedekiah in Riblah before his eyes. The king of Babylon also killed all the nobles of Judah. 7 Moreover he put out Zedekiah’s eyes, and bound him in fetters, to carry him to Babylon.

8 The Chaldeans burned the king’s house, and the houses of the people, with fire, and broke down the walls of Jerusalem. 9 Then Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive into Babylon the residue of the people who remained in the city, the deserters also who fell away to him, and the residue of the people who remained. 10 But Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard left of the poor of the people, who had nothing, in the land of Judah, and gave them vineyards and fields at the same time.

11 Now Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon commanded Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard concerning Jeremiah, saying, 12 “Take him, and look well to him, and do him no harm; but do to him even as he shall tell you.”

13 So Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard sent, and Nebushazban, Rabsaris, and Nergal Sharezer, Rabmag, and all the chief officers of the king of Babylon; 14 they sent, and took Jeremiah out of the court of the guard, and committed him to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, that he should carry him home: so he lived among the people.

15 Now Yahweh’s word came to Jeremiah, while he was shut up in the court of the guard, saying, 16 “Go, and speak to Ebedmelech the Ethiopian, saying, Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Behold, I will bring my words on this city for evil, and not for good; and they shall be accomplished before you in that day. 17 But I will deliver you in that day,’ says Yahweh; ‘and you will not be given into the hand of the men of whom you are afraid. 18 For I will surely save you, and you shall not fall by the sword, but your life shall be for a prey to you; because you have put your trust in me,’ says Yahweh.”

Jeremiah 40

1 The word which came to Jeremiah from Yahweh, after Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard had let him go from Ramah, when he had taken him being bound in chains among all the captives of Jerusalem and Judah, who were carried away captive to Babylon. 2 The captain of the guard took Jeremiah, and said to him, “Yahweh your God pronounced this evil on this place; 3 and Yahweh has brought it, and done according as he spoke: because you have sinned against Yahweh, and have not obeyed his voice, therefore this thing has come on you. 4 Now, behold, I release you today from the chains which are on your hand. If it seems good to you to come with me into Babylon, come, and I will take care of you; but if it seems bad to you to come with me into Babylon, don’t. Behold, all the land is before you. Where it seems good and right to you to go, there go.” 5 Now while he had not yet gone back, “Go back then,” he said, “to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, whom the king of Babylon has made governor over the cities of Judah, and dwell with him among the people; or go wherever it seems right to you to go.”

So the captain of the guard gave him food and a present, and let him go. 6 Then Jeremiah went to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam to Mizpah, and lived with him among the people who were left in the land.

7 Now when all the captains of the forces who were in the fields, even they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah the son of Ahikam governor in the land, and had committed to him men, women, children, and of the poorest of the land, of those who were not carried away captive to Babylon; 8 then they came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan and Jonathan the sons of Kareah, and Seraiah the son of Tanhumeth, and the sons of Ephai the Netophathite, and Jezaniah the son of the Maacathite, they and their men. 9 Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan swore to them and to their men, saying, “Don’t be afraid to serve the Chaldeans. Dwell in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it shall be well with you. 10 As for me, behold, I will dwell at Mizpah, to stand before the Chaldeans who will come to us; but you, gather wine and summer fruits and oil, and put them in your vessels, and dwell in your cities that you have taken.”

11 Likewise when all the Jews who were in Moab, and among the children of Ammon, and in Edom, and who were in all the countries, heard that the king of Babylon had left a remnant of Judah, and that he had set over them Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan; 12 then all the Jews returned out of all places where they were driven, and came to the land of Judah, to Gedaliah, to Mizpah, and gathered wine and summer fruits very much.

13 Moreover Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces who were in the fields, came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, 14 and said to him, “Do you know that Baalis the king of the children of Ammon has sent Ishmael the son of Nethaniah to take your life?”

But Gedaliah the son of Ahikam didn’t believe them.

15 Then Johanan the son of Kareah spoke to Gedaliah in Mizpah secretly, saying, “Please let me go, and I will kill Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and no man shall know it. Why should he take your life, that all the Jews who are gathered to you should be scattered, and the remnant of Judah perish?”

16 But Gedaliah the son of Ahikam said to Johanan the son of Kareah, “You shall not do this thing; for you speak falsely of Ishmael.”

Jeremiah 41

1 Now in the seventh month, Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, of the royal offspring[*] and one of the chief officers of the king, and ten men with him, came to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam to Mizpah; and there they ate bread together in Mizpah. 2 Then Ishmael the son of Nethaniah arose, and the ten men who were with him, and struck Gedaliah the son of Ahikam the son of Shaphan with the sword, and killed him, whom the king of Babylon had made governor over the land. 3 Ishmael also killed all the Jews who were with him, with Gedaliah, at Mizpah, and the Chaldeans who were found there, the men of war.

4 The second day after he had killed Gedaliah, and no man knew it, 5 men came from Shechem, from Shiloh, and from Samaria, even eighty men, having their beards shaved and their clothes torn, and having cut themselves, with meal offerings and frankincense in their hand, to bring them to Yahweh’s house. 6 Ishmael the son of Nethaniah went out from Mizpah to meet them, weeping all along as he went: and as he met them, he said to them, “Come to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam.” 7 It was so, when they came into the middle of the city, that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah killed them, and cast them into the middle of the pit, he, and the men who were with him. 8 But ten men were found among those who said to Ishmael, “Don’t kill us; for we have stores hidden in the field, of wheat, and of barley, and of oil, and of honey.”

So he stopped, and didn’t kill them among their brothers. 9 Now the pit in which Ishmael cast all the dead bodies of the men whom he had killed, by the side of Gedaliah (the same was who which Asa the king had made for fear of Baasha king of Israel), Ishmael the son of Nethaniah filled it with those who were killed.

10 Then Ishmael carried away captive all the of the people who were left in Mizpah, even the king’s daughters, and all the people who remained in Mizpah, whom Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard had committed to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam. Ishmael the son of Nethaniah carried them away captive, and departed to go over to the children of Ammon.

11 But when Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces who were with him, heard of all the evil that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah had done, 12 then they took all the men, and went to fight with Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and found him by the great waters that are in Gibeon. 13 Now when all the people who were with Ishmael saw Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces who were with him, then they were glad. 14 So all the people who Ishmael had carried away captive from Mizpah turned about and came back, and went to Johanan the son of Kareah. 15 But Ishmael the son of Nethaniah escaped from Johanan with eight men, and went to the children of Ammon.

16 Then Johanan the son of Kareah, and all the captains of the forces who were with him, took all the remnant of the people whom he had recovered from Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, from Mizpah, after that he had killed Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the men of war, and the women, and the children, and the eunuchs, whom he had brought back from Gibeon. 17 They departed, and lived in Geruth Chimham, which is by Bethlehem, to go to enter into Egypt, 18 because of the Chaldeans; for they were afraid of them, because Ishmael the son of Nethaniah had killed Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, whom the king of Babylon made governor over the land.

or, seed

Jeremiah 44

1 The word that came to Jeremiah concerning all the Jews who lived in the land of Egypt, who lived at Migdol, and at Tahpanhes, and at Memphis, and in the country of Pathros, saying, 2 “Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘You have seen all the evil that I have brought on Jerusalem, and on all the cities of Judah. Behold, today they are a desolation, and no man dwells therein, 3 because of their wickedness which they have committed to provoke me to anger, in that they went to burn incense, to serve other gods, that they didn’t know, neither they, nor you, nor your fathers. 4 However I sent to you all my servants the prophets, rising up early and sending them, saying, “Oh, don’t do this abominable thing that I hate.” 5 But they didn’t listen and didn’t incline their ear. They didn’t turn from their wickedness, to stop burning incense to other gods. 6 Therefore my wrath and my anger was poured out, and was kindled in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem; and they are wasted and desolate, as it is today.’

7 “Therefore now Yahweh, the God of Armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Why do you commit great evil against your own souls, to cut off from yourselves man and woman, infant and nursing child out of the middle of Judah, to leave yourselves no one remaining; 8 in that you provoke me to anger with the works of your hands, burning incense to other gods in the land of Egypt, where you have gone to live; that you may be cut off, and that you may be a curse and a reproach among all the nations of the earth? 9 Have you forgotten the wickedness of your fathers, and the wickedness of the kings of Judah, and the wickedness of their wives, and your own wickedness, and the wickedness of your wives which they committed in the land of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem? 10 They are not humbled even to this day, neither have they feared, nor walked in my law, nor in my statutes, that I set before you and before your fathers.’

11 “Therefore Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Behold, I will set my face against you for evil, even to cut off all Judah. 12 I will take the remnant of Judah, that have set their faces to go into the land of Egypt to live there, and they will all be consumed. They will fall in the land of Egypt. They will be consumed by the sword and by the famine. They will die, from the least even to the greatest, by the sword and by the famine. They will be an object of horror, an astonishment, and a curse, and a reproach. 13 For I will punish those who dwell in the land of Egypt, as I have punished Jerusalem, by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence; 14 so that none of the remnant of Judah, who have gone into the land of Egypt to live there, shall escape or be left, to return into the land of Judah, to which they have a desire to return to dwell there; for no one will return except those who will escape.’”

15 Then all the men who knew that their wives burned incense to other gods, and all the women who stood by, a great assembly, even all the people who lived in the land of Egypt, in Pathros, answered Jeremiah, saying, 16 “As for the word that you have spoken to us in Yahweh’s name, we will not listen to you. 17 But we will certainly perform every word that has gone out of our mouth, to burn incense to the queen of the sky, and to pour out drink offerings to her, as we have done, we and our fathers, our kings and our princes, in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem; for then had we plenty of food, and were well, and saw no evil. 18 But since we stopped burning incense to the queen of the sky, and pouring out drink offerings to her, we have lacked all things, and have been consumed by the sword and by the famine.

19 “When we burned incense to the queen of the sky, and poured out drink offerings to her, did we make her cakes to worship her, and pour out drink offerings to her, without our husbands?”

20 Then Jeremiah said to all the people, to the men, and to the women, even to all the people who had given him an answer, saying, 21 “The incense that you burned in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem, you and your fathers, your kings and your princes, and the people of the land, didn’t Yahweh remember them, and didn’t it come into his mind? 22 Thus Yahweh could no longer bear, because of the evil of your doings, and because of the abominations which you have committed; therefore your land has become a desolation, and an astonishment, and a curse, without inhabitant, as it is today. 23 Because you have burned incense, and because you have sinned against Yahweh, and have not obeyed Yahweh’s voice, nor walked in his law, nor in his statutes, nor in his testimonies; therefore this evil has happened to you, as it is today.”

24 Moreover Jeremiah said to all the people, and to all the women, “Hear Yahweh’s word, all Judah who are in the land of Egypt! 25 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘You and your wives have both spoken with your mouths, and with your hands have fulfilled it, saying, “We will surely perform our vows that we have vowed, to burn incense to the queen of the sky, and to pour out drink offerings to her.”

“‘Establish then your vows, and perform your vows.’

26 “Therefore hear Yahweh’s word, all Judah who dwell in the land of Egypt: ‘Behold, I have sworn by my great name,’ says Yahweh, ‘that my name shall no more be named in the mouth of any man of Judah in all the land of Egypt, saying, “As the Lord Yahweh lives.” 27 Behold, I watch over them for evil, and not for good; and all the men of Judah who are in the land of Egypt shall be consumed by the sword and by the famine, until they are all gone. 28 Those who escape the sword shall return out of the land of Egypt into the land of Judah, few in number; and all the remnant of Judah, who have gone into the land of Egypt to live there, shall know whose word shall stand, mine, or theirs.

29 “‘This shall be the sign to you,’ says Yahweh, ‘that I will punish you in this place, that you may know that my words shall surely stand against you for evil.’ 30 Yahweh says, ‘Behold, I will give Pharaoh Hophra king of Egypt into the hand of his enemies, and into the hand of those who seek his life; as I gave Zedekiah king of Judah into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, who was his enemy, and sought his life.’”

Jeremiah 46

1 Yahweh’s word which came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the nations.

2 Of Egypt: concerning the army of Pharaoh Necoh king of Egypt, which was by the river Euphrates in Carchemish, which Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon struck in the fourth year of Jehoiakim the son of Josiah, king of Judah.

3 “Prepare the buckler and shield,

and draw near to battle!

4 Harness the horses, and get up, you horsemen,

and stand up with your helmets.

Polish the spears,

put on the coats of mail.

5 Why have I seen it?

They are dismayed and are turned backward.

Their mighty ones are beaten down,

have fled in haste,

and don’t look back.

Terror is on every side,”

says Yahweh.

6 “Don’t let the swift flee away,

nor the mighty man escape.

In the north by the river Euphrates

they have stumbled and fallen.

7 “Who is this who rises up like the Nile,

whose waters toss themselves like the rivers?

8 Egypt rises up like the Nile,

and his waters toss themselves like the rivers:

and he says, ‘I will rise up, I will cover the earth.

I will destroy cities and its inhabitants.’

9 Go up, you horses;

and rage, you chariots!

Let the mighty men go out:

Cush and Put, who handle the shield;

and the Ludim, who handle and bend the bow.

10 For that day is of the Lord, Yahweh of Armies,

a day of vengeance,

that he may avenge himself of his adversaries.

The sword will devour and be satiated,

and will drink its fill of their blood;

for the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, has a sacrifice in the north country by the river Euphrates.

11 Go up into Gilead, and take balm, virgin daughter of Egypt.

In vain do you use many medicines.

There is no healing for you.

12 The nations have heard of your shame,

and the earth is full of your cry;

for the mighty man has stumbled against the mighty,

they both fall together.”

13 The word that Yahweh spoke to Jeremiah the prophet, how that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon should come and strike the land of Egypt.

14 “Declare in Egypt,

publish in Migdol,

and publish in Memphis and in Tahpanhes:

say, ‘Stand up, and prepare;

for the sword has devoured around you.’

15 Why are your strong ones swept away?

they didn’t stand, because Yahweh pushed them.

16 He made many to stumble,

yes, they fell on one another:

and they said, ‘Arise, and let us go again to our own people,

and to the land of our birth,

from the oppressing sword.’

17 They cried there, ‘Pharaoh king of Egypt is but a noise;

he has let the appointed time pass by.’

18 “As I live,” says the King,

whose name is Yahweh of Armies,

“surely like Tabor among the mountains,

and like Carmel by the sea,

so shall he come.

19 You daughter who dwells in Egypt,

furnish yourself to go into captivity;

for Memphis shall become a desolation,

and shall be burned up,

without inhabitant.

20 “Egypt is a very beautiful heifer;

but destruction out of the north has come.

It has come.

21 Also her hired men in the middle of her are like calves of the stall;

for they also are turned back.

They have fled away together.

They didn’t stand,

for the day of their calamity has come on them,

the time of their visitation.

22 It’s sound will go like the serpent;

for they shall march with an army,

and come against her with axes, as wood cutters.

23 They shall cut down her forest,” says Yahweh,

“though it can’t be searched;

because they are more than the locusts,

and are innumerable.

24 The daughter of Egypt shall be disappointed;

she shall be delivered into the hand of the people of the north.”

25 Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says: “Behold, I will punish Amon of No, and Pharaoh, and Egypt, with her gods, and her kings; even Pharaoh, and those who trust in him. 26 I will deliver them into the hand of those who seek their lives, and into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and into the hand of his servants. Afterwards it shall be inhabited, as in the days of old,” says Yahweh.

27 “But don’t you be afraid, Jacob my servant,

neither be dismayed, Israel;

for, behold, I will save you from afar,

and your offspring[*] from the land of their captivity.

Jacob will return,

and will be quiet and at ease.

No one will make him afraid.

28 Don’t be afraid, O Jacob my servant,” says Yahweh;

“for I am with you;

for I will make a full end of all the nations where I have driven you;

but I will not make a full end of you,

but I will correct you in measure,

and will in no way leave you unpunished.”

or, seed

Jeremiah 48

1 Of Moab. Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says:

“Woe to Nebo!

for it is laid waste;

Kiriathaim is disappointed,

it is taken;

Misgab[*] is put to shame

and broken down.

2 The praise of Moab is no more;

in Heshbon they have devised evil against her:

‘Come, and let us cut her off from being a nation.’

You also, Madmen, will be brought to silence.

The sword will pursue you.

3 The sound of a cry from Horonaim,

desolation and great destruction!

4 Moab is destroyed.

Her little ones have caused a cry to be heard.

5 For they shall go up by the ascent of Luhith with continual weeping.

For at the descent of Horonaim they have heard the distress of the cry of destruction.

6 Flee! Save your lives!

Be like the juniper bush in the wilderness.

7 For, because you have trusted in your works and in your treasures,

you also shall be taken.

Chemosh will go out into captivity,

his priests and his princes together.

8 The destroyer will come on every city,

and no city will escape;

the valley also will perish,

and the plain will be destroyed; as Yahweh has spoken.

9 Give wings to Moab,

that she may fly and get herself away:

and her cities will become a desolation,

without anyone to dwell in them.

10 “Cursed is he who does the work of Yahweh negligently;

and cursed is he who keeps back his sword from blood.

11 “Moab has been at ease from his youth,

and he has settled on his lees,

and has not been emptied from vessel to vessel,

neither has he gone into captivity:

therefore his taste remains in him,

and his scent is not changed.

12 Therefore behold, the days come,” says Yahweh,

“that I will send to him those who pour off,

and they shall pour him off;

and they shall empty his vessels,

and break their bottles in pieces.

13 Moab shall be ashamed of Chemosh,

as the house of Israel was ashamed of Bethel their confidence.

14 “How do you say, ‘We are mighty men,

and valiant men for the war?’

15 Moab is laid waste,

and they have gone up into his cities,

and his chosen young men have gone down to the slaughter,”

says the King, whose name is Yahweh of Armies.

16 “The calamity of Moab is near to come,

and his affliction hurries fast.

17 All you who are around him, bemoan him,

and all you who know his name; say,

‘How is the strong staff broken,

the beautiful rod!’

18 “You daughter who dwells in Dibon,

come down from your glory,

and sit in thirst;

for the destroyer of Moab has come up against you,

he has destroyed your strongholds.

19 Inhabitant of Aroer, stand by the way, and watch:

ask him who flees, and her who escapes;

say, ‘What has been done?’

20 Moab is disappointed;

for it is broken down.

Wail and cry!

Tell it by the Arnon, that Moab is laid waste.

21 Judgment has come on the plain country,

on Holon, and on Jahzah, and on Mephaath,

22 and on Dibon, and on Nebo, and on Beth Diblathaim,

23 and on Kiriathaim, and on Beth Gamul, and on Beth Meon,

24 and on Kerioth, and on Bozrah,

and on all the cities of the land of Moab, far or near.

25 The horn of Moab is cut off,

and his arm is broken,” says Yahweh.

26 “Make him drunken;

for he magnified himself against Yahweh:

and Moab shall wallow in his vomit,

and he also shall be in derision.

27 For wasn’t Israel a derision to you?

was he found among thieves?

for as often as you speak of him,

you shake your head.

28 You inhabitants of Moab, leave the cities, and dwell in the rock;

and be like the dove that makes her nest over the mouth of the abyss.

29 “We have heard of the pride of Moab.

He is very proud; his loftiness, and his pride,

and his arrogance, and the haughtiness of his heart.

30 I know his wrath,” says Yahweh, “that it is nothing;

his boastings have worked nothing.

31 Therefore I will wail for Moab.

Yes, I will cry out for all Moab.

They shall mourn for the men of Kir Heres.

32 With more than the weeping of Jazer

will I weep for you, vine of Sibmah.

Your branches passed over the sea.

They reached even to the sea of Jazer.

The destroyer has fallen on your summer fruits

and on your vintage.

33 Gladness and joy is taken away from the fruitful field

and from the land of Moab.

I have caused wine to cease from the wine presses.

No one will tread with shouting.

The shouting will be no shouting.

34 From the cry of Heshbon even to Elealeh,

even to Jahaz have they uttered their voice,

from Zoar even to Horonaim, to Eglath Shelishiyah:

for the waters of Nimrim also will become desolate.

35 Moreover I will cause to cease in Moab,” says Yahweh,

“him who offers in the high place,

and him who burns incense to his gods.

36 Therefore my heart sounds for Moab like pipes,

and my heart sounds like pipes for the men of Kir Heres.

Therefore the abundance that he has gotten has perished.

37 For every head is bald,

and every beard clipped.

There are cuttings on all the hands,

and sackcloth on the waist.

38 On all the housetops of Moab,

and in its streets, there is lamentation everywhere;

for I have broken Moab like a vessel in which no one delights,” says Yahweh.

39 “How it is broken down!

How they wail!

How Moab has turned the back with shame!

So shall Moab become a derision

and a terror to all who are around him.”

40 For Yahweh says: “Behold, he shall fly as an eagle,

and shall spread out his wings against Moab.

41 Kerioth is taken,

and the strongholds are seized.

The heart of the mighty men of Moab at that day

shall be as the heart of a woman in her pangs.

42 Moab shall be destroyed from being a people,

because he has magnified himself against Yahweh.

43 Terror, the pit, and the snare are on you,

inhabitant of Moab,” says Yahweh.

44 “He who flees from the terror will fall into the pit;

and he who gets up out of the pit will be taken in the snare:

for I will bring on him, even on Moab,

the year of their visitation,” says Yahweh.

45 “Those who fled stand without strength under the shadow of Heshbon;

for a fire has gone out of Heshbon,

and a flame from the middle of Sihon,

and has devoured the corner of Moab,

and the crown of the head of the tumultuous ones.

46 Woe to you, O Moab!

The people of Chemosh are undone;

for your sons are taken away captive,

and your daughters into captivity.

47 “Yet I will bring back the captivity of Moab in the latter days,”

says Yahweh.

Thus far is the judgment of Moab.

or, The stronghold

Jeremiah 49

1 Of the children of Ammon. Yahweh says:

“Has Israel no sons?

has he no heir?

Why then does Malcam possess Gad,

and his people dwell in its cities?

2 Therefore behold, the days come,”

says Yahweh,

“that I will cause an alarm of war to be heard against Rabbah of the children of Ammon;

and it shall become a desolate heap,

and her daughters will be burned with fire:

then Israel will possess those who possessed him,”

says Yahweh.

3 “Wail, Heshbon, for Ai is laid waste!

Cry, you daughters of Rabbah!

Clothe yourself in sackcloth.

Lament, and run back and forth among the fences;

for Malcam will go into captivity,

his priests and his princes together.

4 Why do you boast in the valleys,

your flowing valley, backsliding daughter?

You trusted in her treasures,

saying, ‘Who will come to me?’

5 Behold, I will bring a terror on you,”

says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies,

“from all who are around you.

All of you will be driven completely out,

and there will be no one to gather together the fugitives.

6 “But afterward I will bring back the captivity of the children of Ammon,”

says Yahweh.

7 Of Edom. Yahweh of Armies says:

“Is wisdom no more in Teman?

Has counsel perished from the prudent?

Has their wisdom vanished?

8 Flee! Turn back!

Dwell in the depths, inhabitants of Dedan;

for I will bring the calamity of Esau on him when I visit him.

9 If grape gatherers came to you,

would they not leave some gleaning grapes?

If thieves came by night,

wouldn’t they steal until they had enough?

10 But I have made Esau bare,

I have uncovered his secret places,

and he will not be able to hide himself.

His offspring[*] is destroyed,

with his brothers and his neighbors;

and he is no more.

11 Leave your fatherless children.

I will preserve them alive.

Let your widows trust in me.”

12 For Yahweh says: “Behold, they to whom it didn’t pertain to drink of the cup shall certainly drink; and are you he who shall altogether go unpunished? You shall not go unpunished, but you shall surely drink. 13 For I have sworn by myself,” says Yahweh, “that Bozrah will become an astonishment, a reproach, a waste, and a curse. All its cities will be perpetual wastes.”

14 I have heard news from Yahweh,

and an ambassador is sent among the nations,

saying, “Gather yourselves together!

Come against her!

Rise up to the battle!”

15 “For, behold, I have made you small among the nations,

and despised among men.

16 As for your terror,

the pride of your heart has deceived you,

O you who dwell in the clefts of the rock,

who hold the height of the hill,

though you should make your nest as high as the eagle,

I will bring you down from there,” says Yahweh.

17 “Edom will become an astonishment.

Everyone who passes by it will be astonished,

and will hiss at all its plagues.

18 As in the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah and its neighbor cities,” says Yahweh,

“no man will dwell there,

neither will any son of man live therein.

19 “Behold, he will come up like a lion from the pride of the Jordan against the strong habitation:

for I will suddenly make them run away from it;

and whoever is chosen,

I will appoint him over it.

For who is like me?

Who will appoint me a time?

Who is the shepherd who will stand before me?”

20 Therefore hear the counsel of Yahweh, that he has taken against Edom;

and his purposes, that he has purposed against the inhabitants of Teman:

Surely they will drag them away,

the little ones of the flock.

Surely he will make their habitation desolate over them.

21 The earth trembles at the noise of their fall;

there is a cry, the noise which is heard in the Red Sea.

22 Behold, he will come up and fly as the eagle,

and spread out his wings against Bozrah.

The heart of the mighty men of Edom at that day will be as the heart of a woman in her pangs.

23 Of Damascus:

“Hamath is confounded, and Arpad;

for they have heard evil news,

they are melted away:

there is sorrow on the sea;

it can’t be quiet.

24 Damascus has grown feeble,

she turns herself to flee,

and trembling has seized on her:

anguish and sorrows have taken hold of her,

as of a woman in travail.

25 How is the city of praise not forsaken,

the city of my joy?

26 Therefore her young men shall fall in her streets,

and all the men of war shall be brought to silence in that day,”

says Yahweh of Armies.

27 “I will kindle a fire in the wall of Damascus,

and it shall devour the palaces of Ben Hadad.”

28 Of Kedar, and of the kingdoms of Hazor, which Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon struck. Yahweh says:

“Arise, go up to Kedar,

and destroy the children of the east.

29 They will take their tents and their flocks.

they will carry away for themselves their curtains,

all their vessels, and their camels;

and they will cry to them, Terror on every side!

30 Flee!

Wander far off!

Dwell in the depths, you inhabitants of Hazor,” says Yahweh;

“for Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon has taken counsel against you,

and has conceived a purpose against you.

31 Arise! Go up to a nation that is at ease,

that dwells without care,” says Yahweh;

“that has neither gates nor bars,

that dwells alone.

32 Their camels will be a booty,

and the multitude of their livestock a plunder.

I will scatter to all winds those who have the corners of their beards cut off;

and I will bring their calamity from every side of them,”

says Yahweh.

33 Hazor will be a dwelling place of jackals,

a desolation forever.

No man shall dwell there,

neither shall any son of man live therein.”

34 Yahweh’s word that came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning Elam, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah king of Judah, saying, 35 “Yahweh of Armies says:

‘Behold, I will break the bow of Elam,

the chief of their might.

36 On Elam will I bring the four winds from the four quarters of the sky,

and will scatter them toward all those winds.

There will be no nation where the outcasts of Elam will not come.

37 I will cause Elam to be dismayed before their enemies,

and before those who seek their life;

and I will bring evil on them, even my fierce anger,’ says Yahweh;

‘and I will send the sword after them,

until I have consumed them;

38 and I will set my throne in Elam,

and will destroy from there king and princes,’ says Yahweh.

39 ‘But it shall happen in the latter days,

that I will bring back the captivity of Elam,’ says Yahweh.”

or, seed

Jeremiah 50

1 The word that Yahweh spoke concerning Babylon, concerning the land of the Chaldeans, by Jeremiah the prophet.

2 “Declare among the nations and publish,

and set up a standard;

publish, and don’t conceal:

say, ‘Babylon has been taken,

Bel is disappointed,

Merodach is dismayed!

Her images are disappointed.

Her idols are dismayed.’

3 For a nation comes up out of the north against her,

which shall make her land desolate,

and no one shall dwell therein.

They have fled.

They are gone,

both man and animal.

4 “In those days, and in that time,” says Yahweh,

“the children of Israel will come,

they and the children of Judah together;

they will go on their way weeping,

and will seek Yahweh their God.

5 They will inquire concerning Zion with their faces turned toward it,

saying, ‘Come, and join yourselves to Yahweh in an everlasting covenant

that shall not be forgotten.’

6 My people have been lost sheep:

their shepherds have caused them to go astray;

they have turned them away on the mountains;

they have gone from mountain to hill;

they have forgotten their resting place.

7 All who found them have devoured them;

and their adversaries said, ‘We are not guilty,

because they have sinned against Yahweh,

the habitation of righteousness,

even Yahweh, the hope of their fathers.’

8 “Flee out of the middle of Babylon!

Go out of the land of the Chaldeans,

and be as the male goats before the flocks.

9 For, behold, I will stir up

and cause to come up against Babylon a company of great nations from the north country;

and they will set themselves in array against her.

She will be taken from there.

Their arrows will be as of an expert mighty man.

None of them will return in vain.

10 Chaldea shall be a prey.

All who prey on her shall be satisfied,” says Yahweh.

11 “Because you are glad,

because you rejoice,

O you who plunder my heritage,

because you are wanton as a heifer that treads out the grain,

and neigh as strong horses;

12 your mother will be utterly disappointed.

She who bore you will be confounded.

Behold, she shall be the least of the nations,

a wilderness, a dry land, and a desert.

13 Because of Yahweh’s wrath she won’t be inhabited,

but she will be wholly desolate.

Everyone who goes by Babylon will be astonished,

and hiss at all her plagues.

14 Set yourselves in array against Babylon all around,

all you who bend the bow;

shoot at her, spare no arrows:

for she has sinned against Yahweh.

15 Shout against her all around.

She has submitted herself.

Her bulwarks have fallen.

Her walls have been thrown down,

for it is the vengeance of Yahweh.

Take vengeance on her.

As she has done, do to her.

16 Cut off the sower from Babylon,

and him who handles the sickle in the time of harvest.

For fear of the oppressing sword,

they will each return to their own people,

and they will each flee to their own land.

17 “Israel is a hunted sheep.

The lions have driven him away.

First, the king of Assyria devoured him,

and now at last Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon has broken his bones.”

18 Therefore Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, says:

“Behold, I will punish the king of Babylon and his land,

as I have punished the king of Assyria.

19 I will bring Israel again to his pasture,

and he will feed on Carmel and Bashan.

His soul will be satisfied on the hills of Ephraim and in Gilead.

20 In those days, and in that time,” says Yahweh,

“the iniquity of Israel shall be sought for,

and there will be none;

also the sins of Judah,

and they won’t be found;

for I will pardon them whom I leave as a remnant.

21 “Go up against the land of Merathaim,

even against it, and against the inhabitants of Pekod.

Kill and utterly destroy after them,” says Yahweh,

“and do according to all that I have commanded you.

22 A sound of battle is in the land,

and of great destruction.

23 How the hammer of the whole earth is cut apart and broken!

How Babylon has become a desolation among the nations!

24 I have laid a snare for you,

and you are also taken, Babylon,

and you weren’t aware.

You are found,

and also caught,

because you have fought against Yahweh.

25 Yahweh has opened his armory,

and has brought out the weapons of his indignation;

for the Lord, Yahweh of Armies, has a work to do in the land of the Chaldeans.

26 Come against her from the farthest border.

Open her storehouses.

Cast her up as heaps.

Destroy her utterly.

Let nothing of her be left.

27 Kill all her bulls.

Let them go down to the slaughter.

Woe to them! For their day has come,

the time of their visitation.

28 Listen to those who flee and escape out of the land of Babylon,

to declare in Zion the vengeance of Yahweh our God,

the vengeance of his temple.

29 “Call together the archers against Babylon,

all those who bend the bow.

Encamp against her all around.

Let none of it escape.

Recompense her according to her work.

According to all that she has done, do to her;

for she has been proud against Yahweh,

against the Holy One of Israel.

30 Therefore her young men will fall in her streets,

and all her men of war will be brought to silence in that day,” says Yahweh.

31 “Behold, I am against you, you proud one,” says the Lord, Yahweh of Armies;

“for your day has come,

the time that I will visit you.

32 The proud one will stumble and fall,

and no one will raise him up.

I will kindle a fire in his cities,

and it shall devour all who are around him.”

33 Yahweh of Armies says: “The children of Israel and the children of Judah are oppressed together.

All who took them captive hold them fast.

They refuse to let them go.

34 Their Redeemer is strong:

Yahweh of Armies is his name.

He will thoroughly plead their cause,

that he may give rest to the earth,

and disquiet the inhabitants of Babylon.

35 “A sword is on the Chaldeans,” says Yahweh,

“and on the inhabitants of Babylon,

on her princes,

and on her wise men.

36 A sword is on the boasters,

and they will become fools.

A sword is on her mighty men,

and they will be dismayed.

37 A sword is on their horses,

on their chariots,

and on all the mixed people who are in the middle of her;

and they will become as women.

A sword is on her treasures,

and they will be robbed.

38 A drought is on her waters,

and they shall be dried up;

for it is a land of engraved images,

and they are mad over idols.

39 Therefore the wild animals of the desert

with the wolves will dwell there.

The ostriches will dwell therein;

and it will be inhabited no more forever;

neither will it be lived in from generation to generation.

40 As when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah and its neighbor cities,” says Yahweh,

“so no man will dwell there,

neither will any son of man live therein.

41 “Behold, a people comes from the north;

and a great nation and many kings shall be stirred up from the uttermost parts of the earth.

42 They take up bow and spear.

They are cruel, and have no mercy.

Their voice roars like the sea.

They ride on horses,

everyone set in array,

as a man to the battle,

against you, daughter of Babylon.

43 The king of Babylon has heard the news of them,

and his hands become feeble:

anguish has taken hold of him,

pains as of a woman in labor.

44 Behold, the enemy will come up like a lion

from the pride of the Jordan against the strong habitation;

for I will suddenly make them run away from it.

Whoever is chosen,

I will appoint him over it;

for who is like me?

Who will appoint me a time?

Who is the shepherd who can stand before me?”

45 Therefore hear the counsel of Yahweh,

that he has taken against Babylon;

and his purposes,

that he has purposed against the land of the Chaldeans:

Surely they shall drag them away,

even the little ones of the flock.

Surely he shall make their habitation desolate over them.

46 At the noise of the taking of Babylon the earth trembles;

and the cry is heard among the nations.

Jeremiah 51

1 Yahweh says:

“Behold, I will raise up against Babylon,

and against those who dwell in Lebkamai, a destroying wind.

2 I will send to Babylon strangers, who will winnow her.

They will empty her land;

for in the day of trouble they will be against her all around.

3 Against him who bends, let the archer bend his bow,

also against him who lifts himself up in his coat of mail.

Don’t spare her young men!

Utterly destroy all her army!

4 They will fall down slain in the land of the Chaldeans,

and thrust through in her streets.

5 For Israel is not forsaken, nor Judah, by his God,

by Yahweh of Armies;

though their land is full of guilt against the Holy One of Israel.

6 “Flee out of the middle of Babylon!

Everyone save his own life!

Don’t be cut off in her iniquity;

for it is the time of Yahweh’s vengeance.

He will render to her a recompense.

7 Babylon has been a golden cup in Yahweh’s hand,

who made all the earth drunk.

The nations have drunk of her wine;

therefore the nations have gone mad.

8 Babylon has suddenly fallen and been destroyed!

Wail for her!

Take balm for her pain.

Perhaps she may be healed.

9 “We would have healed Babylon,

but she is not healed.

Forsake her,

and let us each go into his own country;

for her judgment reaches to heaven,

and is lifted up even to the skies.

10 ‘Yahweh has produced our righteousness:

come, and let us declare in Zion the work of Yahweh our God.’

11 “Make the arrows sharp!

Hold the shields firmly!

Yahweh has stirred up the spirit of the kings of the Medes,

because his purpose is against Babylon, to destroy it;

for it is the vengeance of Yahweh,

the vengeance of his temple.

12 Set up a standard against the walls of Babylon!

Make the watch strong!

Set the watchmen,

and prepare the ambushes;

for Yahweh has both purposed and done

that which he spoke concerning the inhabitants of Babylon.

13 You who dwell on many waters, abundant in treasures,

your end has come, the measure of your covetousness.

14 Yahweh of Armies has sworn by himself, saying,

‘Surely I will fill you with men,

as with the canker worm;

and they will lift up a shout against you.’

15 “He has made the earth by his power.

He has established the world by his wisdom.

By his understanding he has stretched out the heavens.

16 When he utters his voice,

there is a roar of waters in the heavens,

and he causes the vapors to ascend from the ends of the earth.

He makes lightning for the rain,

and brings the wind out of his treasuries.

17 “Every man has become brutish without knowledge.

Every goldsmith is disappointed by his image;

for his molten image is falsehood,

and there is no breath in them.

18 They are vanity,

a work of delusion.

In the time of their visitation, they will perish.

19 The portion of Jacob is not like these,

for he is the former of all things;

including the tribe of his inheritance:

Yahweh of Armies is his name.

20 “You are my battle ax and weapons of war.

With you I will break the nations into pieces.

With you I will destroy kingdoms.

21 With you I will break in pieces

the horse and his rider.

22 With you I will break in pieces

the chariot and him who rides therein.

With you I will break in pieces

man and woman.

With you I will break in pieces

the old man and the youth.

With you I will break in pieces

the young man and the virgin.

23 With you I will break in pieces

the shepherd and his flock.

With you I will break in pieces

the farmer and his yoke.

With you will I break in pieces

governors and deputies.

24 “I will render to Babylon and to all the inhabitants of Chaldea all their evil that they have done in Zion in your sight,” says Yahweh.

25 “Behold, I am against you, destroying mountain,” says Yahweh,

“which destroys all the earth.

I will stretch out my hand on you,

roll you down from the rocks,

and will make you a burned mountain.

26 They shall not take cornerstone from you,

nor a stone for foundations;

but you will be desolate for ever,” says Yahweh.

27 “Set up a standard in the land!

Blow the trumpet among the nations!

Prepare the nations against her!

Call together against her the kingdoms of Ararat, Minni, and Ashkenaz!

Appoint a marshal against her!

Cause the horses to come up as the rough canker worm!

28 Prepare against her the nations,

the kings of the Medes, its governors, and all its deputies, and all the land of their dominion!

29 The land trembles and is in pain;

for the purposes of Yahweh against Babylon stand,

to make the land of Babylon a desolation, without inhabitant.

30 The mighty men of Babylon have stopped fighting,

they remain in their strongholds.

Their might has failed.

They have become as women.

Her dwelling places are set on fire.

Her bars are broken.

31 One runner will run to meet another,

and one messenger to meet another,

to show the king of Babylon that his city is taken on every quarter.

32 So the passages are seized.

They have burned the reeds with fire.

The men of war are frightened.”

33 For Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel says:

“The daughter of Babylon is like a threshing floor at the time when it is trodden.

Yet a little while, and the time of harvest shall come for her.”

34 “Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon has devoured me.

He has crushed me.

He has made me an empty vessel.

He has, like a monster, swallowed me up.

He has filled his mouth with my delicacies.

He has cast me out.

35 May the violence done to me and to my flesh be on Babylon!”

the inhabitant of Zion will say; and,

“May my blood be on the inhabitants of Chaldea!”

will Jerusalem say.

36 Therefore Yahweh says:

“Behold, I will plead your cause,

and take vengeance for you.

I will dry up her sea,

and make her fountain dry.

37 Babylon will become heaps,

a dwelling place for jackals,

an astonishment, and a hissing,

without inhabitant.

38 They will roar together like young lions.

They will growl as lions’ cubs.

39 When they are heated, I will make their feast,

and I will make them drunk,

that they may rejoice,

and sleep a perpetual sleep,

and not wake up,” says Yahweh.

40 “I will bring them down like lambs to the slaughter,

like rams with male goats.

41 “How Sheshach is taken!

and the praise of the whole earth seized!

How Babylon has become a desolation among the nations!

42 The sea has come up on Babylon.

She is covered with the multitude of its waves.

43 Her cities have become a desolation,

a dry land, and a desert,

a land in which no man dwells,

neither does any son of man pass by it.

44 I will execute judgment on Bel in Babylon,

and I will bring out of his mouth that which he has swallowed up.

The nations shall not flow any more to him.

Yes, the wall of Babylon will fall.

45 “My people, go away from the middle of her,

and each of you save yourselves from Yahweh’s fierce anger.

46 Don’t let your heart faint.

Don’t fear for the news that will be heard in the land.

For news will come one year,

and after that in another year news will come,

and violence in the land,

ruler against ruler.

47 Therefore behold, the days come that I will execute judgment on the engraved images of Babylon;

and her whole land will be confounded.

All her slain will fall in the middle of her.

48 Then the heavens and the earth,

and all that is therein,

will sing for joy over Babylon;

for the destroyers will come to her from the north,” says Yahweh.

49 “As Babylon has caused the slain of Israel to fall,

so the slain of all the land will fall at Babylon.

50 You who have escaped the sword, go!

Don’t stand still!

Remember Yahweh from afar,

and let Jerusalem come into your mind.”

51 “We are confounded,

because we have heard reproach.

Confusion has covered our faces,

for strangers have come into the sanctuaries of Yahweh’s house.”

52 “Therefore behold, the days come,” says Yahweh,

“that I will execute judgment on her engraved images;

and through all her land the wounded will groan.

53 Though Babylon should mount up to the sky,

and though she should fortify the height of her strength,

yet destroyers will come to her from me,” says Yahweh.

54 “The sound of a cry comes from Babylon,

and of great destruction from the land of the Chaldeans!

55 For Yahweh lays Babylon waste,

and destroys out of her the great voice!

Their waves roar like many waters.

The noise of their voice is uttered.

56 For the destroyer has come on her,

even on Babylon.

Her mighty men are taken.

Their bows are broken in pieces,

for Yahweh is a God of recompenses.

He will surely repay.

57 I will make her princes, her wise men,

her governors, her deputies, and her mighty men drunk.

They will sleep a perpetual sleep,

and not wake up,”

says the King, whose name is Yahweh of Armies.

58 Yahweh of Armies says:

“The wide walls of Babylon will be utterly overthrown.

Her high gates will be burned with fire.

The peoples will labor for vanity,

and the nations for the fire;

and they will be weary.”

59 The word which Jeremiah the prophet commanded Seraiah the son of Neriah, the son of Mahseiah, when he went with Zedekiah the king of Judah to Babylon in the fourth year of his reign. Now Seraiah was chief quartermaster. 60 Jeremiah wrote in a book all the evil that should come on Babylon, even all these words that are written concerning Babylon. 61 Jeremiah said to Seraiah, “When you come to Babylon, then see that you read all these words, 62 and say, ‘Yahweh, you have spoken concerning this place, to cut it off, that no one will dwell in it, neither man nor animal, but that it will be desolate forever.’ 63 It shall be, when you have finished reading this book, that you shall bind a stone to it, and cast it into the middle of the Euphrates. 64 Then you shall say, ‘Thus will Babylon sink, and will not rise again because of the evil that I will bring on her; and they shall be weary.’”

Thus far are the words of Jeremiah.

Jeremiah 52

1 Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign. He reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. 2 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, according to all that Jehoiakim had done. 3 For through Yahweh’s anger this happened in Jerusalem and Judah, until he had cast them out from his presence.

Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon. 4 In the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, in the tenth day of the month, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came, he and all his army, against Jerusalem, and encamped against it; and they built forts against it round about. 5 So the city was besieged to the eleventh year of king Zedekiah.

6 In the fourth month, in the ninth day of the month, the famine was severe in the city, so that there was no bread for the people of the land. 7 Then a breach was made in the city, and all the men of war fled, and went out of the city by night by the way of the gate between the two walls, which was by the king’s garden. Now the Chaldeans were against the city all around. The men of war went toward the Arabah, 8 but the army of the Chaldeans pursued the king, and overtook Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho; and all his army was scattered from him. 9 Then they took the king, and carried him up to the king of Babylon to Riblah in the land of Hamath; and he gave judgment on him. 10 The king of Babylon killed the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes: he killed also all the princes of Judah in Riblah. 11 He put out the eyes of Zedekiah; and the king of Babylon bound him in fetters, and carried him to Babylon, and put him in prison until the day of his death.

12 Now in the fifth month, in the tenth day of the month, which was the nineteenth year of king Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard, who stood before the king of Babylon, came into Jerusalem. 13 He burned Yahweh’s house, and the king’s house; and all the houses of Jerusalem, even every great house, he burned with fire. 14 All the army of the Chaldeans, who were with the captain of the guard, broke down all the walls of Jerusalem all around. 15 Then Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive of the poorest of the people, and the residue of the people who were left in the city, and those who fell away, who fell to the king of Babylon, and the residue of the multitude. 16 But Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard left of the poorest of the land to be vineyard keepers and farmers.

17 The Chaldeans broke the pillars of brass that were in Yahweh’s house, and the bases and the bronze sea that were in Yahweh’s house in pieces, and carried all of their brass to Babylon. 18 They also took away the pots, the shovels, the snuffers, the basins, the spoons, and all the vessels of brass with which they ministered. 19 The captain of the guard took away the cups, the fire pans, the basins, the pots, the lamp stands, the spoons, and the bowls; that which was of gold, in gold, and that which was of silver, in silver.

20 They took the two pillars, the one sea, and the twelve bronze bulls that were under the bases, which king Solomon had made for Yahweh’s house. The brass of all these vessels was without weight. 21 As for the pillars, the height of the one pillar was eighteen cubits;[*] and a line of twelve cubits encircled it; and its thickness was four fingers. It was hollow. 22 A capital of brass was on it; and the height of the one capital was five cubits,[*] with network and pomegranates on the capital all around, all of brass: and the second pillar also had like these, and pomegranates. 23 There were ninety-six pomegranates on the sides; all the pomegranates were one hundred on the network all around.

24 The captain of the guard took Seraiah the chief priest, and Zephaniah the second priest, and the three keepers of the threshold: 25 and out of the city he took an officer who was set over the men of war; and seven men of those who saw the king’s face, who were found in the city; and the scribe of the captain of the army, who mustered the people of the land; and sixty men of the people of the land, who were found in the middle of the city. 26 Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard took them, and brought them to the king of Babylon to Riblah. 27 The king of Babylon struck them, and put them to death at Riblah in the land of Hamath.

So Judah was carried away captive out of his land. 28 This is the people whom Nebuchadnezzar carried away captive:

in the seventh year three thousand twenty-three Jews;

29 in the eighteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar he carried away captive from Jerusalem eight hundred thirty-two persons;

30 in the twenty-third year of Nebuchadnezzar Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive of the Jews seven hundred forty-five persons:

all the persons were four thousand and six hundred.

31 In the thirty-seventh year of the captivity of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the twelfth month, in the twenty-fifth day of the month, Evilmerodach king of Babylon, in the first year of his reign, lifted up the head of Jehoiachin king of Judah, and released him from prison; 32 and he spoke kindly to him, and set his throne above the throne of the kings who were with him in Babylon, 33 and changed his prison garments. Jehoiachin ate bread before him continually all the days of his life: 34 and for his allowance, there was a continual allowance given him by the king of Babylon, every day a portion until the day of his death, all the days of his life.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Lamentations 1

1 How the city sits solitary,

that was full of people!

She has become as a widow,

who was great among the nations!

She who was a princess among the provinces

has become tributary!

2 She weeps bitterly in the night,

and her tears are on her cheeks;

among all her lovers

she has no one to comfort her:

All her friends have dealt treacherously with her;

they have become her enemies.

3 Judah has gone into captivity because of affliction,

and because of great servitude;

she dwells among the nations,

she finds no rest:

all her persecutors overtook her within the straits.

4 The ways of Zion mourn,

because no one come to the solemn assembly;

all her gates are desolate,

her priests sigh:

her virgins are afflicted,

and she herself is in bitterness.

5 Her adversaries have become the head,

her enemies prosper;

for Yahweh[*] has afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions:

her young children have gone into captivity before the adversary.

6 All majesty has departed from the daughter of Zion:

her princes have become like deer that find no pasture,

they have gone without strength before the pursuer.

7 Jerusalem remembers in the days of her affliction and of her miseries

all her pleasant things that were from the days of old:

when her people fell into the hand of the adversary,

and no one helped her,

The adversaries saw her,

they mocked at her desolations.

8 Jerusalem has grievously sinned;

therefore she has become as an unclean thing;

all who honored her despise her,

because they have seen her nakedness:

yes, she sighs, and turns backward.

9 Her filthiness was in her skirts;

she didn’t remember her latter end;

therefore she has come down astoundingly;

she has no comforter:

“See, Yahweh, my affliction;

for the enemy has magnified himself.”

10 The adversary has spread out his hand on all her pleasant things:

for she has seen that the nations are entered into her sanctuary,

concerning whom you commanded that they should not enter into your assembly.

11 All her people sigh, they seek bread;

they have given their pleasant things for food to refresh the soul:

“Look, Yahweh, and see;

for I have become abject.”

12 “Is it nothing to you, all you who pass by?

Look, and see if there is any sorrow like my sorrow,

which is brought on me,

with which Yahweh has afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger.

13 “From on high has he sent fire into my bones,

and it prevails against them;

He has spread a net for my feet.

He has turned me back.

He has made me desolate and faint all day long.

14 “The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand;

They are knit together.

They have come up on my neck.

He has made my strength to fail.

The Lord[*] has delivered me into their hands,

against whom I am not able to stand.

15 “The Lord has set at nothing all my mighty men within me.

He has called a solemn assembly against me to crush my young men.

The Lord has trodden as in a wine press the virgin daughter of Judah.

16 “For these things I weep.

My eye, my eye runs down with water,

because the comforter who should refresh my soul is far from me.

My children are desolate,

because the enemy has prevailed.”

17 Zion spreads out her hands.

There is no one to comfort her;

Yahweh has commanded concerning Jacob,

that those who are around him should be his adversaries.

Jerusalem is among them as an unclean thing.

18 “Yahweh is righteous;

for I have rebelled against his commandment.

Please hear all you peoples,

and see my sorrow.

My virgins and my young men have gone into captivity.

19 “I called for my lovers,

but they deceived me.

My priests and my elders gave up the spirit in the city,

while they sought food for themselves to refresh their souls.

20 “See, Yahweh; for I am in distress.

My heart is troubled.

My heart is turned within me,

for I have grievously rebelled.

Abroad the sword bereaves.

At home it is like death.

21 “They have heard that I sigh.

There is no one to comfort me.

All my enemies have heard of my trouble.

They are glad that you have done it:

You will bring the day that you have proclaimed,

and they will be like me.

22 “Let all their wickedness come before you;

Do to them as you have done to me for all my transgressions.

For my sighs are many,

and my heart is faint.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Lamentations 2

1 How has the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger!

He has cast down from heaven to the earth the beauty of Israel,

And hasn’t remembered his footstool in the day of his anger.

2 The Lord has swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob,

and has not pitied:

He has thrown down in his wrath the strongholds of the daughter of Judah;

He has brought them down to the ground;

he has profaned the kingdom and its princes.

3 He has cut off in fierce anger all the horn of Israel;

He has drawn back his right hand from before the enemy:

He has burned up Jacob like a flaming fire,

which devours all around.

4 He has bent his bow like an enemy,

he has stood with his right hand as an adversary,

Has killed all that were pleasant to the eye:

In the tent of the daughter of Zion he has poured out his wrath like fire.

5 The Lord has become as an enemy,

he has swallowed up Israel;

He has swallowed up all her palaces,

he has destroyed his strongholds;

He has multiplied in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation.

6 He has violently taken away his tabernacle,

as if it were of a garden;

he has destroyed his place of assembly:

Yahweh has caused solemn assembly and Sabbath to be forgotten in Zion,

Has despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest.

7 The Lord has cast off his altar,

he has abhorred his sanctuary;

He has given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces:

They have made a noise in Yahweh’s house,

as in the day of a solemn assembly.

8 Yahweh has purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion;

He has stretched out the line,

he has not withdrawn his hand from destroying;

He has made the rampart and wall to lament;

they languish together.

9 Her gates are sunk into the ground;

he has destroyed and broken her bars:

Her king and her princes are among the nations where the law is not;

Yes, her prophets find no vision from Yahweh.

10 The elders of the daughter of Zion sit on the ground,

they keep silence;

They have cast up dust on their heads;

they have clothed themselves with sackcloth:

The virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.

11 My eyes fail with tears,

my heart is troubled;

My liver is poured on the earth,

because of the destruction of the daughter of my people,

Because the young children and the infants swoon in the streets of the city.

12 They ask their mothers,

“Where is grain and wine?”

when they swoon as the wounded in the streets of the city,

when their soul is poured out into their mothers’ bosom.

13 What shall I testify to you?

what shall I liken to you, daughter of Jerusalem?

What shall I compare to you,

that I may comfort you, virgin daughter of Zion?

For your breach is great like the sea:

who can heal you?

14 Your prophets have seen for you false and foolish visions;

They have not uncovered your iniquity,

to bring back your captivity,

but have seen for you false revelations and causes of banishment.

15 All that pass by clap their hands at you.

They hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying,

“Is this the city that men called ‘The perfection of beauty,

the joy of the whole earth’?”

16 All your enemies have opened their mouth wide against you.

They hiss and gnash the teeth.

They say, “We have swallowed her up.

Certainly this is the day that we looked for.

We have found it.

We have seen it.”

17 Yahweh has done that which he purposed;

he has fulfilled his word that he commanded in the days of old;

He has thrown down,

and has not pitied:

He has caused the enemy to rejoice over you;

he has exalted the horn of your adversaries.

18 Their heart cried to the Lord:

wall of the daughter of Zion,

let tears run down like a river day and night;

Give yourself no respite;

don’t let the apple of your eye cease.

19 Arise, cry out in the night,

at the beginning of the watches;

Pour out your heart like water before the face of the Lord:

Lift up your hands toward him for the life of your young children,

that faint for hunger at the head of every street.

20 “Look, Yahweh, and see to whom you have done thus!

Shall the women eat their offspring,

the children that are dandled in the hands?

Shall the priest and the prophet be killed in the sanctuary of the Lord?

21 “The youth and the old man lie on the ground in the streets.

My virgins and my young men have fallen by the sword.

You have killed them in the day of your anger.

You have slaughtered, and not pitied.

22 “You have called, as in the day of a solemn assembly, my terrors on every side.

There was no one that escaped or remained in the day of Yahweh’s anger.

My enemy has consumed those whom I have dandled and brought up.

Lamentations 3

1 I am the man that has seen affliction

by the rod of his wrath.

2 He has led me and caused me to walk in darkness,

and not in light.

3 Surely against me he turns his hand

again and again all day long.

4 He has made my flesh and my skin old;

he has broken my bones.

5 He has built against me,

and surrounded me with gall and travail.

6 He has made me to dwell in dark places,

as those that have been long dead.

7 He has walled me about, that I can’t go out;

he has made my chain heavy.

8 Yes, when I cry, and call for help,

he shuts out my prayer.

9 He has walled up my ways with cut stone;

he has made my paths crooked.

10 He is to me as a bear lying in wait,

as a lion in secret places.

11 He has turned aside my ways,

and pulled me in pieces;

he has made me desolate.

12 He has bent his bow,

and set me as a mark for the arrow.

13 He has caused the shafts of his quiver to enter into my kidneys.

14 I have become a derision to all my people,

and their song all day long.

15 He has filled me with bitterness.

He has sated me with wormwood.

16 He has also broken my teeth with gravel stones;

he has covered me with ashes.

17 You have removed my soul far off from peace;

I forgot prosperity.

18 I said, “My strength has perished,

along with my expectation from Yahweh.”

19 Remember my affliction and my misery,

the wormwood and the gall.

20 My soul still remembers them,

and is bowed down within me.

21 This I recall to my mind;

therefore I have hope.

22 It is because of Yahweh’s loving kindnesses that we are not consumed,

because his compassion doesn’t fail.

23 They are new every morning;

great is your faithfulness.

24 “Yahweh is my portion,” says my soul.

“Therefore I will hope in him.”

25 Yahweh is good to those who wait for him,

to the soul who seeks him.

26 It is good that a man should hope

and quietly wait for the salvation of Yahweh.

27 It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth.

28 Let him sit alone and keep silence,

because he has laid it on him.

29 Let him put his mouth in the dust,

if so be there may be hope.

30 Let him give his cheek to him who strikes him;

let him be filled full with reproach.

31 For the Lord will not cast off forever.

32 For though he cause grief,

yet he will have compassion according to the multitude of his loving kindnesses.

33 For he does not afflict willingly,

nor grieve the children of men.

34 To crush under foot all the prisoners of the earth,

35 To turn aside the right of a man before the face of the Most High,

36 To subvert a man in his cause, the Lord doesn’t approve.

37 Who is he who says, and it comes to pass,

when the Lord doesn’t command it?

38 Doesn’t evil and good come out of the mouth of the Most High?

39 Why does a living man complain,

a man for the punishment of his sins?

40 Let us search and try our ways,

and turn again to Yahweh.

41 Let us lift up our heart with our hands to God[*] in the heavens.

42 “We have transgressed and have rebelled.

You have not pardoned.

43 “You have covered us with anger and pursued us.

You have killed.

You have not pitied.

44 You have covered yourself with a cloud,

so that no prayer can pass through.

45 You have made us an off-scouring and refuse

in the middle of the peoples.

46 “All our enemies have opened their mouth wide against us.

47 Terror and the pit have come on us,

devastation and destruction.”

48 My eye runs down with streams of water,

for the destruction of the daughter of my people.

49 My eye pours down,

and doesn’t cease,

without any intermission,

50 until Yahweh looks down,

and sees from heaven.

51 My eye affects my soul,

because of all the daughters of my city.

52 They have chased me relentlessly like a bird,

those who are my enemies without cause.

53 They have cut off my life in the dungeon,

and have cast a stone on me.

54 Waters flowed over my head;

I said, I am cut off.

55 I called on your name, Yahweh,

out of the lowest dungeon.

56 You heard my voice:

“Don’t hide your ear from my sighing,

and my cry.”

57 You came near in the day that I called on you;

you said, “Don’t be afraid.”

58 Lord, you have pleaded the causes of my soul;

you have redeemed my life.

59 Yahweh, you have seen my wrong.

Judge my cause.

60 You have seen all their vengeance

and all their devices against me.

61 You have heard their reproach, Yahweh,

and all their devices against me,

62 The lips of those that rose up against me,

and their device against me all day long.

63 You see their sitting down and their rising up;

I am their song.

64 You will render to them a recompense, Yahweh,

according to the work of their hands.

65 You will give them hardness of heart,

your curse to them.

66 You will pursue them in anger,

and destroy them from under the heavens of Yahweh.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Lamentations 4

1 How the gold has become dim!

The most pure gold has changed!

The stones of the sanctuary are poured out

at the head of every street.

2 The precious sons of Zion,

comparable to fine gold,

How are they esteemed as earthen pitchers,

the work of the hands of the potter!

3 Even the jackals draw out the breast,

they nurse their young ones:

But the daughter of my people has become cruel,

like the ostriches in the wilderness.

4 The tongue of the nursing child clings to the roof of his mouth for thirst:

The young children ask bread,

and no man breaks it to them.

5 Those who fed delicately are desolate in the streets:

Those who were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills.

6 For the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the sin of Sodom,

That was overthrown as in a moment,

and no hands were laid on her.

7 Her nobles were purer than snow,

they were whiter than milk;

They were more ruddy in body than rubies,

their polishing was as of sapphire.

8 Their appearance is blacker than a coal;

they are not known in the streets:

Their skin clings to their bones;

it is withered,

it has become like a stick.

9 Those who are killed with the sword are better than those who are killed with hunger;

For these pine away, stricken through,

for want of the fruits of the field.

10 The hands of the pitiful women have boiled their own children;

They were their food in the destruction of the daughter of my people.

11 Yahweh has accomplished his wrath,

he has poured out his fierce anger;

He has kindled a fire in Zion,

which has devoured its foundations.

12 The kings of the earth didn’t believe,

neither did all the inhabitants of the world,

That the adversary and the enemy would enter into the gates of Jerusalem.

13 It is because of the sins of her prophets,

and the iniquities of her priests,

That have shed the blood of the just in the middle of her.

14 They wander as blind men in the streets.

They are polluted with blood,

So that men can’t touch their garments.

15 “Go away!” they cried to them,

“Unclean! Go away! Go away! Don’t touch!

When they fled away and wandered, men said among the nations,

“They can’t live here any more.”

16 Yahweh’s anger has scattered them;

he will no more regard them:

They didn’t respect the persons of the priests,

they didn’t favor the elders.

17 Our eyes still fail,

looking in vain for our help:

In our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save.

18 They hunt our steps,

so that we can’t go in our streets:

Our end is near,

our days are fulfilled;

for our end has come.

19 Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the sky:

They chased us on the mountains,

they laid wait for us in the wilderness.

20 The breath of our nostrils,

the anointed of Yahweh,

was taken in their pits;

Of whom we said,

Under his shadow we shall live among the nations.

21 Rejoice and be glad, daughter of Edom,

that dwell in the land of Uz:

The cup shall pass through to you also;

you shall be drunken,

and shall make yourself naked.

22 The punishment of your iniquity is accomplished, daughter of Zion;

he will no more carry you away into captivity:

He will visit your iniquity, daughter of Edom;

he will uncover your sins.

Lamentations 5

1 Remember, Yahweh, what has come on us:

Look, and see our reproach.

2 Our inheritance is turned to strangers,

Our houses to aliens.

3 We are orphans and fatherless;

Our mothers are as widows.

4 We have drunken our water for money;

Our wood is sold to us.

5 Our pursuers are on our necks:

We are weary, and have no rest.

6 We have given the hand to the Egyptians,

To the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread.

7 Our fathers sinned, and are no more;

We have borne their iniquities.

8 Servants rule over us:

There is no one to deliver us out of their hand.

9 We get our bread at the peril of our lives,

Because of the sword of the wilderness.

10 Our skin is black like an oven,

Because of the burning heat of famine.

11 They ravished the women in Zion,

The virgins in the cities of Judah.

12 Princes were hanged up by their hand:

The faces of elders were not honored.

13 The young men bare the mill;

The children stumbled under the wood.

14 The elders have ceased from the gate,

The young men from their music.

15 The joy of our heart is ceased;

Our dance is turned into mourning.

16 The crown is fallen from our head:

Woe to us! for we have sinned.

17 For this our heart is faint;

For these things our eyes are dim;

18 For the mountain of Zion, which is desolate:

The foxes walk on it.

19 You, Yahweh, remain forever;

Your throne is from generation to generation.

20 Why do you forget us forever,

And forsake us so long time?

21 Turn us to yourself, Yahweh, and we shall be turned.

Renew our days as of old.

22 But you have utterly rejected us;

You are very angry against us.

Ezekiel 1

1 Now in the thirtieth year, in the fourth month, in the fifth of the month, as I was among the captives by the river Chebar, the heavens were opened, and I saw visions of God.[*]

2 In the fifth of the month, which was the fifth year of king Jehoiachin’s captivity, 3 Yahweh’s[*] word came expressly to Ezekiel the priest, the son of Buzi, in the land of the Chaldeans by the river Chebar; and Yahweh’s hand was there on him.

4 I looked, and behold,[*] a stormy wind came out of the north, a great cloud, with flashing lightning, and a brightness around it, and out of the middle of it as it were glowing metal, out of the middle of the fire. 5 Out of its center came the likeness of four living creatures. This was their appearance: they had the likeness of a man. 6 Everyone had four faces, and each one of them had four wings. 7 Their feet were straight feet; and the sole of their feet was like the sole of a calf’s foot; and they sparkled like burnished brass. 8 They had the hands of a man under their wings on their four sides; and the four of them had their faces and their wings thus: 9 their wings were joined to one another; they didn’t turn when they went; each one went straight forward.

10 As for the likeness of their faces, they had the face of a man; and the four of them had the face of a lion on the right side; and the four of them had the face of an ox on the left side; the four of them also had the face of an eagle. 11 Such were their faces. Their wings were spread out above. Two wings of each one touched another, and two covered their bodies. 12 Each one went straight forward: where the spirit was to go, they went; they didn’t turn when they went. 13 As for the likeness of the living creatures, their appearance was like burning coals of fire, like the appearance of torches: the fire went up and down among the living creatures; and the fire was bright, and lightning went out of the fire. 14 The living creatures ran and returned as the appearance of a flash of lightning.

15 Now as I saw the living creatures, behold, one wheel on the earth beside the living creatures, for each of the four faces of it. 16 The appearance of the wheels and their work was like a beryl: and the four of them had one likeness; and their appearance and their work was as it were a wheel within a wheel. 17 When they went, they went in their four directions: they didn’t turn when they went. 18 As for their rims, they were high and dreadful; and the four of them had their rims full of eyes all around.

19 When the living creatures went, the wheels went beside them; and when the living creatures were lifted up from the earth, the wheels were lifted up. 20 Wherever the spirit was to go, they went; there was the spirit to go: and the wheels were lifted up beside them; for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels. 21 When those went, these went; and when those stood, these stood; and when those were lifted up from the earth, the wheels were lifted up beside them: for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels.

22 Over the head of the living creature there was the likeness of an expanse, like the awesome crystal to look on, stretched out over their heads above. 23 Under the expanse were their wings straight, the one toward the other: each one had two which covered on this side, and every one had two which covered on that side, their bodies. 24 When they went, I heard the noise of their wings like the noise of great waters, like the voice of the Almighty, a noise of tumult like the noise of an army: when they stood, they let down their wings.

25 There was a voice above the expanse that was over their heads: when they stood, they let down their wings. 26 Above the expanse that was over their heads was the likeness of a throne, as the appearance of a sapphire[*] stone; and on the likeness of the throne was a likeness as the appearance of a man on it above. 27 I saw as it were glowing metal, as the appearance of fire within it all around, from the appearance of his waist and upward; and from the appearance of his waist and downward I saw as it were the appearance of fire, and there was brightness around him. 28 As the appearance of the rainbow that is in the cloud in the day of rain, so was the appearance of the brightness all around.

This was the appearance of the likeness of Yahweh’s glory. When I saw it, I fell on my face, and I heard a voice of one that spoke.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

or, lapis lazuli

Ezekiel 2

1 He said to me, “Son of man, stand on your feet, and I will speak with you.” 2 The Spirit entered into me when he spoke to me, and set me on my feet; and I heard him who spoke to me.

3 He said to me, “Son of man, I send you to the children of Israel, to a nation of rebels who have rebelled against me. They and their fathers have transgressed against me even to this very day. 4 The children are impudent and stiff-hearted. I am sending you to them, and you shall tell them, ‘Thus says the Lord[*] Yahweh.’ 5 They, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear, (for they are a rebellious house), yet shall know that there has been a prophet among them. 6 You, son of man, don’t be afraid of them, neither be afraid of their words, though briers and thorns are with you, and you do dwell among scorpions. Don’t be afraid of their words, nor be dismayed at their looks, though they are a rebellious house. 7 You shall speak my words to them, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear; for they are most rebellious. 8 But you, son of man, hear what I tell you. Don’t be rebellious like that rebellious house. Open your mouth, and eat that which I give you.”

9 When I looked, behold, a hand was stretched out to me; and, behold, a scroll of a book was therein; 10 He spread it before me: and it was written within and without; and there were written therein lamentations, and mourning, and woe.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Ezekiel 4

1 “You also, son of man, take a tile, and lay it before yourself, and portray on it a city, even Jerusalem. 2 Lay siege against it, build forts against it, and cast up a mound against it. Also set camps against it and plant battering rams against it all around. 3 Take for yourself an iron pan, and set it for a wall of iron between you and the city: and set your face toward it. It shall be besieged, and you shall lay siege against it. This shall be a sign to the house of Israel.

4 “Moreover lie on your left side, and lay the iniquity of the house of Israel on it. According to the number of the days that you shall lie on it, you shall bear their iniquity. 5 For I have appointed the years of their iniquity to be to you a number of days, even three hundred ninety days: so you shall bear the iniquity of the house of Israel.

6 “Again, when you have accomplished these, you shall lie on your right side, and shall bear the iniquity of the house of Judah. I have appointed forty days, each day for a year, to you. 7 You shall set your face toward the siege of Jerusalem, with your arm uncovered; and you shall prophesy against it. 8 Behold, I put ropes on you, and you shall not turn yourself from one side to the other, until you have accomplished the days of your siege.

9 “Take for yourself also wheat, barley, beans, lentils, millet, and spelt, and put them in one vessel. Make bread of it. According to the number of the days that you shall lie on your side, even three hundred ninety days, you shall eat of it. 10 Your food which you shall eat shall be by weight, twenty shekels[*] a day. From time to time you shall eat it. 11 You shall drink water by measure, the sixth part of a hin. From time to time you shall drink. 12 You shall eat it as barley cakes, and you shall bake it in their sight with dung that comes out of man.” 13 Yahweh said, “Even thus shall the children of Israel eat their bread unclean, among the nations where I will drive them.”

14 Then I said, “Ah Lord Yahweh! Behold, my soul has not been polluted; for from my youth up even until now I have not eaten of that which dies of itself, or is torn of animals; neither came there abominable meat into my mouth!”

15 Then he said to me, “Behold, I have given you cow’s dung for man’s dung, and you shall prepare your bread on it.”

16 Moreover he said to me, “Son of man, behold, I will break the staff of bread in Jerusalem. They will eat bread by weight, and with fearfulness; and they shall drink water by measure, and in dismay; 17 that they may lack bread and water, be dismayed one with another, and pine away in their iniquity.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

Ezekiel 5

1 “You, son of man, take a sharp sword. You shall take it as a barber’s razor to yourself, and shall cause it to pass over your head and over your beard. Then take balances to weigh and divide the hair. 2 A third part you shall burn in the fire in the middle of the city, when the days of the siege are fulfilled. You shall take a third part, and strike with the sword around it. A third part you shall scatter to the wind, and I will draw out a sword after them. 3 You shall take of it a few in number, and bind them in your skirts. 4 Of these again you shall take, and cast them into the middle of the fire, and burn them in the fire; from it shall a fire come out into all the house of Israel.

5 “Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘This is Jerusalem. I have set her in the middle of the nations, and countries are around her. 6 She has rebelled against my ordinances in doing wickedness more than the nations, and against my statutes more than the countries that are around her; for they have rejected my ordinances, and as for my statutes, they have not walked in them.’

7 “Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because you are turbulent more than the nations that are around you, and have not walked in my statutes, neither have kept my ordinances, neither have done after the ordinances of the nations that are around you; 8 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Behold, I, even I, am against you; and I will execute judgments among you in the sight of the nations. 9 I will do in you that which I have not done, and which I will not do any more the like, because of all your abominations. 10 Therefore the fathers will eat the sons within you, and the sons will eat their fathers. I will execute judgments on you; and I will scatter the whole remnant of you to all the winds. 11 Therefore as I live,’ says the Lord Yahweh, ‘surely, because you have defiled my sanctuary with all your detestable things, and with all your abominations, therefore I will also diminish you. My eye won’t spare, and I will have no pity. 12 A third part of you will die with the pestilence, and with famine shall they be consumed within you. A third part will fall by the sword around you. A third part I will scatter to all the winds, and will draw out a sword after them.

13 “‘Thus my anger will be accomplished, and I will cause my wrath toward them to rest, and I will be comforted. They will know that I, Yahweh, have spoken in my zeal, when I have accomplished my wrath on them.

14 “‘Moreover I will make you a desolation and a reproach among the nations that are around you, in the sight of all that pass by. 15 So it shall be a reproach and a taunt, an instruction and an astonishment, to the nations that are around you, when I shall execute judgments on you in anger and in wrath, and in wrathful rebukes—I, Yahweh, have spoken it— 16 when I send on them the evil arrows of famine that are for destruction, which I will send to destroy you. I will increase the famine on you, and will break your staff of bread. 17 I will send on you famine and evil animals, and they will bereave you. Pestilence and blood will pass through you; and I will bring the sword on you. I, Yahweh, have spoken it.’”

Ezekiel 6

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, set your face toward the mountains of Israel, and prophesy to them, 3 and say, ‘You mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Yahweh! Thus says the Lord Yahweh to the mountains and to the hills, to the watercourses and to the valleys: “Behold, I, even I, will bring a sword on you, and I will destroy your high places. 4 Your altars will become desolate, and your incense altars will be broken. I will cast down your slain men before your idols. 5 I will lay the dead bodies of the children of Israel before their idols; and I will scatter your bones around your altars. 6 In all your dwelling places the cities shall be laid waste, and the high places shall be desolate; that your altars may be laid waste and made desolate, and your idols may be broken and cease, and your incense altars may be cut down, and your works may be abolished. 7 The slain shall fall among you, and you shall know that I am Yahweh.

8 “‘“Yet I will leave a remnant, in that you will have some that escape the sword among the nations, when you are scattered through the countries. 9 Those of you that escape will remember me among the nations where they are carried captive, how I have been broken with their lewd heart, which has departed from me, and with their eyes, which play the prostitute after their idols. Then they will loathe themselves in their own sight for the evils which they have committed in all their abominations. 10 They will know that I am Yahweh. I have not said in vain that I would do this evil to them.”’

11 “Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Strike with your hand, and stamp with your foot, and say, “Alas!” Because of all the evil abominations of the house of Israel; for they shall fall by the sword, by the famine, and by the pestilence. 12 He who is far off will die of the pestilence. He who is near will fall by the sword. He who remains and is besieged will die by the famine. Thus I will accomplish my wrath on them. 13 You will know that I am Yahweh, when their slain men are among their idols around their altars, on every high hill, on all the tops of the mountains, under every green tree, and under every thick oak, the places where they offered pleasant aroma to all their idols. 14 I will stretch out my hand on them, and make the land desolate and waste, from the wilderness toward Diblah, throughout all their habitations: and they will know that I am Yahweh. ’”

Ezekiel 7

1 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “You, son of man, thus says the Lord Yahweh to the land of Israel, ‘An end! The end has come on the four corners of the land. 3 Now is the end on you, and I will send my anger on you, and will judge you according to your ways. I will bring on you all your abominations. 4 My eye will not spare you, neither will I have pity; but I will bring your ways on you, and your abominations will be among you. Then you will know that I am Yahweh.’

5 “Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘An evil! A unique evil! Behold, it comes. 6 An end has come. The end has come! It awakes against you. Behold, it comes. 7 Your doom has come to you, inhabitant of the land! The time has come! The day is near, a day of tumult, and not of joyful shouting, on the mountains. 8 Now I will shortly pour out my wrath on you, and accomplish my anger against you, and will judge you according to your ways. I will bring on you all your abominations. 9 My eye won’t spare, neither will I have pity. I will bring on you according to your ways. Your abominations will be among you; and you will know that I, Yahweh, strike.

10 “‘Behold, the day! Behold, it comes! Your doom has gone out. The rod has blossomed. Pride has budded. 11 Violence has risen up into a rod of wickedness. None of them will remain, nor of their multitude, nor of their wealth. There shall be nothing of value among them. 12 The time has come! The day draws near. Don’t let the buyer rejoice, nor the seller mourn; for wrath is on all its multitude. 13 For the seller won’t return to that which is sold, although they are still alive; for the vision concerns the whole multitude of it. None shall return; neither will any strengthen himself in the iniquity of his life. 14 They have blown the trumpet, and have made all ready; but no one goes to the battle; for my wrath is on all its multitude.

15 “‘The sword is outside, and the pestilence and the famine within. He who is in the field will die by the sword. He who is in the city will be devoured by famine and pestilence. 16 But those of those who escape will escape, and will be on the mountains like doves of the valleys, all of them moaning, everyone in his iniquity. 17 All hands will be feeble, and all knees will be weak as water. 18 They will also clothe themselves with sackcloth, and horror will cover them. Shame will be on all faces, and baldness on all their heads. 19 They will cast their silver in the streets, and their gold will be as an unclean thing. Their silver and their gold shall not be able to deliver them in the day of Yahweh’s wrath. They won’t satisfy their souls, neither fill their bellies; because it has been the stumbling block of their iniquity. 20 As for the beauty of his ornament, he set it in majesty; but they made the images of their abominations and their detestable things therein. Therefore I have made it to them as an unclean thing. 21 I will give it into the hands of the strangers for a prey, and to the wicked of the earth for a plunder; and they will profane it. 22 I will also turn my face from them, and they will profane my secret place. Robbers will enter into it, and profane it.

23 “‘Make chains; for the land is full of bloody crimes, and the city is full of violence. 24 Therefore I will bring the worst of the nations, and they will possess their houses. I will also make the pride of the strong to cease. Their holy places will be profaned. 25 Destruction comes! They will seek peace, and there will be none. 26 Mischief will come on mischief, and rumor will be on rumor. They will seek a vision of the prophet; but the law will perish from the priest, and counsel from the elders. 27 The king will mourn, and the prince will be clothed with desolation. The hands of the people of the land will be troubled. I will do to them after their way, and according to their own judgments will I judge them; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.’”

Ezekiel 8

1 In the sixth year, in the sixth month, in the fifth day of the month, as I sat in my house, and the elders of Judah sat before me, the Lord Yahweh’s hand fell there on me. 2 Then I saw, and behold, a likeness as the appearance of fire; from the appearance of his waist and downward, fire; and from his waist and upward, as the appearance of brightness, as it were glowing metal. 3 He stretched out the form of a hand, and took me by a lock of my head; and the Spirit lifted me up between earth and the sky, and brought me in the visions of God to Jerusalem, to the door of the gate of the inner court that looks toward the north; where there was the seat of the image of jealousy, which provokes to jealousy. 4 Behold, the glory of the God of Israel was there, according to the appearance that I saw in the plain.

5 Then he said to me, “Son of man, lift up your eyes now the way toward the north.”

So I lifted up my eyes the way toward the north, and saw, northward of the gate of the altar this image of jealousy in the entry.

6 He said to me, “Son of man, do you see what they do? Even the great abominations that the house of Israel commit here, that I should go far off from my sanctuary? But you will again see yet other great abominations.”

7 He brought me to the door of the court; and when I looked, behold, a hole in the wall. 8 Then he said to me, “Son of man, dig now in the wall.”

When I had dug in the wall, I saw a door.

9 He said to me, “Go in, and see the wicked abominations that they do here.”

10 So I went in and looked, and saw every form of creeping things, abominable animals, and all the idols of the house of Israel, portrayed around on the wall. 11 Seventy men of the elders of the house of Israel stood before them. In the middle of them Jaazaniah the son of Shaphan stood, every man with his censer in his hand; and the smell of the cloud of incense went up.

12 Then he said to me, “Son of man, have you seen what the elders of the house of Israel do in the dark, every man in his rooms of imagery? For they say, ‘Yahweh doesn’t see us. Yahweh has forsaken the land.’” 13 He said also to me, “You will again see more of the great abominations which they do.”

14 Then he brought me to the door of the gate of Yahweh’s house which was toward the north; and I saw the women sit there weeping for Tammuz. 15 Then he said to me, “Have you seen this, son of man? You will again see yet greater abominations than these.”

16 He brought me into the inner court of Yahweh’s house; and I saw at the door of Yahweh’s temple, between the porch and the altar, were about twenty-five men, with their backs toward Yahweh’s temple, and their faces toward the east; and they were worshiping the sun toward the east.

17 Then he said to me, “Have you seen this, son of man? Is it a light thing to the house of Judah that they commit the abominations which they commit here? For they have filled the land with violence, and have turned again to provoke me to anger. Behold, they put the branch to their nose. 18 Therefore will I also deal in wrath. My eye won’t spare, neither will I have pity. Though they cry in my ears with a loud voice, yet I will not hear them.”

Ezekiel 9

1 Then he cried in my ears with a loud voice, saying, “Cause those who are in charge of the city to draw near, each man with his destroying weapon in his hand.” 2 Behold, six men came from the way of the upper gate, which lies toward the north, every man with his slaughter weapon in his hand. One man in the middle of them was clothed in linen, with a writer’s inkhorn by his side. They went in, and stood beside the bronze altar.

3 The glory of the God of Israel went up from the cherub, whereupon it was, to the threshold of the house; and he called to the man clothed in linen, who had the writer’s inkhorn by his side. 4 Yahweh said to him, “Go through the middle of the city, through the middle of Jerusalem, and set a mark on the foreheads of the men that sigh and that cry over all the abominations that are done within it.”

5 To the others he said in my hearing, “Go through the city after him, and strike. Don’t let your eye spare, neither have pity. 6 Kill utterly the old man, the young man, the virgin, little children and women; but don’t come near any man on whom is the mark. Begin at my sanctuary.”

Then they began at the old men who were before the house.

7 He said to them, “Defile the house, and fill the courts with the slain. Go out!”

They went out, and struck in the city. 8 While they were killing, and I was left, I fell on my face, and cried, and said, “Ah Lord Yahweh! Will you destroy all the residue of Israel in your pouring out of your wrath on Jerusalem?”

9 Then he said to me, “The iniquity of the house of Israel and Judah is exceedingly great, and the land is full of blood, and the city full of perversion; for they say, ‘Yahweh has forsaken the land, and Yahweh doesn’t see.’ 10 As for me also, my eye won’t spare, neither will I have pity, but I will bring their way on their head.”

11 Behold, the man clothed in linen, who had the inkhorn by his side, reported the matter, saying, “I have done as you have commanded me.”

Ezekiel 10

1 Then I looked, and see, in the expanse that was over the head of the cherubim there appeared above them as it were a sapphire[*] stone, as the appearance of the likeness of a throne. 2 He spoke to the man clothed in linen, and said, “Go in between the whirling wheels, even under the cherub, and fill both your hands with coals of fire from between the cherubim, and scatter them over the city.”

He went in as I watched. 3 Now the cherubim stood on the right side of the house, when the man went in; and the cloud filled the inner court. 4 Yahweh’s glory mounted up from the cherub, and stood over the threshold of the house; and the house was filled with the cloud, and the court was full of the brightness of Yahweh’s glory. 5 The sound of the wings of the cherubim was heard even to the outer court, as the voice of God Almighty when he speaks.

6 It came to pass, when he commanded the man clothed in linen, saying, “Take fire from between the whirling wheels, from between the cherubim,” that he went in, and stood beside a wheel. 7 The cherub stretched out his hand from between the cherubim to the fire that was between the cherubim, and took some of it, and put it into the hands of him who was clothed in linen, who took it and went out. 8 There appeared in the cherubim the form of a man’s hand under their wings.

9 I looked, and behold, four wheels beside the cherubim, one wheel beside one cherub, and another wheel beside another cherub; and the appearance of the wheels was like a beryl stone. 10 As for their appearance, the four of them had one likeness, like a wheel within a wheel. 11 When they went, they went in their four directions: they didn’t turn as they went, but to the place where the head looked they followed it; they didn’t turn as they went. 12 Their whole body, and their backs, and their hands, and their wings, and the wheels, were full of eyes all around, even the wheels that the four of them had. 13 As for the wheels, they were called in my hearing, “the whirling wheels”. 14 Every one them had four faces. The first face was the face of the cherub. The second face was the face of a man. The third face was the face of a lion. The fourth was the face of an eagle.

15 The cherubim mounted up: this is the living creature that I saw by the river Chebar. 16 When the cherubim went, the wheels went beside them; and when the cherubim lifted up their wings to mount up from the earth, the wheels also didn’t turn from beside them. 17 When they stood, these stood; and when they mounted up, these mounted up with them: for the spirit of the living creature was in them.

18 Yahweh’s glory went out from over the threshold of the house, and stood over the cherubim. 19 The cherubim lifted up their wings, and mounted up from the earth in my sight when they went out, and the wheels beside them: and they stood at the door of the east gate of Yahweh’s house; and the glory of the God of Israel was over them above.

20 This is the living creature that I saw under the God of Israel by the river Chebar; and I knew that they were cherubim. 21 Every one had four faces, and every one four wings; and the likeness of the hands of a man was under their wings. 22 As for the likeness of their faces, they were the faces which I saw by the river Chebar, their appearances and themselves; they went every one straight forward.

or, lapis lazuli

Ezekiel 11

1 Moreover the Spirit lifted me up, and brought me to the east gate of Yahweh’s house, which looks eastward: and see, at the door of the gate twenty-five men; and I saw among them Jaazaniah the son of Azzur, and Pelatiah the son of Benaiah, princes of the people. 2 He said to me, “Son of man, these are the men who devise iniquity, and who give wicked counsel in this city; 3 who say, ‘The time is not near to build houses. This is the cauldron, and we are the meat.’ 4 Therefore prophesy against them, prophesy, son of man.”

5 Yahweh’s Spirit fell on me, and he said to me, “Speak, ‘Yahweh says: “Thus you have said, house of Israel; for I know the things that come into your mind. 6 You have multiplied your slain in this city, and you have filled its streets with the slain.

7 “‘Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Your slain whom you have laid in the middle of it, they are the meat, and this is the cauldron; but you will be brought out of the middle of it. 8 You have feared the sword; and I will bring the sword on you,” says the Lord Yahweh. 9 “I will bring you out of the middle of it, and deliver you into the hands of strangers, and will execute judgments among you. 10 You will fall by the sword. I will judge you in the border of Israel; and you will know that I am Yahweh. 11 This will not be your cauldron, neither will you be the meat in the middle of it. I will judge you in the border of Israel. 12 You will know that I am Yahweh, for you have not walked in my statutes, neither have you executed my ordinances, but have done after the ordinances of the nations that are around you.”’”

13 When I prophesied, Pelatiah the son of Benaiah died. Then fell I down on my face, and cried with a loud voice, and said, “Ah Lord Yahweh! will you make a full end of the remnant of Israel?”

14 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 15 “Son of man, your brothers, even your brothers, the men of your relatives, and all the house of Israel, all of them, to whom the inhabitants of Jerusalem have said, ‘Go far away from Yahweh. This land has been given to us for a possession.’”

16 “Therefore say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Whereas I have removed them far off among the nations, and whereas I have scattered them among the countries, yet I will be to them a sanctuary for a little while in the countries where they have come.”’

17 “Therefore say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “I will gather you from the peoples, and assemble you out of the countries where you have been scattered, and I will give you the land of Israel.”

18 “‘They will come there, and they will take away all its detestable things and all its abominations from there. 19 I will give them one heart, and I will put a new spirit within you. I will take the stony heart out of their flesh, and will give them a heart of flesh; 20 that they may walk in my statutes, and keep my ordinances, and do them. They will be my people, and I will be their God. 21 But as for them whose heart walks after the heart of their detestable things and their abominations, I will bring their way on their own heads,’ says the Lord Yahweh.”

22 Then the cherubim lifted up their wings, and the wheels were beside them; and the glory of the God of Israel was over them above. 23 Yahweh’s glory went up from the middle of the city, and stood on the mountain which is on the east side of the city. 24 The Spirit lifted me up, and brought me in the vision by the Spirit of God into Chaldea, to them of the captivity.

So the vision that I had seen went up from me. 25 Then I spoke to them of the captivity all the things that Yahweh had shown me.

Ezekiel 12

1 Yahweh’s word also came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, you dwell in the middle of the rebellious house, who have eyes to see, and don’t see, who have ears to hear, and don’t hear; for they are a rebellious house.

3 “Therefore, you son of man, prepare your stuff for moving, and move by day in their sight. You shall move from your place to another place in their sight. It may be they will consider, though they are a rebellious house. 4 You shall bring out your stuff by day in their sight, as stuff for moving; and you shall go out yourself at evening in their sight, as when men go out into exile. 5 Dig through the wall in their sight, and carry your stuff out that way. 6 In their sight you shall bear it on your shoulder, and carry it out in the dark. You shall cover your face, so that you don’t see the land, for I have set you for a sign to the house of Israel.”

7 I did so as I was commanded. I brought out my stuff by day, as stuff for moving, and in the evening I dug through the wall with my hand. I brought it out in the dark, and bore it on my shoulder in their sight.

8 In the morning, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 9 “Son of man, hasn’t the house of Israel, the rebellious house, said to you, ‘What are you doing?’

10 “Say to them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “This burden concerns the prince in Jerusalem, and all the house of Israel among whom they are.”’

11 “Say, ‘I am your sign. As I have done, so will it be done to them. They will go into exile, into captivity.

12 “‘The prince who is among them will bear on his shoulder in the dark, and will go out. They will dig through the wall to carry out that way. He will cover his face, because he will not see the land with his eyes. 13 I will also spread my net on him, and he will be taken in my snare. I will bring him to Babylon to the land of the Chaldeans; yet he will not see it, though he will die there. 14 I will scatter toward every wind all who are around him to help him, and all his bands. I will draw out the sword after them.

15 “‘They shall know that I am Yahweh, when I shall disperse them among the nations, and scatter them through the countries. 16 But I will leave a few men of them from the sword, from the famine, and from the pestilence, that they may declare all their abominations among the nations where they come; and they will know that I am Yahweh.’”

17 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 18 “Son of man, eat your bread with quaking, and drink your water with trembling and with fearfulness. 19 Tell the people of the land, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh concerning the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and the land of Israel: “They will eat their bread with fearfulness, and drink their water in dismay, that her land may be desolate, and all that is therein, because of the violence of all those who dwell therein. 20 The cities that are inhabited will be laid waste, and the land will be a desolation; then you will know that I am Yahweh.”’”

21 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 22 “Son of man, what is this proverb that you have in the land of Israel, saying, ‘The days are prolonged, and every vision fails?’ 23 Tell them therefore, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “I will make this proverb to cease, and they shall no more use it as a proverb in Israel;”’ but tell them, ‘“The days are at hand, and the fulfillment of every vision. 24 For there will be no more any false vision nor flattering divination within the house of Israel. 25 For I am Yahweh. I will speak, and the word that I speak will be performed. It will be no more deferred; for in your days, rebellious house, I will speak the word, and will perform it,” says the Lord Yahweh.’”

26 Again Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 27 “Son of man, behold, they of the house of Israel say, ‘The vision that he sees is for many day to come, and he prophesies of times that are far off.’

28 “Therefore tell them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “None of my words shall be deferred any more, but the word which I speak will be performed,” says the Lord Yahweh.’”

Ezekiel 13

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, prophesy against the prophets of Israel who prophesy, and say to those who prophesy out of their own heart, ‘Hear Yahweh’s word: 3 Thus says the Lord Yahweh, “Woe to the foolish prophets, who follow their own spirit, and have seen nothing! 4 Israel, your prophets have been like foxes in the waste places. 5 You have not gone up into the gaps, neither built up the wall for the house of Israel, to stand in the battle in the day of Yahweh. 6 They have seen falsehood and lying divination, who say, ‘Yahweh says;’ but Yahweh has not sent them. They have made men to hope that the word would be confirmed. 7 Haven’t you seen a false vision, and haven’t you spoken a lying divination, in that you say, ‘Yahweh says;’ but I have not spoken?”

8 “‘Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Because you have spoken falsehood and seen lies, therefore, behold, I am against you,” says the Lord Yahweh. 9 “My hand will be against the prophets who see false visions and who divine lies. They will not be in the council of my people, neither will they be written in the writing of the house of Israel, neither will they enter into the land of Israel. Then you will know that I am the Lord Yahweh”

10 “‘Because, even because they have seduced my people, saying, “Peace;” and there is no peace. When one builds up a wall, behold, they plaster it with whitewash. 11 Tell those who plaster it with whitewash that it will fall. There will be an overflowing shower; and you, great hailstones, will fall. A stormy wind will tear it. 12 Behold, when the wall has fallen, won’t it be said to you, “Where is the plaster with which you have plastered it?”

13 “‘Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “I will even tear it with a stormy wind in my wrath. There shall be an overflowing shower in my anger, and great hailstones in wrath to consume it. 14 So will I break down the wall that you have plastered with whitewash, and bring it down to the ground, so that its foundation will be uncovered. It will fall, and you will be consumed in the middle of it. Then you will know that I am Yahweh. 15 Thus will I accomplish my wrath on the wall, and on those who have plastered it with whitewash; and I will tell you, ‘The wall is no more, neither those who plastered it; 16 to wit, the prophets of Israel who prophesy concerning Jerusalem, and who see visions of peace for her, and there is no peace,’” says the Lord Yahweh.’”

17 You, son of man, set your face against the daughters of your people, who prophesy out of their own heart; and prophesy against them, 18 and say, “Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Woe to the women who sew pillows on all elbows, and make kerchiefs for the head of persons of every stature to hunt souls! Will you hunt the souls of my people, and save souls alive for yourselves? 19 You have profaned me among my people for handfuls of barley and for pieces of bread, to kill the souls who should not die, and to save the souls alive who should not live, by your lying to my people who listen to lies.’

20 “Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Behold, I am against your pillows, with which you hunt the souls to make them fly, and I will tear them from your arms. I will let the souls go, even the souls whom you hunt to make them fly. 21 I will also tear your kerchiefs, and deliver my people out of your hand, and they will be no more in your hand to be hunted. Then you will know that I am Yahweh. 22 Because with lies you have grieved the heart of the righteous, whom I have not made sad; and strengthened the hands of the wicked, that he should not return from his wicked way, and be saved alive. 23 Therefore you shall no more see false visions, nor practice divination. I will deliver my people out of your hand. Then you will know that I am Yahweh.’”

Ezekiel 14

1 Then came certain of the elders of Israel to me, and sat before me. 2 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 3 “Son of man, these men have taken their idols into their heart, and put the stumbling block of their iniquity before their face. Should I be inquired of at all by them? 4 Therefore speak to them, and tell them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Every man of the house of Israel who takes his idols into his heart, and puts the stumbling block of his iniquity before his face, and comes to the prophet; I Yahweh will answer him therein according to the multitude of his idols; 5 that I may take the house of Israel in their own heart, because they are all estranged from me through their idols.”’

6 “Therefore tell the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Return, and turn yourselves from your idols! Turn away your faces from all your abominations.

7 “‘“For everyone of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who live in Israel, who separates himself from me, and takes his idols into his heart, and puts the stumbling block of his iniquity before his face, and comes to the prophet to inquire for himself of me; I Yahweh will answer him by myself. 8 I will set my face against that man, and will make him an astonishment, for a sign and a proverb, and I will cut him off from among my people; and you will know that I am Yahweh.

9 “‘“If the prophet is deceived and speaks a word, I, Yahweh, have deceived that prophet, and I will stretch out my hand on him, and will destroy him from among my people Israel. 10 They will bear their iniquity. The iniquity of the prophet will be even as the iniquity of him who seeks him; 11 that the house of Israel may go no more astray from me, neither defile themselves any more with all their transgressions; but that they may be my people, and I may be their God,” says the Lord Yahweh.’”

12 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 13 “Son of man, when a land sins against me by committing a trespass, and I stretch out my hand on it, and break the staff of its bread, and send famine on it, and cut off from it man and animal; 14 though these three men, Noah, Daniel, and Job, were in it, they should deliver only their own souls by their righteousness,” says the Lord Yahweh.

15 “If I cause evil animals to pass through the land, and they ravage it, and it is made desolate, so that no man may pass through because of the animals; 16 though these three men were in it, as I live,” says the Lord Yahweh, “they would deliver neither sons nor daughters. They only would be delivered, but the land would be desolate.

17 “Or if I bring a sword on that land, and say, ‘Sword, go through the land; so that I cut off from it man and animal;’ 18 though these three men were in it, as I live,” says the Lord Yahweh, “they would deliver neither sons nor daughters, but they only would be delivered themselves.

19 “Or if I send a pestilence into that land, and pour out my wrath on it in blood, to cut off from it man and animal; 20 though Noah, Daniel, and Job, were in it, as I live,” says the Lord Yahweh, “they would deliver neither son nor daughter; they would deliver only their own souls by their righteousness.”

21 For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “How much more when I send my four severe judgments on Jerusalem, the sword, and the famine, and the evil animals, and the pestilence, to cut off from it man and animal! 22 Yet, behold, therein shall be left a remnant that shall be carried out, both sons and daughters. Behold, they shall come out to you, and you shall see their way and their doings; and you shall be comforted concerning the evil that I have brought on Jerusalem, even concerning all that I have brought on it. 23 They will comfort you, when you see their way and their doings; and you will know that I have not done without cause all that I have done in it,” says the Lord Yahweh.

Ezekiel 16

1 Again Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, cause Jerusalem to know her abominations; 3 and say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh to Jerusalem: “Your origin and your birth is of the land of the Canaanite. An Amorite was your father, and your mother was a Hittite. 4 As for your birth, in the day you were born your navel was not cut, neither were you washed in water to cleanse you. You weren’t salted at all, nor swaddled at all. 5 No eye pitied you, to do any of these things to you, to have compassion on you; but you were cast out in the open field, because you were abhorred in the day that you were born.

6 “‘“When I passed by you, and saw you wallowing in your blood, I said to you, ‘Though you are in your blood, live!’ Yes, I said to you, ‘Though you are in your blood, live!’ 7 I caused you to multiply as that which grows in the field, and you increased and grew great, and you attained to excellent ornament. Your breasts were formed, and your hair grew; yet you were naked and bare.

8 “‘“Now when I passed by you, and looked at you, behold, your time was the time of love; and I spread my skirt over you, and covered your nakedness: yes, I swore to you, and entered into a covenant with you,” says the Lord Yahweh, “and you became mine.

9 “‘“Then washed I you with water. Yes, I thoroughly washed away your blood from you, and I anointed you with oil. 10 I clothed you also with embroidered work, and put sealskin shoes on you. I dressed you with fine linen and covered you with silk. 11 I decked you with ornaments. put bracelets on your hands, and a chain on your neck. 12 I put a ring on your nose, and earrings in your ears, and a beautiful crown on your head. 13 Thus you were decked with gold and silver. Your clothing was of fine linen, silk, and embroidered work. You ate fine flour, honey, and oil. You were exceedingly beautiful, and you prospered to royal estate. 14 Your renown went out among the nations for your beauty; for it was perfect, through my majesty which I had put on you,” says the Lord Yahweh.

15 “‘“But you trusted in your beauty, and played the prostitute because of your renown, and poured out your prostitution on everyone who passed by. It was his. 16 You took some of your garments, and made for yourselves high places decked with various colors, and played the prostitute on them. This shall not come, neither shall it be. 17 You also took your beautiful jewels of my gold and of my silver, which I had given you, and made for yourself images of men, and played the prostitute with them. 18 You took your embroidered garments, covered them, and set my oil and my incense before them. 19 My bread also which I gave you, fine flour, oil, and honey, with which I fed you, you even set it before them for a pleasant aroma; and so it was,” says the Lord Yahweh.

20 “‘“Moreover you have taken your sons and your daughters, whom you have borne to me, and you have sacrificed these to them to be devoured. Was your prostitution a small matter, 21 that you have slain my children, and delivered them up, in causing them to pass through the fire to them? 22 In all your abominations and your prostitution you have not remembered the days of your youth, when you were naked and bare, and were wallowing in your blood.

23 “‘“It has happened after all your wickedness. Woe, woe to you!” says the Lord Yahweh, 24 “that you have built for yourselves a vaulted place, and have made yourselves a lofty place in every street. 25 You have built your lofty place at the head of every way, and have made your beauty an abomination, and have opened your feet to everyone who passed by, and multiplied your prostitution. 26 You have also committed sexual immorality with the Egyptians, your neighbors, great of flesh; and have multiplied your prostitution, to provoke me to anger. 27 See therefore, I have stretched out my hand over you, and have diminished your portion, and delivered you to the will of those who hate you, the daughters of the Philistines, who are ashamed of your lewd way. 28 You have played the prostitute also with the Assyrians, because you were insatiable; yes, you have played the prostitute with them, and yet you weren’t satisfied. 29 You have moreover multiplied your prostitution to the land of merchants, to Chaldea; and yet you weren’t satisfied with this.

30 “‘“How weak is your heart,” says the Lord Yahweh, “since you do all these things, the work of an impudent prostitute; 31 in that you build your vaulted place at the head of every way, and make your lofty place in every street, and have not been as a prostitute, in that you scorn pay.

32 “‘“A wife who commits adultery! Who takes strangers instead of her husband! 33 People give gifts to all prostitutes; but you give your gifts to all your lovers, and bribe them, that they may come to you on every side for your prostitution. 34 You are different from other women in your prostitution, in that no one follows you to play the prostitute; and whereas you give hire, and no hire is given to you, therefore you are different.”’

35 “Therefore, prostitute, hear Yahweh’s word: 36 ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh, “Because your filthiness was poured out, and your nakedness uncovered through your prostitution with your lovers; and because of all the idols of your abominations, and for the blood of your children, that you gave to them; 37 therefore see, I will gather all your lovers, with whom you have taken pleasure, and all those who you have loved, with all those who you have hated; I will even gather them against you on every side, and will uncover your nakedness to them, that they may see all your nakedness. 38 I will judge you, as women who break wedlock and shed blood are judged; and I will bring on you the blood of wrath and jealousy. 39 I will also give you into their hand, and they will throw down your vaulted place, and break down your lofty places; and they will strip you of your clothes, and take your beautiful jewels. They will leave you naked and bare. 40 They will also bring up a company against you, and they will stone you with stones, and thrust you through with their swords. 41 They will burn your houses with fire, and execute judgments on you in the sight of many women. I will cause you to cease from playing the prostitute, and you will also give no hire any more. 42 So will I cause my wrath toward you to rest, and my jealousy will depart from you. I will be quiet, and will be no more angry.

43 “‘“Because you have not remembered the days of your youth, but have raged against me in all these things; therefore, behold, I also will bring your way on your head,” says the Lord Yahweh: “and you shall not commit this lewdness with all your abominations.

44 “‘“Behold, everyone who uses proverbs shall use this proverb against you, saying, ‘As is the mother, so is her daughter.’ 45 You are the daughter of your mother, who loathes her husband and her children; and you are the sister of your sisters, who loathed their husbands and their children. Your mother was a Hittite, and your father an Amorite. 46 Your elder sister is Samaria, who dwells at your left hand, she and her daughters; and your younger sister, who dwells at your right hand, is Sodom and her daughters. 47 Yet you have not walked in their ways, nor done after their abominations; but, soon you were more corrupt than they in all your ways. 48 As I live,” says the Lord Yahweh, “Sodom your sister has not done, she nor her daughters, as you have done, you and your daughters.

49 “‘“Behold, this was the iniquity of your sister Sodom: pride, fullness of bread, and prosperous ease was in her and in her daughters; neither did she strengthen the hand of the poor and needy. 50 They were haughty, and committed abomination before me. Therefore I took them away when I saw it. 51 Neither has Samaria committed half of your sins; but you have multiplied your abominations more than they, and have justified your sisters by all your abominations which you have done. 52 You also, bear your own shame yourself, in that you have given judgment for your sisters; through your sins that you have committed more abominable than they, they are more righteous that you. Yes, be also confounded, and bear your shame, in that you have justified your sisters.

53 “‘“I will turn again their captivity, the captivity of Sodom and her daughters, and the captivity of Samaria and her daughters, and the captivity of your captives among them; 54 that you may bear your own shame, and may be ashamed because of all that you have done, in that you are a comfort to them. 55 Your sisters, Sodom and her daughters, will return to their former estate; and Samaria and her daughters will return to their former estate; and you and your daughters will return to your former estate. 56 For your sister Sodom was not mentioned by your mouth in the day of your pride, 57 before your wickedness was uncovered, as at the time of the reproach of the daughters of Syria, and of all who are around her, the daughters of the Philistines, who do despite to you all around. 58 You have borne your lewdness and your abominations,” says Yahweh.

59 “‘For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “I will also deal with you as you have done, who have despised the oath in breaking the covenant. 60 Nevertheless I will remember my covenant with you in the days of your youth, and I will establish to you an everlasting covenant. 61 Then you will remember your ways and be ashamed, when you receive your sisters, your elder sisters and your younger; and I will give them to you for daughters, but not by your covenant. 62 I will establish my covenant with you; and you will know that I am Yahweh; 63 that you may remember, and be confounded, and never open your mouth any more, because of your shame, when I have forgiven you all that you have done,” says the Lord Yahweh.’”

Ezekiel 17

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, tell a riddle, and speak a parable to the house of Israel; 3 and say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “A great eagle with great wings and long feathers, full of feathers, which had various colors, came to Lebanon, and took the top of the cedar. 4 He cropped off the topmost of its young twigs, and carried it to a land of traffic. He planted it in a city of merchants.

5 “‘“He also took some of the seed of the land, and planted it in fruitful soil. He placed it beside many waters. He set it as a willow tree. 6 It grew, and became a spreading vine of low stature, whose branches turned toward him, and its roots were under him. So it became a vine, produced branches, and shot out sprigs.

7 “‘“There was also another great eagle with great wings and many feathers. Behold, this vine bent its roots toward him, and shot out its branches toward him, from the beds of its plantation, that he might water it. 8 It was planted in a good soil by many waters, that it might produce branches, and that it might bear fruit, that it might be a good vine.”’

9 “Say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Will it prosper? Won’t he pull up its roots, and cut off its fruit, that it may wither; that all its fresh springing leaves may wither? Not by a strong arm or many people can it be raised from its roots. 10 Yes, behold, being planted, shall it prosper? Won’t it utterly wither when the east wind touches it? It will wither in the beds where it grew.”’”

11 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 12 “Say now to the rebellious house, ‘Don’t you know what these things mean?’ Tell them, ‘Behold, the king of Babylon came to Jerusalem, and took its king, and its princes, and brought them to him to Babylon. 13 He took some of the royal offspring,[*] and made a covenant with him. He also brought him under an oath, and took away the mighty of the land; 14 that the kingdom might be brought low, that it might not lift itself up, but that by keeping his covenant it might stand. 15 But he rebelled against him in sending his ambassadors into Egypt, that they might give him horses and many people. Will he prosper? Will he who does such things escape? Will he break the covenant, and still escape?

16 “‘As I live,’ says the Lord Yahweh, ‘surely in the place where the king dwells who made him king, whose oath he despised, and whose covenant he broke, even with him in the middle of Babylon he will die. 17 Neither shall Pharaoh with his mighty army and great company help him in the war, when they cast up mounds and build forts, to cut off many persons. 18 For he has despised the oath by breaking the covenant; and behold, he had given his hand, and yet has done all these things. He won’t escape.

19 “Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘As I live, surely my oath that he has despised, and my covenant that he has broken, I will even bring it on his own head. 20 I will spread my net on him, and he shall be taken in my snare, and I will bring him to Babylon, and will enter into judgment with him there for his trespass that he has trespassed against me. 21 All his fugitives in all his bands shall fall by the sword, and those who remain shall be scattered toward every wind: and you will know that I, Yahweh, have spoken it.’

22 “Thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘I will also take some of the lofty top of the cedar, and will plant it. I will crop off from the topmost of its young twigs a tender one, and I will plant it on a high and lofty mountain. 23 I will plant it in the mountain of the height of Israel; and it will produce boughs, and bear fruit, and be a good cedar. Birds of every kind will dwell in the shade of its branches. 24 All the trees of the field will know that I, Yahweh, have brought down the high tree, have exalted the low tree, have dried up the green tree, and have made the dry tree to flourish.

I, Yahweh, have spoken and have done it.’”

or, seed

Ezekiel 18

1 Yahweh’s word came to me again, saying, 2 “What do you mean, that you use this proverb concerning the land of Israel, saying,

‘The fathers have eaten sour grapes,

and the children’s teeth are set on edge’?

3 “As I live,” says the Lord Yahweh, “you shall not use this proverb any more in Israel. 4 Behold, all souls are mine; as the soul of the father, so also the soul of the son is mine: the soul who sins, he shall die.

5 “But if a man is just,

and does that which is lawful and right,

6 and has not eaten on the mountains,

neither has lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel,

neither has defiled his neighbor’s wife,

neither has come near to a woman in her impurity,

7 and has not wronged any,

but has restored to the debtor his pledge,

has taken nothing by robbery,

has given his bread to the hungry,

and has covered the naked with a garment;

8 he who has not lent on interest,

neither has taken any increase,

who has withdrawn his hand from iniquity,

has executed true justice between man and man,

9 has walked in my statutes,

and has kept my ordinances,

to deal truly;

he is just,

he shall surely live,” says the Lord Yahweh.

10 “If he fathers a son who is a robber who sheds blood, and who does any one of these things, 11 or who does not do any of those things,

but even has eaten at the mountain shrines,

and defiled his neighbor’s wife,

12 has wronged the poor and needy,

has taken by robbery,

has not restored the pledge,

and has lifted up his eyes to the idols,

has committed abomination,

13 has lent on interest,

and has taken increase;

shall he then live? He shall not live. He has done all these abominations. He shall surely die. His blood shall be on him.

14 “Now, behold, if he fathers a son, who sees all his father’s sins, which he has done, and fears, and does not such like;

15 who has not eaten on the mountains,

neither has lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel,

has not defiled his neighbor’s wife,

16 neither has wronged any,

has not taken anything to pledge,

neither has taken by robbery,

but has given his bread to the hungry,

and has covered the naked with a garment;

17 who has withdrawn his hand from the poor,

who has not received interest nor increase,

has executed my ordinances,

has walked in my statutes;

he shall not die for the iniquity of his father, he shall surely live. 18 As for his father, because he cruelly oppressed, robbed his brother, and did that which is not good among his people, behold, he shall die in his iniquity.

19 “Yet you say, ‘Why doesn’t the son bear the iniquity of the father?’ When the son has done that which is lawful and right, and has kept all my statutes, and has done them, he shall surely live. 20 The soul who sins, he shall die. The son shall not bear the iniquity of the father, neither shall the father bear the iniquity of the son. The righteousness of the righteous shall be on him, and the wickedness of the wicked shall be on him.

21 “But if the wicked turns from all his sins that he has committed, and keeps all my statutes, and does that which is lawful and right, he shall surely live. He shall not die. 22 None of his transgressions that he has committed shall be remembered against him. In his righteousness that he has done, he shall live. 23 Have I any pleasure in the death of the wicked?” says the Lord Yahweh; “and not rather that he should return from his way, and live?

24 “But when the righteous turns away from his righteousness, and commits iniquity, and does according to all the abominations that the wicked man does, shall he live? None of his righteous deeds that he has done shall be remembered. In his trespass that he has trespassed, and in his sin that he has sinned, in them he shall die.

25 “Yet you say, ‘The way of the Lord is not equal.’ Hear now, house of Israel: Is my way not equal? Aren’t your ways unequal? 26 When the righteous man turns away from his righteousness, and commits iniquity, and dies therein; in his iniquity that he has done shall he die. 27 Again, when the wicked man turns away from his wickedness that he has committed, and does that which is lawful and right, he shall save his soul alive. 28 Because he considers, and turns away from all his transgressions that he has committed, he shall surely live. He shall not die. 29 Yet the house of Israel says, ‘The way of the Lord is not fair.’ House of Israel, aren’t my ways fair? Aren’t your ways unfair?

30 “Therefore I will judge you, house of Israel, everyone according to his ways,” says the Lord Yahweh. “Return, and turn yourselves from all your transgressions; so iniquity shall not be your ruin. 31 Cast away from you all your transgressions, in which you have transgressed; and make yourself a new heart and a new spirit: for why will you die, house of Israel? 32 For I have no pleasure in the death of him who dies,” says the Lord Yahweh. “Therefore turn yourselves, and live!

Ezekiel 19

1 “Moreover, take up a lamentation for the princes of Israel, 2 and say,

‘What was your mother?

A lioness.

She couched among lions,

in the middle of the young lions she nourished her cubs.

3 She brought up one of her cubs.

He became a young lion,

and he learned to catch the prey.

He devoured men.

4 The nations also heard of him.

He was taken in their pit;

and they brought him with hooks to the land of Egypt.

5 “‘Now when she saw that she had waited,

and her hope was lost,

then she took another of her cubs,

and made him a young lion.

6 He went up and down among the lions;

he became a young lion,

and he learned to catch the prey.

He devoured men.

7 He knew their palaces,

and laid waste their cities;

and the land was desolate,

with its fullness,

because of the noise of his roaring.

8 Then the nations set against him on every side from the provinces;

and they spread their net over him.

He was taken in their pit.

9 They put him in a cage with hooks,

and brought him to the king of Babylon.

They brought him into strongholds,

that his voice should no more be heard on the mountains of Israel.

10 “‘Your mother was like a vine,

in your blood,

planted by the waters.

It was fruitful and full of branches by reason of many waters.

11 It had strong rods for the scepters of those who bore rule,

and their stature was exalted among the thick boughs,

and they were seen in their height

with the multitude of their branches.

12 But it was plucked up in fury,

it was cast down to the ground,

and the east wind dried up its fruit.

Its strong rods were broken off and withered.

The fire consumed them.

13 Now it is planted in the wilderness,

in a dry and thirsty land.

14 Fire has gone out of the rods of its branches.

It has devoured its fruit,

so that there is in it no strong rod to be a scepter to rule.’

This is a lamentation, and shall be for a lamentation.”

Ezekiel 20

1 In the seventh year, in the fifth month, the tenth day of the month, some of the elders of Israel came to inquire of Yahweh, and sat before me.

2 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 3 “Son of man, speak to the elders of Israel, and tell them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Is it to inquire of me that you have come? As I live,” says the Lord Yahweh, “I will not be inquired of by you.”’

4 “Will you judge them, son of man, will you judge them? Cause them to know the abominations of their fathers; 5 and tell them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “In the day when I chose Israel, and swore to the offspring[*] of the house of Jacob, and made myself known to them in the land of Egypt, when I swore to them, saying, ‘I am Yahweh your God;’ 6 in that day I swore to them, to bring them out of the land of Egypt into a land that I had searched out for them, flowing with milk and honey, which is the glory of all lands. 7 I said to them, ‘Each of you throw away the abominations of his eyes, and don’t defile yourselves with the idols of Egypt. I am Yahweh your God.’

8 “‘“But they rebelled against me, and would not listen to me. They didn’t all throw away the abominations of their eyes, neither did they forsake the idols of Egypt. Then I said I would pour out my wrath on them, to accomplish my anger against them in the middle of the land of Egypt. 9 But I worked for my name’s sake, that it should not be profaned in the sight of the nations, among which they were, in whose sight I made myself known to them, in bringing them out of the land of Egypt. 10 So I caused them to go out of the land of Egypt, and brought them into the wilderness. 11 I gave them my statutes, and showed them my ordinances, which if a man does, he shall live in them. 12 Moreover also I gave them my Sabbaths, to be a sign between me and them, that they might know that I am Yahweh who sanctifies them.

13 “‘“But the house of Israel rebelled against me in the wilderness. They didn’t walk in my statutes, and they rejected my ordinances, which if a man keeps, he shall live in them. They greatly profaned my Sabbaths. Then I said I would pour out my wrath on them in the wilderness, to consume them. 14 But I worked for my name’s sake, that it should not be profaned in the sight of the nations, in whose sight I brought them out. 15 Moreover also I swore to them in the wilderness, that I would not bring them into the land which I had given them, flowing with milk and honey, which is the glory of all lands; 16 because they rejected my ordinances, and didn’t walk in my statutes, and profaned my Sabbaths; for their heart went after their idols. 17 Nevertheless my eye spared them, and I didn’t destroy them, neither did I make a full end of them in the wilderness. 18 I said to their children in the wilderness, ‘Don’t walk in the statutes of your fathers, neither observe their ordinances, nor defile yourselves with their idols. 19 I am Yahweh your God. Walk in my statutes, and keep my ordinances, and do them; 20 and make my Sabbaths holy; and they shall be a sign between me and you, that you may know that I am Yahweh your God. ’

21 “‘“But the children rebelled against me. They didn’t walk in my statutes, neither kept my ordinances to do them, which if a man do, he shall live in them. They profaned my Sabbaths. Then I said I would pour out my wrath on them, to accomplish my anger against them in the wilderness. 22 Nevertheless I withdrew my hand, and worked for my name’s sake, that it should not be profaned in the sight of the nations, in whose sight I brought them out. 23 Moreover I swore to them in the wilderness, that I would scatter them among the nations, and disperse them through the countries; 24 because they had not executed my ordinances, but had rejected my statutes, and had profaned my Sabbaths, and their eyes were after their fathers’ idols. 25 Moreover also I gave them statutes that were not good, and ordinances in which they should not live; 26 and I polluted them in their own gifts, in that they caused all that opens the womb to pass through the fire, that I might make them desolate, to the end that they might know that I am Yahweh.”’

27 “Therefore, son of man, speak to the house of Israel, and tell them, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “In this moreover your fathers have blasphemed me, in that they have committed a trespass against me. 28 For when I had brought them into the land, which I swore to give to them, then they saw every high hill, and every thick tree, and they offered there their sacrifices, and there they presented the provocation of their offering; there also they made their pleasant aroma, and they poured out there their drink offerings. 29 Then I said to them, ‘What does the high place where you go mean?’ So its name is called Bamah[*] to this day. ”’

30 “Therefore tell the house of Israel, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Do you pollute yourselves in the way of your fathers? Do you play the prostitute after their abominations? 31 When you offer your gifts, when you make your sons to pass through the fire, do you pollute yourselves with all your idols to this day? Shall I be inquired of by you, house of Israel? As I live, says the Lord Yahweh, I will not be inquired of by you!

32 “‘“That which comes into your mind shall not be at all, in that you say, ‘We will be as the nations, as the families of the countries, to serve wood and stone.’ 33 As I live, says the Lord Yahweh, surely with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with wrath poured out, I will be king over you. 34 I will bring you out from the peoples, and will gather you out of the countries in which you are scattered, with a mighty hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with wrath poured out. 35 I will bring you into the wilderness of the peoples, and there I will enter into judgment with you face to face. 36 Like as I entered into judgment with your fathers in the wilderness of the land of Egypt, so will I enter into judgment with you,” says the Lord Yahweh. 37 “I will cause you to pass under the rod, and I will bring you into the bond of the covenant. 38 I will purge out from among you the rebels, and those who disobey against me. I will bring them out of the land where they live, but they shall not enter into the land of Israel; and you shall know that I am Yahweh.”

39 “‘As for you, house of Israel, thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Go, everyone serve his idols, and hereafter also, if you will not listen to me; but you shall no more profane my holy name with your gifts, and with your idols. 40 For in my holy mountain, in the mountain of the height of Israel,” says the Lord Yahweh, “there shall all the house of Israel, all of them, serve me in the land. There I will accept them, and there I will require your offerings and the first fruits of your offerings, with all your holy things. 41 As a pleasant aroma I will accept you, when I bring you out from the peoples, and gather you out of the countries in which you have been scattered; and I will be sanctified in you in the sight of the nations. 42 You shall know that I am Yahweh, when I bring you into the land of Israel, into the country which I swore to give to your fathers. 43 There you shall remember your ways, and all your doings, in which you have polluted yourselves; and you shall loathe yourselves in your own sight for all your evils that you have committed. 44 You shall know that I am Yahweh, when I have dealt with you for my name’s sake, not according to your evil ways, nor according to your corrupt doings, you house of Israel,” says the Lord Yahweh.’”

45 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 46 “Son of man, set your face toward the south, and preach toward the south, and prophesy against the forest of the field in the South; 47 and tell the forest of the South, ‘Hear Yahweh’s word: Thus says the Lord Yahweh, “Behold, I will kindle a fire in you, and it shall devour every green tree in you, and every dry tree: the flaming flame shall not be quenched, and all faces from the south to the north shall be burned thereby. 48 All flesh shall see that I, Yahweh, have kindled it; it shall not be quenched.”’”

49 Then I said, “Ah Lord Yahweh! they say of me, ‘Isn’t he a speaker of parables?’”

or, seed

“Bamah” means “High Place”.

Ezekiel 21

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, set your face toward Jerusalem, and preach toward the sanctuaries, and prophesy against the land of Israel. 3 Tell the land of Israel, ‘Yahweh says: “Behold, I am against you, and will draw my sword out of its sheath, and will cut off from you the righteous and the wicked. 4 Seeing then that I will cut off from you the righteous and the wicked, therefore my sword will go out of its sheath against all flesh from the south to the north. 5 All flesh will know that I, Yahweh, have drawn my sword out of its sheath. It will not return any more.”’

6 “Sigh therefore, you son of man. You shall sigh before their eyes with a broken heart[*] and with bitterness. 7 It shall be, when they ask you, ‘Why do you sigh?’ that you shall say, ‘Because of the news, for it comes! Every heart will melt, all hands will be feeble, every spirit will faint, and all knees will be weak as water. Behold, it comes, and it shall be done, says the Lord Yahweh.’”

8 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 9 “Son of man, prophesy, and say, ‘Yahweh says:

“A sword! A sword!

It is sharpened,

and also polished.

10 It is sharpened that it may make a slaughter.

It is polished that it may be as lightning.

Shall we then make mirth?

The rod of my son condemns every tree.

11 It is given to be polished,

that it may be handled.

The sword is sharpened.

Yes, it is polished,

to give it into the hand of the killer.”’

12 Cry and wail, son of man;

for it is on my people.

It is on all the princes of Israel.

They are delivered over to the sword with my people.

Therefore beat your thigh.

13 “For there is a trial. What if even the rod that condemns will be no more?” says the Lord Yahweh.

14 “You therefore, son of man, prophesy,

and strike your hands together.

Let the sword be doubled the third time,

the sword of the fatally wounded.

It is the sword of the great one who is fatally wounded,

which enters into their rooms.

15 I have set the threatening sword against all their gates,

that their heart may melt,

and their stumblings be multiplied.

Ah! It is made as lightning.

It is pointed for slaughter.

16 Gather yourselves together.

Go to the right.

Set yourselves in array.

Go to the left,

wherever your face is set.

17 I will also strike my hands together,

and I will cause my wrath to rest.

I, Yahweh, have spoken it.”

18 Yahweh’s word came to me again, saying, 19 “Also, you son of man, appoint two ways, that the sword of the king of Babylon may come. They both shall come out of one land, and mark out a place; mark it out at the head of the way to the city. 20 You shall appoint a way for the sword to come to Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and to Judah in Jerusalem the fortified. 21 For the king of Babylon stood at the parting of the way, at the head of the two ways, to use divination. He shook the arrows back and forth. He consulted the teraphim.[*] He looked in the liver. 22 In his right hand was the lot for Jerusalem, to set battering rams, to open the mouth in the slaughter, to lift up the voice with shouting, to set battering rams against the gates, to cast up mounds, to build forts. 23 It shall be to them as a false divination in their sight, who have sworn oaths to them; but he brings iniquity to memory, that they may be taken.

24 “Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because you have made your iniquity to be remembered, in that your transgressions are uncovered, so that in all your doings your sins appear; because you have come to memory, you shall be taken with the hand.

25 “‘You, deadly wounded wicked one, the prince of Israel, whose day has come, in the time of the iniquity of the end, 26 thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Remove the turban, and take off the crown. This will not be as it was. Exalt that which is low, and abase that which is high. 27 I will overturn, overturn, overturn it. This also shall be no more, until he comes whose right it is; and I will give it.”’

28 “You, son of man, prophesy, and say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh concerning the children of Ammon, and concerning their reproach:

“A sword! A sword is drawn!

It is polished for the slaughter,

to cause it to devour,

that it may be as lightning;

29 while they see for you false visions,

while they divine lies to you,

to lay you on the necks of the wicked who are deadly wounded,

whose day has come in the time of the iniquity of the end.

30 Cause it to return into its sheath.

In the place where you were created,

in the land of your birth, will I judge you.

31 I will pour out my indignation on you;

I will blow on you with the fire of my wrath;

and I will deliver you into the hand of brutish men,

skillful to destroy.

32 You will be for fuel to the fire.

Your blood will be in the middle of the land.

You shall be remembered no more;

for I, Yahweh, have spoken it.”’”

literally, the breaking of your thighs

teraphim were household idols that may have been associated with inheritance rights to the household property.

Ezekiel 22

1 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “You, son of man, will you judge? Will you judge the bloody city? Then cause her to know all her abominations. 3 You shall say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh: “A city that sheds blood within herself, that her time may come, and that makes idols against herself to defile her! 4 You have become guilty in your blood that you have shed, and are defiled in your idols which you have made! You have caused your days to draw near, and have come even to your years. Therefore I have made you a reproach to the nations, and a mocking to all the countries. 5 Those who are near, and those who are far from you, will mock you, you infamous one, full of tumult.

6 “‘“Behold, the princes of Israel, everyone according to his power, have been in you to shed blood. 7 In you have they treated father and mother with contempt.[*] Among you they have oppressed the foreigner. In you they have wronged the fatherless and the widow. 8 You have despised my holy things, and have profaned my Sabbaths. 9 Slanderous men have been in you to shed blood. In you they have eaten on the mountains. They have committed lewdness among you. 10 In you have they uncovered their fathers’ nakedness. In you have they humbled her who was unclean in her impurity. 11 One has committed abomination with his neighbor’s wife; and another has lewdly defiled his daughter-in-law. Another in you has humbled his sister, his father’s daughter. 12 In you have they taken bribes to shed blood. You have taken interest and increase, and you have greedily gained of your neighbors by oppression, and have forgotten me,” says the Lord Yahweh.

13 “‘“Behold, therefore I have struck my hand at your dishonest gain which you have made, and at your blood which has been within you. 14 Can your heart endure, or can your hands be strong, in the days that I shall deal with you? I, Yahweh, have spoken it, and will do it. 15 I will scatter you among the nations, and disperse you through the countries. I will consume your filthiness out of you. 16 You will be profaned in yourself, in the sight of the nations; and you shall know that I am Yahweh.”’”

17 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 18 “Son of man, the house of Israel has become dross to me. All of them are brass, tin, iron, and lead in the middle of the furnace. They are the dross of silver. 19 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because you have all become dross, therefore, behold, I will gather you into the middle of Jerusalem. 20 As they gather silver, brass, iron, lead, and tin into the middle of the furnace, to blow the fire on it, to melt it; so will I gather you in my anger and in my wrath, and I will lay you there, and melt you. 21 Yes, I will gather you, and blow on you with the fire of my wrath, and you will be melted in the middle of it. 22 As silver is melted in the middle of the furnace, so you will be melted in the middle of it; and you will know that I, Yahweh, have poured out my wrath on you.’”

23 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 24 “Son of man, tell her, ‘You are a land that is not cleansed, nor rained on in the day of indignation.’ 25 There is a conspiracy of her prophets within it, like a roaring lion ravening the prey. They have devoured souls. They take treasure and precious things. They have made her widows many within it. 26 Her priests have done violence to my law, and have profaned my holy things. They have made no distinction between the holy and the common, neither have they caused men to discern between the unclean and the clean, and have hidden their eyes from my Sabbaths, and I am profaned among them. 27 Her princes within it are like wolves ravening the prey, to shed blood, and to destroy souls, that they may get dishonest gain. 28 Her prophets have plastered for them with whitewash, seeing false visions, and divining lies to them, saying, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh,’ when Yahweh has not spoken. 29 The people of the land have used oppression, and exercised robbery. Yes, they have troubled the poor and needy, and have oppressed the foreigner wrongfully.

30 “I sought for a man among them, who should build up the wall, and stand in the gap before me for the land, that I should not destroy it; but I found no one. 31 Therefore I have poured out my indignation on them. I have consumed them with the fire of my wrath. I have brought their own way on their heads,” says the Lord Yahweh.

Literally, made light of father and mother.

Ezekiel 23

1 Yahweh’s word came again to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, there were two women, the daughters of one mother. 3 They played the prostitute in Egypt. They played the prostitute in their youth. Their breasts were fondled there, and their youthful nipples were caressed there. 4 Their names were Oholah the elder, and Oholibah her sister. They became mine, and they bore sons and daughters. As for their names, Samaria is Oholah, and Jerusalem Oholibah.

5 “Oholah played the prostitute when she was mine. She doted on her lovers, on the Assyrians her neighbors, 6 who were clothed with blue, governors and rulers, all of them desirable young men, horsemen riding on horses. 7 She gave herself as a prostitute to them, the choicest men of Assyria all of them. She defiled herself with the idols of whoever she lusted after. 8 She hasn’t left her prostitution since leaving Egypt; for in her youth they lay with her. They carressed her youthful nipples; and they poured out their prostitution on her.

9 “Therefore I delivered her into the hand of her lovers, into the hand of the Assyrians, on whom she doted. 10 These uncovered her nakedness. They took her sons and her daughters; and they killed her with the sword. She became a byword among women; for they executed judgments on her.

11 “Her sister Oholibah saw this, yet she was more corrupt in her lusting than she, and in her prostitution which was more depraved than the prostitution of her sister. 12 She lusted after the Assyrians, governors and rulers, her neighbors, clothed most gorgeously, horsemen riding on horses, all of them desirable young men. 13 I saw that she was defiled. They both went the same way.

14 “She increased her prostitution; for she saw men portrayed on the wall, the images of the Chaldeans portrayed with vermilion, 15 dressed with girdles on their waists, with flowing turbans on their heads, all of them looking like princes, after the likeness of the Babylonians in Chaldea, the land of their birth. 16 As soon as she saw them she lusted after them, and sent messengers to them into Chaldea. 17 The Babylonians came to her into the bed of love, and they defiled her with their prostitution. She was polluted with them, and her soul was alienated from them. 18 So she uncovered her prostitution, and uncovered her nakedness. Then my soul was alienated from her, just like my soul was alienated from her sister. 19 Yet she multiplied her prostitution, remembering the days of her youth, in which she had played the prostitute in the land of Egypt. 20 She lusted after their paramours, whose flesh is as the flesh of donkeys, and whose issue is like the issue of horses. 21 Thus you called to memory the lewdness of your youth, in the caressing of your nipples by the Egyptians because of your youthful breasts.

22 “Therefore, Oholibah, thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Behold, I will raise up your lovers against you, from whom your soul is alienated, and I will bring them against you on every side: 23 the Babylonians and all the Chaldeans, Pekod, Shoa, Koa, and all the Assyrians with them; desirable young men, governors and rulers all of them, princes and men of renown, all of them riding on horses. 24 They will come against you with weapons, chariots, and wagons, and with a company of peoples. They will set themselves against you with buckler, shield, and helmet all around. I will commit the judgment to them, and they will judge you according to their judgments. 25 I will set my jealousy against you, and they will deal with you in fury; they will take away your nose and your ears; and your remnant will fall by the sword. They will take your sons and your daughters; and your residue will be devoured by the fire. 26 They will also strip you of your clothes, and take away your beautiful jewels. 27 Thus I will make your lewdness to cease from you, and remove your prostitution from the land of Egypt; so that you will not lift up your eyes to them, nor remember Egypt any more.’

28 “For thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Behold, I will deliver you into the hand of them whom you hate, into the hand of them from whom your soul is alienated. 29 They will deal with you in hatred, and will take away all your labor, and shall leave you naked and bare. The nakedness of your prostitution will be uncovered, both your lewdness and your prostitution. 30 These things will be done to you, because you have played the prostitute after the nations, and because you are polluted with their idols. 31 You have walked in the way of your sister; therefore will I give her cup into your hand.’

32 “Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

‘You will drink of your sister’s cup,

which is deep and large.

You will be ridiculed and held in derision.

It contains much.

33 You will be filled with drunkenness and sorrow,

with the cup of astonishment and desolation,

with the cup of your sister Samaria.

34 You will even drink it and drain it out.

You will gnaw the broken pieces of it,

and will tear your breasts;

for I have spoken it,’ says the Lord Yahweh.

35 “Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘Because you have forgotten me, and cast me behind your back, therefore you also bear your lewdness and your prostitution.’”

36 Yahweh said moreover to me: “Son of man, will you judge Oholah and Oholibah? Then declare to them their abominations. 37 For they have committed adultery, and blood is in their hands. They have committed adultery with their idols. They have also caused their sons, whom they bore to me, to pass through the fire to them to be devoured. 38 Moreover this they have done to me: they have defiled my sanctuary in the same day, and have profaned my Sabbaths. 39 For when they had slain their children to their idols, then they came the same day into my sanctuary to profane it; and behold, thus have they done in the middle of my house.

40 “Furthermore you sisters have sent for men who come from far away, to whom a messenger was sent, and behold, they came; for whom you washed yourself, painted your eyes, decorated yourself with ornaments, 41 and sat on a stately bed, with a table prepared before it, whereupon you set my incense and my oil.

42 “The voice of a multitude being at ease was with her. With men of the common sort were brought drunkards from the wilderness; and they put bracelets on their hands, and beautiful crowns on their heads. 43 Then I said of her who was old in adulteries, ‘Now they will play the prostitute with her, and she with them.’ 44 They went in to her, as they go in to a prostitute. So they went in to Oholah and to Oholibah, the lewd women. 45 Righteous men will judge them with the judgment of adulteresses and with the judgment of women who shed blood; because they are adulteresses, and blood is in their hands.

46 “For thus says the Lord Yahweh: ‘I will bring up a company against them, and will give them to be tossed back and forth and robbed. 47 The company will stone them with stones, and dispatch them with their swords. They will kill their sons and their daughters, and burn up their houses with fire.

48 “‘Thus I will cause lewdness to cease out of the land, that all women may be taught not to be lewd like you. 49 They shall recompense your lewdness on you, and you will bear the sins of your idols; and you shall know that I am the Lord Yahweh.’”

Ezekiel 24

1 Again, in the ninth year, in the tenth month, in the tenth day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, write the name of the day, this same day. The king of Babylon drew close to Jerusalem this same day. 3 Utter a parable to the rebellious house, and tell them, Thus says the Lord Yahweh,

Set on the cauldron,

set it on,

and also pour water into it:

4 gather its pieces into it,

even every good piece,

the thigh, and the shoulder;

fill it with the choice bones.

5 Take the choice of the flock,

and also a pile of wood for the bones under the cauldron;

make it boil well;

yes, let its bones be boiled within it.

6 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh:

Woe to the bloody city,

to the cauldron whose rust is therein,

and whose rust is not gone out of it!

take out of it piece after piece;

No lot is fallen on it.

7 For her blood is in the middle of her;

she set it on the bare rock;

she didn’t pour it on the ground,

to cover it with dust.

8 That it may cause wrath to come up to take vengeance,

I have set her blood on the bare rock,

that it should not be covered.

9 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh:

Woe to the bloody city!

I also will make the pile great.

10 Heap on the wood,

make the fire hot,

boil the meat well,

and make the broth thick,

and let the bones be burned.

11 Then set it empty on its coals,

that it may be hot,

and its brass may burn,

and that its filthiness may be molten in it,

that its rust may be consumed.

12 She is weary with toil;

yet her great rust,

rust by fire, doesn’t leave her.

13 In your filthiness is lewdness: because I have cleansed you and you weren’t cleansed, you shall not be cleansed from your filthiness any more, until I have caused my wrath toward you to rest.

14 I, Yahweh, have spoken it: it shall happen, and I will do it: I will not go back, neither will I spare, neither will I repent; according to your ways, and according to your doings, shall they judge you, says the Lord Yahweh.

15 Also Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 16 Son of man, behold, I will take away from you the desire of your eyes with a stroke: yet you shall neither mourn nor weep, neither shall your tears run down. 17 Sigh, but not aloud, make no mourning for the dead; bind your headdress on you, and put your shoes on your feet, and don’t cover your lips, and don’t eat men’s bread.

18 So I spoke to the people in the morning; and at evening my wife died; and I did in the morning as I was commanded.

19 The people said to me, Won’t you tell us what these things are to us, that you do so?

20 Then I said to them, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 21 Speak to the house of Israel, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I will profane my sanctuary, the pride of your power, the desire of your eyes, and that which your soul pities; and your sons and your daughters whom you have left behind shall fall by the sword. 22 You shall do as I have done: you shall not cover your lips, nor eat the bread of men. 23 Your tires shall be on your heads, and your shoes on your feet: you shall not mourn nor weep; but you shall pine away in your iniquities, and moan one toward another. 24 Thus Ezekiel shall be a sign to you; according to all that he has done, you will do. When this comes, then you will know that I am the Lord Yahweh.

25 You, son of man, shall it not be in the day when I take from them their strength, the joy of their glory, the desire of their eyes, and that whereupon they set their heart, their sons and their daughters, 26 that in that day he who escapes shall come to you, to cause you to hear it with your ears? 27 In that day your mouth will be opened to him who has escaped, and you shall speak, and be no more mute: so you will be a sign to them; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Ezekiel 25

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, set your face toward the children of Ammon, and prophesy against them: 3 and tell the children of Ammon, Hear the word of the Lord Yahweh: Thus says the Lord Yahweh, Because you said, Aha, against my sanctuary, when it was profaned; and against the land of Israel, when it was made desolate; and against the house of Judah, when they went into captivity: 4 therefore, behold, I will deliver you to the children of the east for a possession, and they shall set their encampments in you, and make their dwellings in you; they shall eat your fruit, and they shall drink your milk. 5 I will make Rabbah a stable for camels, and the children of Ammon a resting place for flocks: and you shall know that I am Yahweh. 6 For thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because you have clapped your hands, and stamped with the feet, and rejoiced with all the despite of your soul against the land of Israel; 7 therefore, behold, I have stretched out my hand on you, and will deliver you for a plunder to the nations; and I will cut you off from the peoples, and I will cause you to perish out of the countries: I will destroy you; and you shall know that I am Yahweh.

8 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because Moab and Seir say, Behold, the house of Judah is like all the nations; 9 therefore, behold, I will open the side of Moab from the cities, from his cities which are on his frontiers, the glory of the country, Beth Jeshimoth, Baal Meon, and Kiriathaim, 10 to the children of the east, to go against the children of Ammon; and I will give them for a possession, that the children of Ammon may not be remembered among the nations. 11 and I will execute judgments on Moab; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

12 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because Edom has dealt against the house of Judah by taking vengeance, and has greatly offended, and revenged himself on them; 13 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh, I will stretch out my hand on Edom, and will cut off man and animal from it; and I will make it desolate from Teman; even to Dedan shall they fall by the sword. 14 I will lay my vengeance on Edom by the hand of my people Israel; and they shall do in Edom according to my anger and according to my wrath; and they shall know my vengeance, says the Lord Yahweh.

15 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because the Philistines have dealt by revenge, and have taken vengeance with despite of soul to destroy with perpetual hostility; 16 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh, Behold, I will stretch out my hand on the Philistines, and I will cut off the Cherethites, and destroy the remnant of the sea coast. 17 I will execute great vengeance on them with wrathful rebukes; and they shall know that I am Yahweh, when I shall lay my vengeance on them.

Ezekiel 26

1 In the eleventh year, in the first of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, because Tyre has said against Jerusalem, Aha, she is broken: the gate of the peoples; she is turned to me; I shall be replenished, now that she is laid waste: 3 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh, Behold, I am against you, Tyre, and will cause many nations to come up against you, as the sea causes its waves to come up. 4 They shall destroy the walls of Tyre, and break down her towers: I will also scrape her dust from her, and make her a bare rock. 5 She shall be a place for the spreading of nets in the middle of the sea; for I have spoken it, says the Lord Yahweh; and she shall become a plunder to the nations. 6 Her daughters who are in the field shall be slain with the sword: and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

7 For thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I will bring on Tyre Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, king of kings, from the north, with horses, and with chariots, and with horsemen, and a company, and many people. 8 He shall kill your daughters in the field with the sword; and he shall make forts against you, and cast up a mound against you, and raise up the buckler against you. 9 He shall set his battering engines against your walls, and with his axes he shall break down your towers. 10 By reason of the abundance of his horses their dust shall cover you: your walls shall shake at the noise of the horsemen, and of the wagons, and of the chariots, when he shall enter into your gates, as men enter into a city in which is made a breach. 11 With the hoofs of his horses shall he tread down all your streets; he shall kill your people with the sword; and the pillars of your strength shall go down to the ground. 12 They shall make a plunder of your riches, and make a prey of your merchandise; and they shall break down your walls, and destroy your pleasant houses; and they shall lay your stones and your timber and your dust in the middle of the waters. 13 I will cause the noise of your songs to cease; and the sound of your harps shall be no more heard. 14 I will make you a bare rock; you shall be a place for the spreading of nets; you shall be built no more: for I Yahweh have spoken it, says the Lord Yahweh.

15 Thus says the Lord Yahweh to Tyre: shall not the islands shake at the sound of your fall, when the wounded groan, when the slaughter is made within you? 16 Then all the princes of the sea shall come down from their thrones, and lay aside their robes, and strip off their embroidered garments: they shall clothe themselves with trembling; they shall sit on the ground, and shall tremble every moment, and be astonished at you. 17 They shall take up a lamentation over you, and tell you,

How you are destroyed,

who were inhabited by seafaring men,

the renowned city,

who was strong in the sea,

she and her inhabitants,

who caused their terror to be on all who lived there!

18 Now shall the islands tremble in the day of your fall;

yes, the islands that are in the sea shall be dismayed at your departure.

19 For thus says the Lord Yahweh: When I shall make you a desolate city, like the cities that are not inhabited; when I shall bring up the deep on you, and the great waters shall cover you; 20 then I will bring you down with those who descend into the pit, to the people of old time, and will make you to dwell in the lower parts of the earth, in the places that are desolate of old, with those who go down to the pit, that you be not inhabited; and I will set glory in the land of the living: 21 I will make you a terror, and you shall no more have any being; though you are sought for, yet you will never be found again, says the Lord Yahweh.

Ezekiel 27

1 Yahweh’s word came again to me, saying, 2 You, son of man, take up a lamentation over Tyre; 3 and tell Tyre, you who dwell at the entry of the sea, who are the merchant of the peoples to many islands, thus says the Lord Yahweh:

You, Tyre, have said,

I am perfect in beauty.

4 Your borders are in the heart of the seas;

your builders have perfected your beauty.

5 They have made all your planks of cypress trees from Senir;

they have taken a cedar from Lebanon to make a mast for you.

6 Of the oaks of Bashan have they made your oars;

they have made your benches of ivory inlaid in boxwood,

from the islands of Kittim.

7 Your sail was of fine linen with embroidered work from Egypt,

that it might be to you for a banner;

blue and purple from the islands of Elishah was your awning.

8 The inhabitants of Sidon and Arvad were your rowers:

your wise men, Tyre, were in you,

they were your pilots.

9 The old men of Gebal

and its wise men were your repairers of ship seams in you:

all the ships of the sea with their mariners were in you

to deal in your merchandise.

10 Persia and Lud and Put were in your army,

your men of war:

they hanged the shield and helmet in you;

they showed your beauty.

11 The men of Arvad with your army were on your walls all around,

and valorous men were in your towers;

they hung their shields on your walls all around;

they have perfected your beauty.

12 Tarshish was your merchant by reason of the multitude of all kinds of riches; with silver, iron, tin, and lead, they traded for your wares.

13 Javan, Tubal, and Meshech, they were your traffickers; they traded the persons of men and vessels of brass for your merchandise.

14 They of the house of Togarmah traded for your wares with horses and war horses and mules.

15 The men of Dedan were your traffickers; many islands were the market of your hand: they brought you in exchange horns of ivory and ebony.

16 Syria was your merchant by reason of the multitude of your handiworks: they traded for your wares with emeralds, purple, and embroidered work, and fine linen, and coral, and rubies.

17 Judah, and the land of Israel, they were your traffickers: they traded for your merchandise wheat of Minnith, and confections, and honey, and oil, and balm.

18 Damascus was your merchant for the multitude of your handiworks, by reason of the multitude of all kinds of riches, with the wine of Helbon, and white wool.

19 Vedan and Javan traded with yarn for your wares: bright iron, cassia, and calamus, were among your merchandise.

20 Dedan was your trafficker in precious cloths for riding.

21 Arabia, and all the princes of Kedar, they were the merchants of your hand; in lambs, and rams, and goats, in these were they your merchants.

22 The traffickers of Sheba and Raamah, they were your traffickers; they traded for your wares with the chief of all spices, and with all precious stones, and gold.

23 Haran and Canneh and Eden, the traffickers of Sheba, Asshur and Chilmad, were your traffickers. 24 These were your traffickers in choice wares, in wrappings of blue and embroidered work, and in chests of rich clothing, bound with cords and made of cedar, among your merchandise.

25 The ships of Tarshish were your caravans for your merchandise:

and you were replenished,

and made very glorious in the heart of the seas.

26 Your rowers have brought you into great waters:

the east wind has broken you in the heart of the seas.

27 Your riches,

and your wares,

your merchandise,

your mariners,

and your pilots,

your repairers of ship seams,

and the dealers in your merchandise,

and all your men of war, who are in you,

with all your company which is among you,

shall fall into the heart of the seas in the day of your ruin.

28 At the sound of the cry of your pilots

the suburbs shall shake.

29 All who handled the oar,

the mariners,

and all the pilots of the sea,

shall come down from their ships;

they shall stand on the land,

30 and shall cause their voice to be heard over you,

and shall cry bitterly,

and shall cast up dust on their heads,

they shall wallow themselves in the ashes:

31 and they shall make themselves bald for you,

and clothe them with sackcloth,

and they shall weep for you in bitterness of soul

with bitter mourning.

32 In their wailing they shall take up a lamentation for you,

and lament over you, saying,

Who is there like Tyre,

like her who is brought to silence in the middle of the sea?

33 When your wares went out of the seas,

you filled many peoples;

you enriched the kings of the earth

with the multitude of your riches and of your merchandise.

34 In the time that you were broken by the seas

in the depths of the waters,

your merchandise

and all your company fell within you.

35 All the inhabitants of the islands are astonished at you,

and their kings are horribly afraid;

they are troubled in their face.

36 The merchants among the peoples hiss at you;

you have become a terror,

and you will be no more.

Ezekiel 28

1 Yahweh’s word came again to me, saying, 2 Son of man, tell the prince of Tyre, Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

Because your heart is lifted up,

and you have said, I am a god,

I sit in the seat of God,

in the middle of the seas;

yet you are man,

and not God,

though you set your heart as the heart of God—

3 behold, you are wiser than Daniel;

there is no secret that is hidden from you;

4 by your wisdom and by your understanding you have gotten yourself riches,

and have gotten gold and silver into your treasures;

5 by your great wisdom

and by your traffic you have increased your riches,

and your heart is lifted up because of your riches—

6 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh:

Because you have set your heart as the heart of God,

7 therefore, behold, I will bring strangers on you,

the terrible of the nations;

and they shall draw their swords against the beauty of your wisdom,

and they shall defile your brightness.

8 They shall bring you down to the pit;

and you shall die the death of those who are slain,

in the heart of the seas.

9 Will you yet say before him who kills you, I am God?

but you are man, and not God,

in the hand of him who wounds you.

10 You shall die the death of the uncircumcised

by the hand of strangers:

for I have spoken it, says the Lord Yahweh.

11 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 12 Son of man, take up a lamentation over the king of Tyre, and tell him, Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

You were the seal of full measure,

full of wisdom,

and perfect in beauty.

13 You were in Eden,

the garden of God;

every precious stone adorned you:

ruby, topaz, emerald,

chrysolite, onyx, jasper,

sapphire,[*] turquoise, and beryl.

Gold work of tambourines

and of pipes was in you.

In the day that you were created they were prepared.

14 You were the anointed cherub who covers:

and I set you, so that you were on the holy mountain of God;

you have walked up and down in the middle of the stones of fire.

15 You were perfect in your ways from the day that you were created,

until unrighteousness was found in you.

16 By the abundance of your traffic they filled your insides with violence,

and you have sinned:

therefore I have cast you as profane out of the mountain of God;

and I have destroyed you, covering cherub,

from the middle of the stones of fire.

17 Your heart was lifted up because of your beauty;

you have corrupted your wisdom by reason of your brightness:

I have cast you to the ground;

I have laid you before kings,

that they may see you.

18 By the multitude of your iniquities,

in the unrighteousness of your traffic,

you have profaned your sanctuaries;

therefore I have brought out a fire from the middle of you;

it has devoured you,

and I have turned you to ashes on the earth

in the sight of all those who see you.

19 All those who know you among the peoples shall be astonished at you:

you have become a terror,

and you shall exist no more.

20 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 21 Son of man, set your face toward Sidon, and prophesy against it, 22 and say, Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

Behold, I am against you, Sidon;

and I will be glorified among you;

and they shall know that I am Yahweh,

when I shall have executed judgments in her,

and shall be sanctified in her.

23 For I will send pestilence into her,

and blood into her streets;

and the wounded shall fall within her,

with the sword on her on every side;

and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

24 There shall be no more a pricking brier to the house of Israel, nor a hurting thorn of any that are around them, that scorned them; and they shall know that I am the Lord Yahweh.

25 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: When I shall have gathered the house of Israel from the peoples among whom they are scattered, and shall be sanctified in them in the sight of the nations, then shall they dwell in their own land which I gave to my servant Jacob. 26 They shall dwell securely therein; yes, they shall build houses, and plant vineyards, and shall dwell securely, when I have executed judgments on all those who do them despite all around them; and they shall know that I am Yahweh their God.

or, lapis lazuli

Ezekiel 29

1 In the tenth year, in the tenth month, on the twelfth day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 “Son of man, set your face against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and prophesy against him and against all Egypt. 3 Speak and say, ‘Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

“Behold, I am against you, Pharaoh king of Egypt,

the great monster that lies in the middle of his rivers,

that has said, ‘My river is my own,

and I have made it for myself.’

4 I will put hooks in your jaws,

and I will make the fish of your rivers stick to your scales;

and I will bring you up out of the middle of your rivers,

with all the fish of your rivers which stick to your scales.

5 I’ll cast you out into the wilderness,

you and all the fish of your rivers.

You’ll fall on the open field.

You won’t be brought together,

nor gathered.

I have given you for food to the animals of the earth

and to the birds of the sky.

6 All the inhabitants of Egypt will know that I am Yahweh, because they have been a staff of reed to the house of Israel. 7 When they took hold of you by your hand, you broke, and tore all their shoulders; and when they leaned on you, you broke, and paralyzed all of their thighs.”

8 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: “Behold, I will bring a sword on you, and will cut off man and animal from you. 9 The land of Egypt shall be a desolation and a waste; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Because he has said, ‘The river is mine, and I have made it;’ 10 therefore, behold, I am against you, and against your rivers, and I will make the land of Egypt an utter waste and desolation, from the tower of Seveneh even to the border of Ethiopia. 11 No foot of man shall pass through it, nor foot of animal shall pass through it, neither shall it be inhabited forty years. 12 I will make the land of Egypt a desolation in the middle of the countries that are desolate; and her cities among the cities that are laid waste shall be a desolation forty years; and I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and will disperse them through the countries.”

13 For thus says the Lord Yahweh: “At the end of forty years will I gather the Egyptians from the peoples where they were scattered; 14 and I will bring back the captivity of Egypt, and will cause them to return into the land of Pathros, into the land of their birth; and they shall be there a base kingdom. 15 It shall be the base of the kingdoms; neither shall it any more lift itself up above the nations: and I will diminish them, that they shall no more rule over the nations. 16 It shall be no more the confidence of the house of Israel, bringing iniquity to memory, when they turn to look after them: and they shall know that I am the Lord Yahweh.”’”

17 It came to pass in the seven and twentieth year, in the first month, in the first day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 18 Son of man, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon caused his army to serve a great service against Tyre: every head was made bald, and every shoulder was worn; yet had he no wages, nor his army, from Tyre, for the service that he had served against it. 19 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I will give the land of Egypt to Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon; and he shall carry off her multitude, and take her plunder, and take her prey; and it shall be the wages for his army. 20 I have given him the land of Egypt as his recompense for which he served, because they worked for me, says the Lord Yahweh.

21 In that day will I cause a horn to sprout for the house of Israel, and I will give you the opening of the mouth among them; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Ezekiel 30

1 Yahweh’s word came again to me, saying, 2 Son of man, prophesy, and say, Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

Wail, Alas for the day!

3 For the day is near,

even the day of Yahweh is near;

it shall be a day of clouds,

a time of the nations.

4 A sword shall come on Egypt,

and anguish shall be in Ethiopia,

when the slain shall fall in Egypt;

and they shall take away her multitude,

and her foundations shall be broken down.

5 Ethiopia, and Put, and Lud, and all the mixed people, and Cub, and the children of the land that is allied with them, shall fall with them by the sword.

6 Yahweh says:

They also who uphold Egypt shall fall;

and the pride of her power shall come down:

they shall fall by the sword in it from the tower of Seveneh,

says the Lord Yahweh.

7 They shall be desolate in the middle of the countries that are desolate;

and her cities shall be in the middle of the cities that are wasted.

8 They shall know that I am Yahweh,

when I have set a fire in Egypt,

and all her helpers are destroyed.

9 In that day messengers will go out from before me in ships to make the careless Ethiopians afraid; and there shall be anguish on them, as in the day of Egypt; for, behold, it comes.

10 Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

I will also make the multitude of Egypt to cease,

by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon.

11 He and his people with him,

the terrible of the nations,

shall be brought in to destroy the land;

and they shall draw their swords against Egypt,

and fill the land with the slain.

12 I will make the rivers dry,

and will sell the land into the hand of evil men;

and I will make the land desolate,

and all that is therein,

by the hand of strangers:

I, Yahweh, have spoken it.

13 Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

I will also destroy the idols,

and I will cause the images to cease from Memphis;

and there shall be no more a prince from the land of Egypt:

and I will put a fear in the land of Egypt.

14 I will make Pathros desolate,

and will set a fire in Zoan,

and will execute judgments on No.

15 I will pour my wrath on Sin,

the stronghold of Egypt;

and I will cut off the multitude of No.

16 I will set a fire in Egypt:

Sin shall be in great anguish,

and No shall be broken up;

and Memphis shall have adversaries in the daytime.

17 The young men of Aven and of Pibeseth shall fall by the sword;

and they shall go into captivity.

18 At Tehaphnehes also the day shall withdraw itself,

when I shall break there the yokes of Egypt,

and the pride of her power shall cease in her:

as for her, a cloud shall cover her,

and her daughters shall go into captivity.

19 Thus will I execute judgments on Egypt;

and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

20 In the eleventh year, in the first month, in the seventh day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 21 Son of man, I have broken the arm of Pharaoh king of Egypt; and behold, it has not been bound up, to apply medicines, to put a bandage to bind it, that it be strong to hold the sword. 22 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I am against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and will break his arms, the strong arm, and that which was broken; and I will cause the sword to fall out of his hand. 23 I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and will disperse them through the countries. 24 I will strengthen the arms of the king of Babylon, and put my sword in his hand: but I will break the arms of Pharaoh, and he shall groan before him with the groaning of a mortally wounded man. 25 I will hold up the arms of the king of Babylon; and the arms of Pharaoh shall fall down; and they shall know that I am Yahweh, when I shall put my sword into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he shall stretch it out on the land of Egypt. 26 I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations, and disperse them through the countries; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Ezekiel 31

1 In the eleventh year, in the third month, in the first day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, tell Pharaoh king of Egypt, and to his multitude:

Whom are you like in your greatness?

3 Behold, the Assyrian was a cedar in Lebanon

with beautiful branches,

and with a forest-like shade,

and of high stature;

and its top was among the thick boughs.

4 The waters nourished it,

the deep made it to grow:

its rivers ran all around its plantation;

and it sent out its channels to all the trees of the field.

5 Therefore its stature was exalted above all the trees of the field;

and its boughs were multiplied,

and its branches became long by reason of many waters,

when it spread them out.

6 All the birds of the sky made their nests in its boughs;

and under its branches all the animals of the field gave birth to their young;

and all great nations lived under its shadow.

7 Thus was it beautiful in its greatness,

in the length of its branches;

for its root was by many waters.

8 The cedars in the garden of God could not hide it;

the cypress trees were not like its boughs,

and the pine trees were not as its branches;

nor was any tree in the garden of God like it in its beauty.

9 I made it beautiful by the multitude of its branches,

so that all the trees of Eden,

that were in the garden of God, envied it.

10 Therefore thus said the Lord Yahweh: Because you are exalted in stature, and he has set his top among the thick boughs, and his heart is lifted up in his height; 11 I will even deliver him into the hand of the mighty one of the nations; he shall surely deal with him; I have driven him out for his wickedness. 12 Strangers, the terrible of the nations, have cut him off, and have left him: on the mountains and in all the valleys his branches are fallen, and his boughs are broken by all the watercourses of the land; and all the peoples of the earth are gone down from his shadow, and have left him. 13 On his ruin all the birds of the sky shall dwell, and all the animals of the field shall be on his branches; 14 to the end that none of all the trees by the waters exalt themselves in their stature, neither set their top among the thick boughs, nor that their mighty ones stand up on their height, even all who drink water: for they are all delivered to death, to the lower parts of the earth, among the children of men, with those who go down to the pit.

15 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: In the day when he went down to Sheol[*] I caused a mourning: I covered the deep for him, and I restrained its rivers; and the great waters were stayed; and I caused Lebanon to mourn for him, and all the trees of the field fainted for him. 16 I made the nations to shake at the sound of his fall, when I cast him down to Sheol[*] with those who descend into the pit; and all the trees of Eden, the choice and best of Lebanon, all that drink water, were comforted in the lower parts of the earth. 17 They also went down into Sheol with him to those who are slain by the sword; yes, those who were his arm, who lived under his shadow in the middle of the nations.

18 To whom are you thus like in glory and in greatness among the trees of Eden? yet you will be brought down with the trees of Eden to the lower parts of the earth: you shall lie in the middle of the uncircumcised, with those who are slain by the sword.

This is Pharaoh and all his multitude, says the Lord Yahweh.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Ezekiel 32

1 In the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, in the first day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, take up a lamentation over Pharaoh king of Egypt, and tell him,

You were likened to a young lion of the nations:

yet you are as a monster in the seas;

and you broke out with your rivers,

and troubled the waters with your feet,

and fouled their rivers.

3 Thus says the Lord Yahweh:

I will spread out my net on you with a company of many peoples;

and they shall bring you up in my net.

4 I will leave you on the land,

I will cast you out on the open field,

and will cause all the birds of the sky to settle on you,

and I will satisfy the animals of the whole earth with you.

5 I will lay your flesh on the mountains,

and fill the valleys with your height.

6 I will also water with your blood the land in which you swim,

even to the mountains;

and the watercourses shall be full of you.

7 When I shall extinguish you, I will cover the heavens,

and make its stars dark;

I will cover the sun with a cloud,

and the moon shall not give its light.

8 I will make all the bright lights of the sky dark over you,

and set darkness on your land, says the Lord Yahweh.

9 I will also trouble the hearts of many peoples,

when I shall bring your destruction among the nations,

into the countries which you have not known.

10 Yes, I will make many peoples amazed at you,

and their kings shall be horribly afraid for you,

when I shall brandish my sword before them;

and they shall tremble at every moment,

every man for his own life,

in the day of your fall.

11 For thus says the Lord Yahweh:

The sword of the king of Babylon shall come on you.

12 By the swords of the mighty will I cause your multitude to fall;

they are all the ruthless of the nations:

and they shall bring to nothing the pride of Egypt,

and all its multitude shall be destroyed.

13 I will destroy also all its animals from beside many waters;

neither shall the foot of man trouble them any more,

nor the hoofs of animals trouble them.

14 Then will I make their waters clear,

and cause their rivers to run like oil,

says the Lord Yahweh.

15 When I shall make the land of Egypt desolate and waste,

a land destitute of that of which it was full,

when I shall strike all those who dwell therein,

then shall they know that I am Yahweh.

16 This is the lamentation with which they shall lament; the daughters of the nations shall lament therewith; over Egypt, and over all her multitude, shall they lament therewith, says the Lord Yahweh.

17 Also in the twelfth year, in the fifteenth day of the month, Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 18 Son of man, wail for the multitude of Egypt, and cast them down, even her, and the daughters of the famous nations, to the lower parts of the earth, with those who go down into the pit. 19 Whom do you pass in beauty? Go down, and be laid with the uncircumcised. 20 They shall fall among those who are slain by the sword: she is delivered to the sword; draw her away and all her multitudes. 21 The strong among the mighty shall speak to him out of the middle of Sheol[*] with those who help him: they are gone down, they lie still, even the uncircumcised, slain by the sword.

22 Asshur is there and all her company; her graves are all around her; all of them slain, fallen by the sword; 23 whose graves are set in the uttermost parts of the pit, and her company is around her grave; all of them slain, fallen by the sword, who caused terror in the land of the living.

24 There is Elam and all her multitude around her grave; all of them slain, fallen by the sword, who are gone down uncircumcised into the lower parts of the earth, who caused their terror in the land of the living, and have borne their shame with those who go down to the pit. 25 They have set her a bed among the slain with all her multitude; her graves are around her; all of them uncircumcised, slain by the sword; for their terror was caused in the land of the living, and they have borne their shame with those who go down to the pit: he is put among those who are slain.

26 There is Meshech, Tubal, and all their multitude; their graves are around them; all of them uncircumcised, slain by the sword; for they caused their terror in the land of the living. 27 They shall not lie with the mighty who are fallen of the uncircumcised, who have gone down to Sheol with their weapons of war, and have laid their swords under their heads, and their iniquities are on their bones; for they were the terror of the mighty in the land of the living.

28 But you shall be broken among the uncircumcised, and shall lie with those who are slain by the sword.

29 There is Edom, her kings and all her princes, who in their might are laid with those who are slain by the sword: they shall lie with the uncircumcised, and with those who go down to the pit.

30 There are the princes of the north, all of them, and all the Sidonians, who are gone down with the slain; in the terror which they caused by their might they are put to shame; and they lie uncircumcised with those who are slain by the sword, and bear their shame with those who go down to the pit.

31 Pharaoh shall see them, and shall be comforted over all his multitude, even Pharaoh and all his army, slain by the sword, says the Lord Yahweh. 32 For I have put his terror in the land of the living; and he shall be laid among the uncircumcised, with those who are slain by the sword, even Pharaoh and all his multitude, says the Lord Yahweh.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Ezekiel 33

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, speak to the children of your people, and tell them, When I bring the sword on a land, and the people of the land take a man from among them, and set him for their watchman; 3 if, when he sees the sword come on the land, he blow the trumpet, and warn the people; 4 then whoever hears the sound of the trumpet, and doesn’t take warning, if the sword come, and take him away, his blood shall be on his own head. 5 He heard the sound of the trumpet, and didn’t take warning; his blood shall be on him; whereas if he had taken warning, he would have delivered his soul. 6 But if the watchman sees the sword come, and doesn’t blow the trumpet, and the people aren’t warned, and the sword comes, and take any person from among them; he is taken away in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at the watchman’s hand.

7 So you, son of man, I have set you a watchman to the house of Israel; therefore hear the word at my mouth, and give them warning from me. 8 When I tell the wicked, O wicked man, you shall surely die, and you don’t speak to warn the wicked from his way; that wicked man shall die in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at your hand. 9 Nevertheless, if you warn the wicked of his way to turn from it, and he doesn’t turn from his way; he shall die in his iniquity, but you have delivered your soul.

10 You, son of man, tell the house of Israel: Thus you speak, saying, Our transgressions and our sins are on us, and we pine away in them; how then can we live? 11 Tell them, As I live, says the Lord Yahweh, I have no pleasure in the death of the wicked; but that the wicked turn from his way and live: turn, turn from your evil ways; for why will you die, house of Israel?

12 You, son of man, tell the children of your people, The righteousness of the righteous shall not deliver him in the day of his disobedience; and as for the wickedness of the wicked, he shall not fall thereby in the day that he turns from his wickedness; neither shall he who is righteous be able to live thereby in the day that he sins. 13 When I tell the righteous, that he shall surely live; if he trust to his righteousness, and commit iniquity, none of his righteous deeds shall be remembered; but in his iniquity that he has committed, therein shall he die. 14 Again, when I say to the wicked, You shall surely die; if he turn from his sin, and do that which is lawful and right; 15 if the wicked restore the pledge, give again that which he had taken by robbery, walk in the statutes of life, committing no iniquity; he shall surely live, he shall not die. 16 None of his sins that he has committed shall be remembered against him: he has done that which is lawful and right; he shall surely live.

17 Yet the children of your people say, The way of the Lord is not equal: but as for them, their way is not equal. 18 When the righteous turns from his righteousness, and commits iniquity, he shall even die therein. 19 When the wicked turns from his wickedness, and does that which is lawful and right, he shall live thereby. 20 Yet you say, The way of the Lord is not equal. House of Israel, I will judge every one of you after his ways.

21 In the twelfth year of our captivity, in the tenth month, in the fifth day of the month, one who had escaped out of Jerusalem came to me, saying, The city has been struck. 22 Now Yahweh’s hand had been on me in the evening, before he who was escaped came; and he had opened my mouth, until he came to me in the morning; and my mouth was opened, and I was no more mute.

23 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 24 Son of man, they who inhabit those waste places in the land of Israel speak, saying, Abraham was one, and he inherited the land: but we are many; the land is given us for inheritance. 25 Therefore tell them, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: You eat with the blood, and lift up your eyes to your idols, and shed blood: and shall you possess the land? 26 You stand on your sword, you work abomination, and every one of you defiles his neighbor’s wife: and shall you possess the land?

27 You shall tell them, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: As I live, surely those who are in the waste places shall fall by the sword; and him who is in the open field will I give to the animals to be devoured; and those who are in the strongholds and in the caves shall die of the pestilence. 28 I will make the land a desolation and an astonishment; and the pride of her power shall cease; and the mountains of Israel shall be desolate, so that no one shall pass through. 29 Then shall they know that I am Yahweh, when I have made the land a desolation and an astonishment, because of all their abominations which they have committed.

30 As for you, son of man, the children of your people talk of you by the walls and in the doors of the houses, and speak to one another, everyone to his brother, saying, Please come and hear what is the word that comes out from Yahweh. 31 They come to you as the people come, and they sit before you as my people, and they hear your words, but don’t do them; for with their mouth they show much love, but their heart goes after their gain. 32 Behold, you are to them as a very lovely song of one who has a pleasant voice, and can play well on an instrument; for they hear your words, but they don’t do them.

33 When this comes to pass, (behold, it comes), then shall they know that a prophet has been among them.

Ezekiel 34

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, prophesy against the shepherds of Israel, prophesy, and tell them, even to the shepherds, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Woe to the shepherds of Israel who feed themselves! Shouldn’t the shepherds feed the sheep? 3 You eat the fat, and you clothe yourself with the wool, you kill the fatlings; but you don’t feed the sheep. 4 You haven’t strengthened the diseased, neither have you healed that which was sick, neither have you bound up that which was broken, neither have you brought back that which was driven away, neither have you sought that which was lost; but with force and with rigor you have ruled over them. 5 They were scattered, because there was no shepherd; and they became food to all the animals of the field, and were scattered. 6 My sheep wandered through all the mountains, and on every high hill: yes, my sheep were scattered on all the surface of the earth; and there was no one who searched or sought.

7 Therefore, you shepherds, hear Yahweh’s word: 8 As I live, says the Lord Yahweh, surely because my sheep became a prey, and my sheep became food to all the animals of the field, because there was no shepherd, neither did my shepherds search for my sheep, but the shepherds fed themselves, and didn’t feed my sheep; 9 therefore, you shepherds, hear Yahweh’s word: 10 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I am against the shepherds; and I will require my sheep at their hand, and cause them to cease from feeding the sheep; neither shall the shepherds feed themselves any more; and I will deliver my sheep from their mouth, that they may not be food for them.

11 For thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I myself, even I, will search for my sheep, and will seek them out. 12 As a shepherd seeks out his flock in the day that he is among his sheep that are scattered abroad, so will I seek out my sheep; and I will deliver them out of all places where they have been scattered in the cloudy and dark day. 13 I will bring them out from the peoples, and gather them from the countries, and will bring them into their own land; and I will feed them on the mountains of Israel, by the watercourses, and in all the inhabited places of the country. 14 I will feed them with good pasture; and on the mountains of the height of Israel shall their fold be: there shall they lie down in a good fold; and on fat pasture shall they feed on the mountains of Israel. 15 I myself will be the shepherd of my sheep, and I will cause them to lie down, says the Lord Yahweh. 16 I will seek that which was lost, and will bring back that which was driven away, and will bind up that which was broken, and will strengthen that which was sick: but the fat and the strong I will destroy; I will feed them in justice.

17 As for you, O my flock, thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I judge between sheep and sheep, the rams and the male goats. 18 Does it seem a small thing to you to have fed on the good pasture, but you must tread down with your feet the residue of your pasture? and to have drunk of the clear waters, but you must foul the residue with your feet? 19 As for my sheep, they eat that which you have trodden with your feet, and they drink that which you have fouled with your feet.

20 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh to them: Behold, I, even I, will judge between the fat sheep and the lean sheep. 21 Because you thrust with side and with shoulder, and push all the diseased with your horns, until you have scattered them abroad; 22 therefore will I save my flock, and they shall no more be a prey; and I will judge between sheep and sheep. 23 I will set up one shepherd over them, and he shall feed them, even my servant David; he shall feed them, and he shall be their shepherd. 24 I, Yahweh, will be their God, and my servant David prince among them; I, Yahweh, have spoken it.

25 I will make with them a covenant of peace, and will cause evil animals to cease out of the land; and they shall dwell securely in the wilderness, and sleep in the woods. 26 I will make them and the places around my hill a blessing; and I will cause the shower to come down in its season; there shall be showers of blessing. 27 The tree of the field shall yield its fruit, and the earth shall yield its increase, and they shall be secure in their land; and they shall know that I am Yahweh, when I have broken the bars of their yoke, and have delivered them out of the hand of those who made slaves of them. 28 They shall no more be a prey to the nations, neither shall the animals of the earth devour them; but they shall dwell securely, and no one shall make them afraid. 29 I will raise up to them a plantation for renown, and they shall be no more consumed with famine in the land, neither bear the shame of the nations any more. 30 They shall know that I, Yahweh, their God am with them, and that they, the house of Israel, are my people, says the Lord Yahweh. 31 You my sheep, the sheep of my pasture, are men, and I am your God, says the Lord Yahweh.

Ezekiel 35

1 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, set your face against Mount Seir, and prophesy against it, 3 and tell it, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I am against you, Mount Seir, and I will stretch out my hand against you, and I will make you a desolation and an astonishment. 4 I will lay your cities waste, and you shall be desolate; and you shall know that I am Yahweh. 5 Because you have had a perpetual hostility, and have given over the children of Israel to the power of the sword in the time of their calamity, in the time of the iniquity of the end; 6 therefore, as I live, says the Lord Yahweh, I will prepare you for blood, and blood shall pursue you: since you have not hated blood, therefore blood shall pursue you. 7 Thus will I make Mount Seir an astonishment and a desolation; and I will cut off from it him who passes through and him who returns. 8 I will fill its mountains with its slain: in your hills and in your valleys and in all your watercourses shall they fall who are slain with the sword. 9 I will make you a perpetual desolation, and your cities shall not be inhabited; and you shall know that I am Yahweh.

10 Because you have said, These two nations and these two countries shall be mine, and we will possess it; whereas Yahweh was there: 11 therefore, as I live, says the Lord Yahweh, I will do according to your anger, and according to your envy which you have shown out of your hatred against them; and I will make myself known among them, when I shall judge you. 12 You shall know that I, Yahweh, have heard all your insults which you have spoken against the mountains of Israel, saying, They are laid desolate, they have been given us to devour. 13 You have magnified yourselves against me with your mouth, and have multiplied your words against me: I have heard it. 14 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: When the whole earth rejoices, I will make you desolate. 15 As you rejoiced over the inheritance of the house of Israel, because it was desolate, so will I do to you: you shall be desolate, Mount Seir, and all Edom, even all of it; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Ezekiel 36

1 You, son of man, prophesy to the mountains of Israel, and say, You mountains of Israel, hear Yahweh’s word. 2 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because the enemy has said against you, Aha! and, The ancient high places are ours in possession; 3 therefore prophesy, and say, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because, even because they have made you desolate, and swallowed you up on every side, that you might be a possession to the residue of the nations, and you are taken up in the lips of talkers, and the evil report of the people; 4 therefore, you mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Lord Yahweh: Thus says the Lord Yahweh to the mountains and to the hills, to the watercourses and to the valleys, to the desolate wastes and to the cities that are forsaken, which are become a prey and derision to the residue of the nations that are all around; 5 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: Surely in the fire of my jealousy I have spoken against the residue of the nations, and against all Edom, that have appointed my land to themselves for a possession with the joy of all their heart, with despite of soul, to cast it out for a prey. 6 Therefore prophesy concerning the land of Israel, and tell the mountains and to the hills, to the watercourses and to the valleys, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I have spoken in my jealousy and in my wrath, because you have borne the shame of the nations: 7 therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: I have sworn, Surely the nations that are around you, they shall bear their shame.

8 But you, mountains of Israel, you shall shoot out your branches, and yield your fruit to my people Israel; for they are at hand to come. 9 For, behold, I am for you, and I will turn into you, and you shall be tilled and sown; 10 and I will multiply men on you, all the house of Israel, even all of it; and the cities shall be inhabited, and the waste places shall be built; 11 and I will multiply on you man and animal; and they shall increase and be fruitful; and I will cause you to be inhabited after your former estate, and you will do better than at your beginnings: and you shall know that I am Yahweh. 12 Yes, I will cause men to walk on you, even my people Israel; and they shall possess you, and you shall be their inheritance, and you shall no more henceforth bereave them of children.

13 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Because they say to you, You are a devourer of men, and have been a bereaver of your nation; 14 therefore you shall devour men no more, neither bereave your nation any more, says the Lord Yahweh; 15 neither will I let you hear any more the shame of the nations, neither shall you bear the reproach of the peoples any more, neither shall you cause your nation to stumble any more, says the Lord Yahweh.

16 Moreover Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 17 Son of man, when the house of Israel lived in their own land, they defiled it by their way and by their doings: their way before me was as the uncleanness of a woman in her impurity. 18 Therefore I poured out my wrath on them for the blood which they had poured out on the land, and because they had defiled it with their idols; 19 and I scattered them among the nations, and they were dispersed through the countries: according to their way and according to their doings I judged them. 20 When they came to the nations, where they went, they profaned my holy name; in that men said of them, These are the people of Yahweh, and are gone out of his land. 21 But I had respect for my holy name, which the house of Israel had profaned among the nations, where they went.

22 Therefore tell the house of Israel, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: I don’t do this for your sake, house of Israel, but for my holy name, which you have profaned among the nations, where you went. 23 I will sanctify my great name, which has been profaned among the nations, which you have profaned among them; and the nations shall know that I am Yahweh, says the Lord Yahweh, when I shall be sanctified in you before their eyes.

24 For I will take you from among the nations, and gather you out of all the countries, and will bring you into your own land. 25 I will sprinkle clean water on you, and you shall be clean: from all your filthiness, and from all your idols, will I cleanse you. 26 I will also give you a new heart, and I will put a new spirit within you; and I will take away the stony heart out of your flesh, and I will give you a heart of flesh. 27 I will put my Spirit within you, and cause you to walk in my statutes, and you shall keep my ordinances, and do them. 28 You shall dwell in the land that I gave to your fathers; and you shall be my people, and I will be your God. 29 I will save you from all your uncleanness: and I will call for the grain, and will multiply it, and lay no famine on you. 30 I will multiply the fruit of the tree, and the increase of the field, that you may receive no more the reproach of famine among the nations.

31 Then you shall remember your evil ways, and your doings that were not good; and you shall loathe yourselves in your own sight for your iniquities and for your abominations. 32 Nor for your sake do I this, says the Lord Yahweh, be it known to you: be ashamed and confounded for your ways, house of Israel.

33 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: In the day that I cleanse you from all your iniquities, I will cause the cities to be inhabited, and the waste places shall be built. 34 The land that was desolate shall be tilled, whereas it was a desolation in the sight of all who passed by. 35 They shall say, This land that was desolate has become like the garden of Eden; and the waste and desolate and ruined cities are fortified and inhabited. 36 Then the nations that are left around you shall know that I, Yahweh, have built the ruined places, and planted that which was desolate: I, Yahweh, have spoken it, and I will do it.

37 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: For this, moreover, will I be inquired of by the house of Israel, to do it for them: I will increase them with men like a flock. 38 As the flock for sacrifice, as the flock of Jerusalem in her appointed feasts, so shall the waste cities be filled with flocks of men; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Ezekiel 37

1 Yahweh’s hand was on me, and he brought me out in Yahweh’s Spirit, and set me down in the middle of the valley; and it was full of bones. 2 He caused me to pass by them all around: and behold, there were very many in the open valley; and behold, they were very dry. 3 He said to me, Son of man, can these bones live?

I answered, Lord Yahweh, you know.

4 Again he said to me, Prophesy over these bones, and tell them, you dry bones, hear Yahweh’s word. 5 Thus says the Lord Yahweh to these bones: Behold, I will cause breath to enter into you, and you shall live. 6 I will lay sinews on you, and will bring up flesh on you, and cover you with skin, and put breath in you, and you shall live; and you shall know that I am Yahweh.

7 So I prophesied as I was commanded: and as I prophesied, there was a noise, and behold, an earthquake; and the bones came together, bone to its bone. 8 I saw, and, behold, there were sinews on them, and flesh came up, and skin covered them above; but there was no breath in them.

9 Then he said to me, Prophesy to the wind, prophesy, son of man, and tell the wind, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Come from the four winds, breath, and breathe on these slain, that they may live. 10 So I prophesied as he commanded me, and the breath came into them, and they lived, and stood up on their feet, an exceedingly great army.

11 Then he said to me, Son of man, these bones are the whole house of Israel: behold, they say, Our bones are dried up, and our hope is lost; we are clean cut off. 12 Therefore prophesy, and tell them, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I will open your graves, and cause you to come up out of your graves, my people; and I will bring you into the land of Israel. 13 You shall know that I am Yahweh, when I have opened your graves, and caused you to come up out of your graves, my people. 14 I will put my Spirit in you, and you shall live, and I will place you in your own land: and you shall know that I, Yahweh, have spoken it and performed it, says Yahweh.

15 Yahweh’s word came again to me, saying, 16 You, son of man, take one stick, and write on it, For Judah, and for the children of Israel his companions: then take another stick, and write on it, For Joseph, the stick of Ephraim, and for all the house of Israel his companions: 17 and join them for you to one another into one stick, that they may become one in your hand.

18 When the children of your people shall speak to you, saying, Will you not show us what you mean by these? 19 tell them, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I will take the stick of Joseph, which is in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel his companions; and I will put them with it, with the stick of Judah, and make them one stick, and they shall be one in my hand. 20 The sticks whereon you write shall be in your hand before their eyes. 21 Say to them, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I will take the children of Israel from among the nations, where they are gone, and will gather them on every side, and bring them into their own land: 22 and I will make them one nation in the land, on the mountains of Israel; and one king shall be king to them all; and they shall be no more two nations, neither shall they be divided into two kingdoms any more at all; 23 neither shall they defile themselves any more with their idols, nor with their detestable things, nor with any of their transgressions; but I will save them out of all their dwelling places, in which they have sinned, and will cleanse them: so shall they be my people, and I will be their God.

24 My servant David shall be king over them; and they all shall have one shepherd: they shall also walk in my ordinances, and observe my statutes, and do them. 25 They shall dwell in the land that I have given to Jacob my servant, in which your fathers lived; and they shall dwell therein, they, and their children, and their children’s children, forever: and David my servant shall be their prince for ever. 26 Moreover I will make a covenant of peace with them; it shall be an everlasting covenant with them; and I will place them, and multiply them, and will set my sanctuary among them forever more. 27 My tent also shall be with them; and I will be their God, and they shall be my people. 28 The nations shall know that I am Yahweh who sanctifies Israel, when my sanctuary shall be among them forever more.

Ezekiel 38

1 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 2 Son of man, set your face toward Gog, of the land of Magog, the prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal, and prophesy against him, 3 and say, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I am against you, Gog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal: 4 and I will turn you around, and put hooks into your jaws, and I will bring you out, with all your army, horses and horsemen, all of them clothed in full armor, a great company with buckler and shield, all of them handling swords; 5 Persia, Cush, and Put with them, all of them with shield and helmet; 6 Gomer, and all his hordes; the house of Togarmah in the uttermost parts of the north, and all his hordes; even many peoples with you.

7 Be prepared, yes, prepare yourself, you, and all your companies who are assembled to you, and be a guard to them. 8 After many days you shall be visited: in the latter years you shall come into the land that is brought back from the sword, that is gathered out of many peoples, on the mountains of Israel, which have been a continual waste; but it is brought out of the peoples, and they shall dwell securely, all of them. 9 You shall ascend, you shall come like a storm, you shall be like a cloud to cover the land, you, and all your hordes, and many peoples with you.

10 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: It shall happen in that day, that things shall come into your mind, and you shall devise an evil device: 11 and you shall say, I will go up to the land of unwalled villages; I will go to those who are at rest, who dwell securely, all of them dwelling without walls, and having neither bars nor gates; 12 to take the plunder and to take the prey; to turn your hand against the waste places that are inhabited, and against the people who are gathered out of the nations, who have gotten livestock and goods, who dwell in the middle of the earth. 13 Sheba, and Dedan, and the merchants of Tarshish, with all the young lions of it, shall tell you, Have you come to take the plunder? have you assembled your company to take the prey? to carry away silver and gold, to take away livestock and goods, to take great plunder?

14 Therefore, son of man, prophesy, and tell Gog, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: In that day when my people Israel dwells securely, shall you not know it? 15 You shall come from your place out of the uttermost parts of the north, you, and many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great company and a mighty army; 16 and you shall come up against my people Israel, as a cloud to cover the land: it shall happen in the latter days, that I will bring you against my land, that the nations may know me, when I shall be sanctified in you, Gog, before their eyes.

17 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Are you he of whom I spoke in old time by my servants the prophets of Israel, who prophesied in those days for years that I would bring you against them? 18 It shall happen in that day, when Gog shall come against the land of Israel, says the Lord Yahweh, that my wrath shall come up into my nostrils. 19 For in my jealousy and in the fire of my wrath I have spoken, Surely in that day there shall be a great shaking in the land of Israel; 20 so that the fish of the sea, and the birds of the sky, and the animals of the field, and all creeping things who creep on the earth, and all the men who are on the surface of the earth, shall shake at my presence, and the mountains shall be thrown down, and the steep places shall fall, and every wall shall fall to the ground. 21 I will call for a sword against him to all my mountains, says the Lord Yahweh: every man’s sword shall be against his brother. 22 With pestilence and with blood will I enter into judgment with him; and I will rain on him, and on his hordes, and on the many peoples who are with him, an overflowing shower, and great hailstones, fire, and sulfur. 23 I will magnify myself, and sanctify myself, and I will make myself known in the eyes of many nations; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

Ezekiel 39

1 You, son of man, prophesy against Gog, and say, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Behold, I am against you, Gog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal: 2 and I will turn you around, and will lead you on, and will cause you to come up from the uttermost parts of the north; and I will bring you on the mountains of Israel; 3 and I will strike your bow out of your left hand, and will cause your arrows to fall out of your right hand. 4 You shall fall on the mountains of Israel, you, and all your hordes, and the peoples who are with you: I will give you to the ravenous birds of every sort, and to the animals of the field to be devoured. 5 You shall fall on the open field; for I have spoken it, says the Lord Yahweh. 6 I will send a fire on Magog, and on those who dwell securely in the islands; and they shall know that I am Yahweh.

7 My holy name will I make known among my people Israel; neither will I allow my holy name to be profaned any more: and the nations shall know that I am Yahweh, the Holy One in Israel. 8 Behold, it comes, and it shall be done, says the Lord Yahweh; this is the day about which I have spoken.

9 Those who dwell in the cities of Israel shall go out, and shall make fires of the weapons and burn them, both the shields and the bucklers, the bows and the arrows, and the war clubs, and the spears, and they shall make fires of them seven years; 10 so that they shall take no wood out of the field, neither cut down any out of the forests; for they shall make fires of the weapons; and they shall plunder those who plundered them, and rob those who robbed them, says the Lord Yahweh.

11 It shall happen in that day, that I will give to Gog a place for burial in Israel, the valley of those who pass through on the east of the sea; and it shall stop those who pass through: and there shall they bury Gog and all his multitude; and they shall call it The valley of Hamon Gog.

12 Seven months shall the house of Israel be burying them, that they may cleanse the land. 13 Yes, all the people of the land shall bury them; and it shall be to them a renown in the day that I shall be glorified, says the Lord Yahweh.

14 They shall set apart men of continual employment, who shall pass through the land, and, with those who pass through, those who bury those who remain on the surface of the land, to cleanse it: after the end of seven months shall they search. 15 Those who pass through the land shall pass through; and when any sees a man’s bone, then shall he set up a sign by it, until the undertakers have buried it in the valley of Hamon Gog. 16 Hamonah shall also be the name of a city. Thus shall they cleanse the land.

17 You, son of man, thus says the Lord Yahweh: Speak to the birds of every sort, and to every animal of the field, Assemble yourselves, and come; gather yourselves on every side to my sacrifice that I do sacrifice for you, even a great sacrifice on the mountains of Israel, that you may eat meat and drink blood. 18 You shall eat the flesh of the mighty, and drink the blood of the princes of the earth, of rams, of lambs, and of goats, of bulls, all of them fatlings of Bashan. 19 You shall eat fat until you be full, and drink blood until you are drunk, of my sacrifice which I have sacrificed for you. 20 You shall be filled at my table with horses and chariots, with mighty men, and with all men of war, says the Lord Yahweh.

21 I will set my glory among the nations; and all the nations shall see my judgment that I have executed, and my hand that I have laid on them. 22 So the house of Israel shall know that I am Yahweh their God, from that day and forward. 23 The nations shall know that the house of Israel went into captivity for their iniquity; because they trespassed against me, and I hid my face from them: so I gave them into the hand of their adversaries, and they fell all of them by the sword. 24 According to their uncleanness and according to their transgressions did I to them; and I hid my face from them.

25 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh: Now will I bring back the captivity of Jacob, and have mercy on the whole house of Israel; and I will be jealous for my holy name. 26 They shall bear their shame, and all their trespasses by which they have trespassed against me, when they shall dwell securely in their land, and no one shall make them afraid; 27 when I have brought them back from the peoples, and gathered them out of their enemies’ lands, and am sanctified in them in the sight of many nations. 28 They shall know that I am Yahweh their God, in that I caused them to go into captivity among the nations, and have gathered them to their own land; and I will leave none of them any more there; 29 neither will I hide my face any more from them; for I have poured out my Spirit on the house of Israel, says the Lord Yahweh.

Ezekiel 40

1 In the twenty-fifth year of our captivity, in the beginning of the year, in the tenth day of the month, in the fourteenth year after that the city was struck, in the same day, Yahweh’s hand was on me, and he brought me there. 2 In the visions of God brought he me into the land of Israel, and set me down on a very high mountain, whereon was as it were the frame of a city on the south. 3 He brought me there; and, behold, there was a man, whose appearance was like the appearance of brass, with a line of flax in his hand, and a measuring reed; and he stood in the gate. 4 The man said to me, Son of man, see with your eyes, and hear with your ears, and set your heart on all that I shall show you; for, to the intent that I may show them to you, you are brought here: declare all that you see to the house of Israel.

5 Behold, a wall on the outside of the house all around, and in the man’s hand a measuring reed six cubits[*] long, of a cubit and a hand width each: so he measured the thickness of the building, one reed; and the height, one reed.

6 Then came he to the gate which looks toward the east, and went up its steps: and he measured the threshold of the gate, one reed wide; and the other threshold, one reed wide. 7 Every lodge was one reed long, and one reed wide; and between the lodges was five cubits; and the threshold of the gate by the porch of the gate toward the house was one reed.

8 He measured also the porch of the gate toward the house, one reed. 9 Then measured he the porch of the gate, eight cubits; and its posts, two cubits; and the porch of the gate was toward the house.

10 The lodges of the gate eastward were three on this side, and three on that side; they three were of one measure: and the posts had one measure on this side and on that side. 11 He measured the width of the opening of the gate, ten cubits; and the length of the gate, thirteen cubits; 12 and a border before the lodges, one cubit on this side, and a border, one cubit on that side; and the lodges, six cubits on this side, and six cubits on that side. 13 He measured the gate from the roof of the one lodge to the roof of the other, a width of twenty-five cubits; door against door. 14 He made also posts, sixty cubits; and the court reached to the posts, around the gate. 15 From the forefront of the gate at the entrance to the forefront of the inner porch of the gate were fifty cubits. 16 There were closed windows to the lodges, and to their posts within the gate all around, and likewise to the arches; and windows were around inward; and on each post were palm trees.

17 Then brought he me into the outer court; and behold, there were rooms and a pavement, made for the court all around: thirty rooms were on the pavement. 18 The pavement was by the side of the gates, answerable to the length of the gates, even the lower pavement. 19 Then he measured the width from the forefront of the lower gate to the forefront of the inner court outside, one hundred cubits, both on the east and on the north.

20 The gate of the outer court whose prospect is toward the north, he measured its length and its width. 21 The lodges of it were three on this side and three on that side; and its posts and its arches were after the measure of the first gate: its length was fifty cubits, and the width twenty-five cubits. 22 The windows of it, and its arches, and the palm trees of it, were after the measure of the gate whose prospect is toward the east; and they went up to it by seven steps; and its arches were before them. 23 There was a gate to the inner court facing the other gate, on the north and on the east; and he measured from gate to gate one hundred cubits.

24 He led me toward the south; and behold, a gate toward the south: and he measured its posts and its arches according to these measurements. 25 There were windows in it and in its arches all around, like those windows: the length was fifty cubits, and the width twenty-five cubits. 26 There were seven steps to go up to it, and its arches were before them; and it had palm trees, one on this side, and another on that side, on its posts. 27 There was a gate to the inner court toward the south: and he measured from gate to gate toward the south a hundred cubits.

28 Then he brought me to the inner court by the south gate: and he measured the south gate according to these measurements; 29 and its lodges, and its posts, and its arches, according to these measurements: and there were windows in it and in its arches all around; it was fifty cubits long, and twenty-five cubits wide. 30 There were arches all around, twenty-five cubits long, and five cubits wide. 31 The arches of it were toward the outer court; and palm trees were on its posts: and the ascent to it had eight steps.

32 He brought me into the inner court toward the east: and he measured the gate according to these measurements; 33 and its lodges, and its posts, and its arches, according to these measurements: and there were windows therein and in its arches all around; it was fifty cubits long, and twenty-five cubits wide. 34 The arches of it were toward the outer court; and palm trees were on its posts, on this side, and on that side: and the ascent to it had eight steps.

35 He brought me to the north gate: and he measured it according to these measurements; 36 its lodges, its posts, and its arches: and there were windows therein all around; the length was fifty cubits, and the width twenty-five cubits. 37 The posts of it were toward the outer court; and palm trees were on its posts, on this side, and on that side: and the ascent to it had eight steps.

38 A room with its door was by the posts at the gates; there they washed the burnt offering. 39 In the porch of the gate were two tables on this side, and two tables on that side, on which to kill the burnt offering, the sin offering, and the trespass offering. 40 On the one side outside, as one goes up to the entry of the gate toward the north, were two tables; and on the other side, which belonged to the porch of the gate, were two tables. 41 Four tables were on this side, and four tables on that side, by the side of the gate; eight tables, whereupon they killed the sacrifices. 42 There were four tables for the burnt offering, of cut stone, a cubit and a half long, and a cubit and a half wide, and one cubit high; whereupon they laid the instruments with which they killed the burnt offering and the sacrifice. 43 The hooks, a hand width long, were fastened within all around: and on the tables was the meat of the offering.

44 Outside of the inner gate were rooms for the singers in the inner court, which was at the side of the north gate; and their prospect was toward the south; one at the side of the east gate having the prospect toward the north. 45 He said to me, This room, whose prospect is toward the south, is for the priests, the keepers of the duty of the house; 46 and the room whose prospect is toward the north is for the priests, the keepers of the duty of the altar: these are the sons of Zadok, who from among the sons of Levi come near to Yahweh to minister to him. 47 He measured the court, one hundred cubits long, and a hundred cubits wide, square; and the altar was before the house.

48 Then he brought me to the porch of the house, and measured each post of the porch, five cubits on this side, and five cubits on that side: and the width of the gate was three cubits on this side, and three cubits on that side. 49 The length of the porch was twenty cubits, and the width eleven cubits; even by the steps by which they went up to it: and there were pillars by the posts, one on this side, and another on that side.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Ezekiel 41

1 He brought me to the temple, and measured the posts, six cubits wide on the one side, and six cubits wide on the other side, which was the width of the tent. 2 The width of the entrance was ten cubits;[*] and the sides of the entrance were five cubits on the one side, and five cubits on the other side: and he measured its length, forty cubits, and the width, twenty cubits.

3 Then went he inward, and measured each post of the entrance, two cubits; and the entrance, six cubits; and the width of the entrance, seven cubits. 4 He measured its length, twenty cubits, and the width, twenty cubits, before the temple: and he said to me, This is the most holy place.

5 Then he measured the wall of the house, six cubits; and the width of every side room, four cubits, all around the house on every side. 6 The side rooms were in three stories, one over another, and thirty in order; and they entered into the wall which belonged to the house for the side rooms all around, that they might be supported, and not penetrate the wall of the house. 7 The side rooms were wider on the higher levels, because the walls were narrower at the higher levels. Therefore the width of the house increased upward; and so one went up from the lowest level to the highest through the middle level.

8 I saw also that the house had a raised base all around: the foundations of the side rooms were a full reed of six great cubits. 9 The thickness of the wall, which was for the side rooms, on the outside, was five cubits: and that which was left was the place of the side rooms that belonged to the house. 10 Between the rooms was a width of twenty cubits around the house on every side. 11 The doors of the side rooms were toward an open area that was left, one door toward the north, and another door toward the south. The width of the open area was five cubits all around.

12 The building that was before the separate place at the side toward the west was seventy cubits wide; and the wall of the building was five cubits thick all around, and its length ninety cubits.

13 So he measured the house, one hundred cubits long; and the separate place, and the building, with its walls, one hundred cubits long; 14 also the width of the face of the house, and of the separate place toward the east, one hundred cubits.

15 He measured the length of the building before the separate place which was at its back, and its galleries on the one side and on the other side, one hundred cubits; and the inner temple, and the porches of the court; 16 the thresholds, and the closed windows, and the galleries around on their three stories, over against the threshold, with wood ceilings all around, and from the ground up to the windows, (now the windows were covered), 17 to the space above the door, even to the inner house, and outside, and by all the wall all around inside and outside, by measure. 18 It was made with cherubim and palm trees; and a palm tree was between cherub and cherub, and every cherub had two faces; 19 so that there was the face of a man toward the palm tree on the one side, and the face of a young lion toward the palm tree on the other side. It was made like this through all the house all around: 20 from the ground to above the door were cherubim and palm trees made: thus was the wall of the temple.

21 As for the temple, the door posts were squared; and as for the face of the sanctuary, its appearance was as the appearance of the temple. 22 The altar was of wood, three cubits high, and its length two cubits; and its corners, and its length, and its walls, were of wood: and he said to me, This is the table that is before Yahweh. 23 The temple and the sanctuary had two doors. 24 The doors had two leaves each, two turning leaves: two for the one door, and two leaves for the other. 25 There were made on them, on the doors of the temple, cherubim and palm trees, like as were made on the walls; and there was a threshold of wood on the face of the porch outside. 26 There were closed windows and palm trees on the one side and on the other side, on the sides of the porch: thus were the side rooms of the house, and the thresholds.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Ezekiel 42

1 Then he brought me out into the outer court, the way toward the north: and he brought me into the room that was over against the separate place, and which was over against the building toward the north. 2 Before the length of one hundred cubits[*] was the north door, and the width was fifty cubits. 3 Over against the twenty cubits which belonged to the inner court, and over against the pavement which belonged to the outer court, was gallery against gallery in the third floor. 4 Before the rooms was a walk of ten cubits’ width inward, a way of one cubit; and their doors were toward the north. 5 Now the upper rooms were shorter; for the galleries took away from these, more than from the lower and the middle, in the building. 6 For they were in three stories, and they didn’t have pillars as the pillars of the courts: therefore the uppermost was set back more than the lowest and the middle from the ground. 7 The wall that was outside by the side of the rooms, toward the outer court before the rooms, its length was fifty cubits. 8 For the length of the rooms that were in the outer court was fifty cubits: and behold, before the temple were one hundred cubits. 9 From under these rooms was the entry on the east side, as one goes into them from the outer court.

10 In the thickness of the wall of the court toward the east, before the separate place, and before the building, there were rooms. 11 The way before them was like the appearance of the rooms which were toward the north; according to their length so was their width: and all their exits were both according to their fashions, and according to their doors. 12 According to the doors of the rooms that were toward the south was a door at the head of the way, even the way directly before the wall toward the east, as one enters into them.

13 Then he said to me, The north rooms and the south rooms, which are before the separate place, they are the holy rooms, where the priests who are near to Yahweh shall eat the most holy things: there shall they lay the most holy things, and the meal offering, and the sin offering, and the trespass offering; for the place is holy. 14 When the priests enter in, then shall they not go out of the holy place into the outer court, but there they shall lay their garments in which they minister; for they are holy: and they shall put on other garments, and shall approach to that which is for the people.

15 Now when he had finished measuring the inner house, he brought me out by the way of the gate whose prospect is toward the east, and measured it all around. 16 He measured on the east side with the measuring reed five hundred reeds, with the measuring reed all around. 17 He measured on the north side five hundred reeds with the measuring reed all around. 18 He measured on the south side five hundred reeds with the measuring reed. 19 He turned about to the west side, and measured five hundred reeds with the measuring reed. 20 He measured it on the four sides: it had a wall around it, the length five hundred, and the width five hundred, to make a separation between that which was holy and that which was common.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Ezekiel 43

1 Afterward he brought me to the gate, even the gate that looks toward the east. 2 Behold, the glory of the God of Israel came from the way of the east: and his voice was like the sound of many waters; and the earth shined with his glory. 3 It was according to the appearance of the vision which I saw, even according to the vision that I saw when I came to destroy the city; and the visions were like the vision that I saw by the river Chebar; and I fell on my face. 4 Yahweh’s glory came into the house by the way of the gate whose prospect is toward the east. 5 The Spirit took me up, and brought me into the inner court; and behold, Yahweh’s glory filled the house.

6 I heard one speaking to me out of the house; and a man stood by me. 7 He said to me, Son of man, this is the place of my throne, and the place of the soles of my feet, where I will dwell among the children of Israel forever. The house of Israel shall no more defile my holy name, neither they, nor their kings, by their prostitution, and by the dead bodies of their kings in their high places; 8 in their setting of their threshold by my threshold, and their door post beside my door post, and there was a wall between me and them; and they have defiled my holy name by their abominations which they have committed: therefore I have consumed them in my anger. 9 Now let them put away their prostitution, and the dead bodies of their kings, far from me; and I will dwell among them forever.

10 You, son of man, show the house to the house of Israel, that they may be ashamed of their iniquities; and let them measure the pattern. 11 If they be ashamed of all that they have done, make known to them the form of the house, and its fashion, and its exits, and its entrances, and all its forms, and all its ordinances, and all its forms, and all its laws; and write it in their sight; that they may keep the whole form of it, and all its ordinances, and do them.

12 This is the law of the house: on the top of the mountain the whole limit around it shall be most holy. Behold, this is the law of the house.

13 These are the measurements of the altar by cubits (the cubit[*] is a cubit and a hand width): the bottom shall be a cubit, and the width a cubit, and its border around its edge a span;[*] and this shall be the base of the altar. 14 From the bottom on the ground to the lower ledge shall be two cubits, and the width one cubit; and from the lesser ledge to the greater ledge shall be four cubits, and the width a cubit. 15 The upper altar shall be four cubits; and from the altar hearth and upward there shall be four horns. 16 The altar hearth shall be twelve cubits long by twelve wide, square in its four sides. 17 The ledge shall be fourteen cubits long by fourteen wide in its four sides; and the border about it shall be half a cubit; and its bottom shall be a cubit around; and its steps shall look toward the east.

18 He said to me, Son of man, thus says the Lord Yahweh: These are the ordinances of the altar in the day when they shall make it, to offer burnt offerings on it, and to sprinkle blood on it. 19 You shall give to the priests the Levites who are of the offspring[*] of Zadok, who are near to me, to minister to me, says the Lord Yahweh, a young bull for a sin offering. 20 You shall take of its blood, and put it on the four horns of it, and on the four corners of the ledge, and on the border all around: thus you shall cleanse it and make atonement for it. 21 You shall also take the bull of the sin offering, and it shall be burned in the appointed place of the house, outside of the sanctuary.

22 On the second day you shall offer a male goat without defect for a sin offering; and they shall cleanse the altar, as they cleansed it with the bull. 23 When you have finished cleansing it, you shall offer a young bull without defect, and a ram out of the flock without defect. 24 You shall bring them near to Yahweh, and the priests shall cast salt on them, and they shall offer them up for a burnt offering to Yahweh.

25 Seven days you shall prepare every day a goat for a sin offering: they shall also prepare a young bull, and a ram out of the flock, without defect. 26 Seven days shall they make atonement for the altar and purify it; so shall they consecrate it. 27 When they have accomplished the days, it shall be that on the eighth day, and forward, the priests shall make your burnt offerings on the altar, and your peace offerings; and I will accept you, says the Lord Yahweh.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

A span is the length from the tip of a man’s thumb to the tip of his little finger when his hand is stretched out (about half a cubit, or 9 inches, or 22.8 cm.)

or, seed

Ezekiel 44

1 Then he brought me back by the way of the outer gate of the sanctuary, which looks toward the east; and it was shut. 2 Yahweh said to me, This gate shall be shut; it shall not be opened, neither shall any man enter in by it; for Yahweh, the God of Israel, has entered in by it; therefore it shall be shut. 3 As for the prince, he shall sit therein as prince to eat bread before Yahweh; he shall enter by the way of the porch of the gate, and shall go out by the way of the same.

4 Then he brought me by the way of the north gate before the house; and I looked, and behold, Yahweh’s glory filled Yahweh’s house: and I fell on my face.

5 Yahweh said to me, Son of man, mark well, and see with your eyes, and hear with your ears all that I tell you concerning all the ordinances of Yahweh’s house, and all its laws; and mark well the entrance of the house, with every exit of the sanctuary. 6 You shall tell the rebellious, even to the house of Israel, Thus says the Lord Yahweh: you house of Israel, let it suffice you of all your abominations, 7 in that you have brought in foreigners, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, to be in my sanctuary, to profane it, even my house, when you offer my bread, the fat and the blood, and they have broken my covenant, to add to all your abominations. 8 You have not performed the duty of my holy things; but you have set performers of my duty in my sanctuary for yourselves. 9 Thus says the Lord Yahweh, No foreigner, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, shall enter into my sanctuary, of any foreigners who are among the children of Israel.

10 But the Levites who went far from me, when Israel went astray, who went astray from me after their idols, they shall bear their iniquity. 11 Yet they shall be ministers in my sanctuary, having oversight at the gates of the house, and ministering in the house: they shall kill the burnt offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they shall stand before them to minister to them. 12 Because they ministered to them before their idols, and became a stumbling block of iniquity to the house of Israel; therefore I have lifted up my hand against them, says the Lord Yahweh, and they shall bear their iniquity. 13 They shall not come near to me, to execute the office of priest to me, nor to come near to any of my holy things, to the things that are most holy; but they shall bear their shame, and their abominations which they have committed. 14 Yet will I make them performers of the duty of the house, for all its service, and for all that shall be done therein.

15 But the priests the Levites, the sons of Zadok, who performed the duty of my sanctuary when the children of Israel went astray from me, they shall come near to me to minister to me; and they shall stand before me to offer to me the fat and the blood, says the Lord Yahweh: 16 they shall enter into my sanctuary, and they shall come near to my table, to minister to me, and they shall keep my instruction.

17 It shall be that, when they enter in at the gates of the inner court, they shall be clothed with linen garments; and no wool shall come on them, while they minister in the gates of the inner court, and within. 18 They shall have linen tires on their heads, and shall have linen breeches on their waists; they shall not clothe themselves with anything that makes them sweat. 19 When they go out into the outer court, even into the outer court to the people, they shall put off their garments in which they minister, and lay them in the holy rooms; and they shall put on other garments, that they not sanctify the people with their garments.

20 Neither shall they shave their heads, nor allow their locks to grow long; they shall only cut off the hair of their heads. 21 Neither shall any of the priests drink wine, when they enter into the inner court. 22 Neither shall they take for their wives a widow, nor her who is put away; but they shall take virgins of the offspring[*] of the house of Israel, or a widow who is the widow of a priest. 23 They shall teach my people the difference between the holy and the common, and cause them to discern between the unclean and the clean.

24 In a controversy they shall stand to judge; according to my ordinances shall they judge it: and they shall keep my laws and my statutes in all my appointed feasts; and they shall make my Sabbaths holy.

25 They shall go in to no dead person to defile themselves; but for father, or for mother, or for son, or for daughter, for brother, or for sister who has had no husband, they may defile themselves. 26 After he is cleansed, they shall reckon to him seven days. 27 In the day that he goes into the sanctuary, into the inner court, to minister in the sanctuary, he shall offer his sin offering, says the Lord Yahweh.

28 They shall have an inheritance: I am their inheritance; and you shall give them no possession in Israel; I am their possession. 29 They shall eat the meal offering, and the sin offering, and the trespass offering; and every devoted thing in Israel shall be theirs. 30 The first of all the first fruits of every thing, and every offering of everything, of all your offerings, shall be for the priest: you shall also give to the priests the first of your dough, to cause a blessing to rest on your house. 31 The priests shall not eat of anything that dies of itself, or is torn, whether it is bird or animal.

or, seed

Ezekiel 45

1 Moreover, when you shall divide by lot the land for inheritance, you shall offer an offering to Yahweh, a holy portion of the land; the length shall be the length of twenty-five thousand reeds, and the width shall be ten thousand: it shall be holy in all its border all around. 2 Of this there shall be a five hundred by five hundred square for the holy place; and fifty cubits[*] for its suburbs all around. 3 Of this measure you shall measure a length of twenty-five thousand, and a width of ten thousand: and in it shall be the sanctuary, which is most holy. 4 It is a holy portion of the land; it shall be for the priests, the ministers of the sanctuary, who come near to minister to Yahweh; and it shall be a place for their houses, and a holy place for the sanctuary. 5 Twenty-five thousand in length, and ten thousand in width, shall be to the Levites, the ministers of the house, for a possession to themselves, for twenty rooms.

6 You shall appoint the possession of the city five thousand wide, and twenty-five thousand long, side by side with the offering of the holy portion: it shall be for the whole house of Israel.

7 What is for the prince shall be on the one side and on the other side of the holy offering and of the possession of the city, in front of the holy offering and in front of the possession of the city, on the west side westward, and on the east side eastward; and in length answerable to one of the portions, from the west border to the east border. 8 In the land it shall be to him for a possession in Israel: and my princes shall no more oppress my people; but they shall give the land to the house of Israel according to their tribes.

9 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: Let it suffice you, princes of Israel: remove violence and plunder, and execute justice and righteousness; dispossessing my people, says the Lord Yahweh. 10 You shall have just balances, and a just ephah,[*] and a just bath. 11 The ephah and the bath shall be of one measure, that the bath may contain one tenth of a homer,[*] and the ephah one tenth of a homer: its measure shall be after the homer. 12 The shekel[*] shall be twenty gerahs.[*] Twenty shekels plus twenty-five shekels plus fifteen shekels shall be your mina.[*]

13 This is the offering that you shall offer: the sixth part of an ephah from a homer of wheat; and you shall give the sixth part of an ephah from a homer of barley; 14 and the set portion of oil, of the bath of oil, one tenth of a bath out of the cor, which is ten baths, even a homer; (for ten baths are a homer;)[*] 15 and one lamb of the flock, out of two hundred, from the well-watered pastures of Israel—for a meal offering, and for a burnt offering, and for peace offerings, to make atonement for them, says the Lord Yahweh. 16 All the people of the land shall give to this offering for the prince in Israel. 17 It shall be the prince’s part to give the burnt offerings, and the meal offerings, and the drink offerings, in the feasts, and on the new moons, and on the Sabbaths, in all the appointed feasts of the house of Israel: he shall prepare the sin offering, and the meal offering, and the burnt offering, and the peace offerings, to make atonement for the house of Israel.

18 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: In the first month, in the first day of the month, you shall take a young bull without defect; and you shall cleanse the sanctuary. 19 The priest shall take of the blood of the sin offering, and put it on the door posts of the house, and on the four corners of the ledge of the altar, and on the posts of the gate of the inner court. 20 So you shall do on the seventh day of the month for everyone who errs, and for him who is simple: so you shall make atonement for the house.

21 In the first month, in the fourteenth day of the month, you shall have the Passover, a feast of seven days; unleavened bread shall be eaten. 22 On that day shall the prince prepare for himself and for all the people of the land a bull for a sin offering. 23 The seven days of the feast he shall prepare a burnt offering to Yahweh, seven bulls and seven rams without defect daily the seven days; and a male goat daily for a sin offering. 24 He shall prepare a meal offering, an ephah[*] for a bull, and an ephah for a ram, and a hin of oil to an ephah.

25 In the seventh month, in the fifteenth day of the month, in the feast, shall he do the like the seven days; according to the sin offering, according to the burnt offering, and according to the meal offering, and according to the oil.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

1 homer is about 220 liters or 6 bushels

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

a gerah is about 0.5 grams or about 7.7 grains

A mina is about 600 grams or 1.3 U. S. pounds.

1 cor is the same as 1 homer in volume, and is about 211 liters, 55.9 gallons, or 6 bushels 1 bath is about 21.1 liters, 5.59 gallons, or 2.4 pecks.

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

Ezekiel 46

1 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: The gate of the inner court that looks toward the east shall be shut the six working days; but on the Sabbath day it shall be opened, and on the day of the new moon it shall be opened. 2 The prince shall enter by the way of the porch of the gate outside, and shall stand by the post of the gate; and the priests shall prepare his burnt offering and his peace offerings, and he shall worship at the threshold of the gate: then he shall go out; but the gate shall not be shut until the evening. 3 The people of the land shall worship at the door of that gate before Yahweh on the Sabbaths and on the new moons. 4 The burnt offering that the prince shall offer to Yahweh shall be on the Sabbath day six lambs without defect and a ram without defect; 5 and the meal offering shall be an ephah for the ram, and the meal offering for the lambs as he is able to give, and a hin of oil to an ephah.[*] 6 On the day of the new moon it shall be a young bull without defect, and six lambs, and a ram; they shall be without defect: 7 and he shall prepare a meal offering, an ephah for the bull, and an ephah for the ram, and for the lambs according as he is able, and a hin of oil to an ephah. 8 When the prince shall enter, he shall go in by the way of the porch of the gate, and he shall go out by its way.

9 But when the people of the land shall come before Yahweh in the appointed feasts, he who enters by the way of the north gate to worship shall go out by the way of the south gate; and he who enters by the way of the south gate shall go out by the way of the north gate: he shall not return by the way of the gate by which he came in, but shall go out straight before him. 10 The prince shall go in with them when they go in; and when they go out, he shall go out.

11 In the feasts and in the solemnities the meal offering shall be an ephah[*] for a bull, and an ephah for a ram, and for the lambs as he is able to give, and a hin of oil to an ephah. 12 When the prince shall prepare a freewill offering, a burnt offering or peace offerings as a freewill offering to Yahweh, one shall open for him the gate that looks toward the east; and he shall prepare his burnt offering and his peace offerings, as he does on the Sabbath day: then he shall go out; and after his going out one shall shut the gate.

13 You shall prepare a lamb a year old without defect for a burnt offering to Yahweh daily: morning by morning you shall prepare it. 14 You shall prepare a meal offering with it morning by morning, the sixth part of an ephah,[*] and the third part of a hin of oil, to moisten the fine flour; a meal offering to Yahweh continually by a perpetual ordinance. 15 Thus shall they prepare the lamb, and the meal offering, and the oil, morning by morning, for a continual burnt offering.

16 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: If the prince give a gift to any of his sons, it is his inheritance, it shall belong to his sons; it is their possession by inheritance. 17 But if he give of his inheritance a gift to one of his servants, it shall be his to the year of liberty; then it shall return to the prince; but as for his inheritance, it shall be for his sons. 18 Moreover the prince shall not take of the people’s inheritance, to thrust them out of their possession; he shall give inheritance to his sons out of his own possession, that my people not be scattered every man from his possession.

19 Then he brought me through the entry, which was at the side of the gate, into the holy rooms for the priests, which looked toward the north: and behold, there was a place on the hinder part westward. 20 He said to me, This is the place where the priests shall boil the trespass offering and the sin offering, and where they shall bake the meal offering; that they not bring them out into the outer court, to sanctify the people.

21 Then he brought me out into the outer court, and caused me to pass by the four corners of the court; and behold, in every corner of the court there was a court. 22 In the four corners of the court there were courts enclosed, forty cubits[*] long and thirty wide: these four in the corners were of one measure. 23 There was a wall around in them, around the four, and boiling places were made under the walls all around. 24 Then he said to me, These are the boiling houses, where the ministers of the house shall boil the sacrifice of the people.

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Ezekiel 47

1 He brought me back to the door of the house; and behold, waters issued out from under the threshold of the house eastward; (for the forefront of the house was toward the east;) and the waters came down from under, from the right side of the house, on the south of the altar. 2 Then he brought me out by the way of the gate northward, and led me round by the way outside to the outer gate, by the way of the gate that looks toward the east; and behold, there ran out waters on the right side.

3 When the man went out eastward with the line in his hand, he measured one thousand cubits,[*] and he caused me to pass through the waters, waters that were to the ankles. 4 Again he measured one thousand, and caused me to pass through the waters, waters that were to the knees. Again he measured one thousand, and caused me to pass through waters that were to the waist. 5 Afterward he measured one thousand; and it was a river that I could not pass through; for the waters were risen, waters to swim in, a river that could not be passed through. 6 He said to me, Son of man, have you seen?

Then he brought me, and caused me to return to the bank of the river. 7 Now when I had returned, behold, on the bank of the river were very many trees on the one side and on the other. 8 Then he said to me, These waters flow out toward the eastern region, and will go down into the Arabah; and they will go toward the sea; and flow into the sea which will be made to flow out; and the waters will be healed. 9 It shall happen, that every living creature which swarms, in every place where the rivers come, shall live; and there shall be a very great multitude of fish; for these waters have come there, and the waters of the sea shall be healed, and everything shall live wherever the river comes. 10 It shall happen, that fishermen shall stand by it: from En Gedi even to En Eglaim shall be a place for the spreading of nets; their fish shall be after their kinds, as the fish of the great sea, exceeding many. 11 But the miry places of it, and its marshes, shall not be healed; they shall be given up to salt. 12 By the river on its bank, on this side and on that side, shall grow every tree for food, whose leaf shall not wither, neither shall its fruit fail: it shall produce new fruit every month, because its waters issue out of the sanctuary; and its fruit shall be for food, and its leaf for healing.

13 Thus says the Lord Yahweh: This shall be the border, by which you shall divide the land for inheritance according to the twelve tribes of Israel: Joseph shall have two portions. 14 You shall inherit it, one as well as another; for I swore to give it to your fathers: and this land shall fall to you for inheritance.

15 This shall be the border of the land:

On the north side, from the great sea, by the way of Hethlon, to the entrance of Zedad; 16 Hamath, Berothah, Sibraim, which is between the border of Damascus and the border of Hamath; Hazer Hatticon, which is by the border of Hauran. 17 The border from the sea, shall be Hazar Enon at the border of Damascus; and on the north northward is the border of Hamath. This is the north side.

18 The east side, between Hauran and Damascus and Gilead, and the land of Israel, shall be the Jordan; from the north border to the east sea you shall measure. This is the east side.

19 The south side southward shall be from Tamar as far as the waters of Meriboth Kadesh, to the brook, to the great sea. This is the south side southward.

20 The west side shall be the great sea, from the south border as far as over against the entrance of Hamath. This is the west side.

21 So you shall divide this land to you according to the tribes of Israel. 22 It shall happen, that you shall divide it by lot for an inheritance to you and to the aliens who live among you, who shall father children among you; and they shall be to you as the native-born among the children of Israel; they shall have inheritance with you among the tribes of Israel. 23 It shall happen, that in what tribe the stranger lives, there you shall give him his inheritance, says the Lord Yahweh.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Ezekiel 48

1 Now these are the names of the tribes: From the north end, beside the way of Hethlon to the entrance of Hamath, Hazar Enan at the border of Damascus, northward beside Hamath, (and they shall have their sides east and west), Dan, one portion.

2 By the border of Dan, from the east side to the west side, Asher, one portion.

3 By the border of Asher, from the east side even to the west side, Naphtali, one portion.

4 By the border of Naphtali, from the east side to the west side, Manasseh, one portion.

5 By the border of Manasseh, from the east side to the west side, Ephraim, one portion.

6 By the border of Ephraim, from the east side even to the west side, Reuben, one portion.

7 By the border of Reuben, from the east side to the west side, Judah, one portion.

8 By the border of Judah, from the east side to the west side, shall be the offering which you shall offer, twenty-five thousand reeds in width, and in length as one of the portions, from the east side to the west side: and the sanctuary shall be in the middle of it.

9 The offering that you shall offer to Yahweh shall be twenty-five thousand reeds in length, and ten thousand in width. 10 For these, even for the priests, shall be the holy offering: toward the north twenty-five thousand in length, and toward the west ten thousand in width, and toward the east ten thousand in width, and toward the south twenty-five thousand in length: and the sanctuary of Yahweh shall be in the middle of it. 11 It shall be for the priests who are sanctified of the sons of Zadok, who have kept my instruction, who didn’t go astray when the children of Israel went astray, as the Levites went astray. 12 It shall be to them an offering from the offering of the land, a thing most holy, by the border of the Levites.

13 Answerable to the border of the priests, the Levites shall have twenty-five thousand in length, and ten thousand in width: all the length shall be twenty-five thousand, and the width ten thousand. 14 They shall sell none of it, nor exchange it, nor shall the first fruits of the land be alienated; for it is holy to Yahweh.

15 The five thousand that are left in the width, in front of the twenty-five thousand, shall be for common use, for the city, for dwelling and for suburbs; and the city shall be in the middle of it. 16 These shall be its measurements: the north side four thousand and five hundred, and the south side four thousand and five hundred, and on the east side four thousand and five hundred, and the west side four thousand and five hundred. 17 The city shall have suburbs: toward the north two hundred fifty, and toward the south two hundred fifty, and toward the east two hundred fifty, and toward the west two hundred fifty. 18 The remainder in the length, answerable to the holy offering, shall be ten thousand eastward, and ten thousand westward; and it shall be answerable to the holy offering; and its increase shall be for food to those who labor in the city. 19 Those who labor in the city, out of all the tribes of Israel, shall cultivate it. 20 All the offering shall be a square of twenty-five thousand by twenty-five thousand: you shall offer it as a holy offering, with the possession of the city.

21 The remainder shall be for the prince, on the one side and on the other of the holy offering and of the possession of the city; in front of the twenty-five thousand of the offering toward the east border, and westward in front of the twenty-five thousand toward the west border, answerable to the portions, it shall be for the prince: and the holy offering and the sanctuary of the house shall be in the middle of it. 22 Moreover from the possession of the Levites, and from the possession of the city, being in the middle of that which is the prince’s, between the border of Judah and the border of Benjamin, it shall be for the prince.

23 As for the rest of the tribes: from the east side to the west side, Benjamin, one portion.

24 By the border of Benjamin, from the east side to the west side, Simeon, one portion.

25 By the border of Simeon, from the east side to the west side, Issachar, one portion.

26 By the border of Issachar, from the east side to the west side, Zebulun, one portion.

27 By the border of Zebulun, from the east side to the west side, Gad, one portion.

28 By the border of Gad, at the south side southward, the border shall be even from Tamar to the waters of Meribath Kadesh, to the brook, to the great sea.

29 This is the land which you shall divide by lot to the tribes of Israel for inheritance, and these are their several portions, says the Lord Yahweh.

30 These are the exits of the city: On the north side four thousand and five hundred reeds by measure; 31 and the gates of the city shall be after the names of the tribes of Israel, three gates northward: the gate of Reuben, one; the gate of Judah, one; the gate of Levi, one.

32 At the east side four thousand and five hundred reeds, and three gates: even the gate of Joseph, one; the gate of Benjamin, one; the gate of Dan, one.

33 At the south side four thousand and five hundred reeds by measure, and three gates: the gate of Simeon, one; the gate of Issachar, one; the gate of Zebulun, one.

34 At the west side four thousand and five hundred reeds, with their three gates: the gate of Gad, one; the gate of Asher, one; the gate of Naphtali, one.

35 It shall be eighteen thousand reeds around: and the name of the city from that day shall be, Yahweh is there.

Daniel 1

1 In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah came Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon to Jerusalem, and besieged it. 2 The Lord[*] gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with part of the vessels of the house of God;[*] and he carried them into the land of Shinar to the house of his god: and he brought the vessels into the treasure house of his god.

3 The king spoke to Ashpenaz the master of his eunuchs, that he should bring in some of the children of Israel, even of the royal offspring[*] and of the nobles; 4 youths in whom was no defect, but well-favored, and skillful in all wisdom, and endowed with knowledge, and understanding science, and such as had ability to stand in the king’s palace; and that he should teach them the learning and the language of the Chaldeans. 5 The king appointed for them a daily portion of the king’s dainties, and of the wine which he drank, and that they should be nourished three years; that at its end they should stand before the king.

6 Now among these were, of the children of Judah, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. 7 The prince of the eunuchs gave names to them: to Daniel he gave the name Belteshazzar; and to Hananiah, Shadrach; and to Mishael, Meshach; and to Azariah, Abednego.

8 But Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself with the king’s dainties, nor with the wine which he drank: therefore he requested of the prince of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself. 9 Now God made Daniel to find kindness and compassion in the sight of the prince of the eunuchs. 10 The prince of the eunuchs said to Daniel, I fear my lord the king, who has appointed your food and your drink: for why should he see your faces worse looking than the youths who are of your own age? so would you endanger my head with the king.

11 Then Daniel said to the steward whom the prince of the eunuchs had appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: 12 Test your servants, I beg you, ten days; and let them give us vegetables to eat, and water to drink. 13 Then let our faces be looked on before you, and the face of the youths who eat of the king’s dainties; and as you see, deal with your servants. 14 So he listened to them in this matter, and proved them ten days.

15 At the end of ten days their faces appeared fairer, and they were fatter in flesh, than all the youths who ate of the king’s dainties. 16 So the steward took away their dainties, and the wine that they should drink, and gave them pulse.

17 Now as for these four youths, God gave them knowledge and skill in all learning and wisdom: and Daniel had understanding in all visions and dreams.

18 At the end of the days which the king had appointed for bringing them in, the prince of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar. 19 The king talked with them; and among them all was found no one like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: therefore stood they before the king. 20 In every matter of wisdom and understanding, concerning which the king inquired of them, he found them ten times better than all the magicians and enchanters who were in all his realm.

21 Daniel continued even to the first year of king Cyrus.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

or, seed

Daniel 2

1 In the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams; and his spirit was troubled, and his sleep went from him. 2 Then the king commanded to call the magicians, and the enchanters, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, to tell the king his dreams. So they came in and stood before the king. 3 The king said to them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit is troubled to know the dream.

4 Then spoke the Chaldeans to the king in the Syrian language, O king, live forever: tell your servants the dream, and we will show the interpretation.

5 The king answered the Chaldeans, The thing is gone from me: if you don’t make known to me the dream and its interpretation, you shall be cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made a dunghill. 6 But if you show the dream and its interpretation, you shall receive of me gifts and rewards and great honor: therefore show me the dream and its interpretation.

7 They answered the second time and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will show the interpretation.

8 The king answered, I know of a certainty that you would gain time, because you see the thing is gone from me. 9 But if you don’t make known to me the dream, there is but one law for you; for you have prepared lying and corrupt words to speak before me, until the time be changed: therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that you can show me its interpretation.

10 The Chaldeans answered before the king, and said, There is not a man on the earth who can show the king’s matter, because no king, lord, or ruler, has asked such a thing of any magician, or enchanter, or Chaldean. 11 It is a rare thing that the king requires, and there is no other who can show it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.

12 For this cause the king was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon. 13 So the decree went out, and the wise men were to be slain; and they sought Daniel and his companions to be slain.

14 Then Daniel returned answer with counsel and prudence to Arioch the captain of the king’s guard, who was gone out to kill the wise men of Babylon; 15 he answered Arioch the king’s captain, Why is the decree so urgent from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel. 16 Daniel went in, and desired of the king that he would appoint him a time, and he would show the king the interpretation.

17 Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions: 18 that they would desire mercies of the God of heaven concerning this secret; that Daniel and his companions should not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon. 19 Then was the secret revealed to Daniel in a vision of the night. Then Daniel blessed the God of heaven. 20 Daniel answered,

Blessed be the name of God forever and ever;

for wisdom and might are his.

21 He changes the times and the seasons;

he removes kings, and sets up kings;

he gives wisdom to the wise,

and knowledge to those who have understanding;

22 he reveals the deep and secret things;

he knows what is in the darkness,

and the light dwells with him.

23 I thank you, and praise you,

you God of my fathers,

who have given me wisdom and might,

and have now made known to me what we desired of you;

for you have made known to us the king’s matter.

24 Therefore Daniel went in to Arioch, whom the king had appointed to destroy the wise men of Babylon; he went and said thus to him: Don’t destroy the wise men of Babylon; bring me in before the king, and I will show to the king the interpretation.

25 Then Arioch brought in Daniel before the king in haste, and said thus to him, I have found a man of the children of the captivity of Judah, who will make known to the king the interpretation.

26 The king answered Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, Are you able to make known to me the dream which I have seen, and its interpretation?

27 Daniel answered before the king, and said, The secret which the king has demanded can neither wise men, enchanters, magicians, nor soothsayers, show to the king; 28 but there is a God in heaven who reveals secrets, and he has made known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Your dream, and the visions of your head on your bed, are these:

29 as for you, O king, your thoughts came on your bed, what should happen hereafter; and he who reveals secrets has made known to you what shall happen. 30 But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for any wisdom that I have more than any living, but to the intent that the interpretation may be made known to the king, and that you may know the thoughts of your heart.

31 You, O king, saw, and behold,[*] a great image. This image, which was mighty, and whose brightness was excellent, stood before you; and its aspect was awesome. 32 As for this image, its head was of fine gold, its breast and its arms of silver, its belly and its thighs of brass, 33 its legs of iron, its feet part of iron, and part of clay. 34 You saw until a stone was cut out without hands, which struck the image on its feet that were of iron and clay, and broke them in pieces. 35 Then was the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold, broken in pieces together, and became like the chaff of the summer threshing floors; and the wind carried them away, so that no place was found for them: and the stone that struck the image became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth.

36 This is the dream; and we will tell its interpretation before the king. 37 You, O king, are king of kings, to whom the God of heaven has given the kingdom, the power, and the strength, and the glory; 38 and wherever the children of men dwell, the animals of the field and the birds of the sky has he given into your hand, and has made you to rule over them all: you are the head of gold.

39 After you shall arise another kingdom inferior to you; and another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear rule over all the earth. 40 The fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron, because iron breaks in pieces and subdues all things; and as iron that crushes all these, shall it break in pieces and crush. 41 Whereas you saw the feet and toes, part of potters’ clay, and part of iron, it shall be a divided kingdom; but there shall be in it of the strength of the iron, because you saw the iron mixed with miry clay. 42 As the toes of the feet were part of iron, and part of clay, so the kingdom shall be partly strong, and partly broken. 43 Whereas you saw the iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mingle themselves with the seed of men; but they shall not cling to one another, even as iron does not mingle with clay.

44 In the days of those kings shall the God of heaven set up a kingdom which shall never be destroyed, nor shall its sovereignty be left to another people; but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it shall stand forever. 45 Because you saw that a stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it broke in pieces the iron, the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold; the great God has made known to the king what shall happen hereafter: and the dream is certain, and its interpretation sure.

46 Then the king Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face, and worshiped Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an offering and sweet odors to him. 47 The king answered to Daniel, and said, Of a truth your God is the God of gods, and the Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, since you have been able to reveal this secret.

48 Then the king made Daniel great, and gave him many great gifts, and made him to rule over the whole province of Babylon, and to be chief governor over all the wise men of Babylon. 49 Daniel requested of the king, and he appointed Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, over the affairs of the province of Babylon: but Daniel was in the gate of the king.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Daniel 3

1 Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was sixty cubits,[*] and its width six cubits: he set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon. 2 Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counselors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. 3 Then the satraps, the deputies, and the governors, the judges, the treasurers, the counselors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together to the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up.

4 Then the herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, peoples, nations, and languages, 5 that whenever you hear the sound of the horn, flute, zither, lyre, harp, pipe, and all kinds of music, you fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king has set up; 6 and whoever doesn’t fall down and worship shall the same hour be cast into the middle of a burning fiery furnace.

7 Therefore at that time, when all the peoples heard the sound of the horn, flute, zither, lyre, harp, pipe, and all kinds of music, all the peoples, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshiped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.

8 Therefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and brought accusation against the Jews. 9 They answered Nebuchadnezzar the king, O king, live for ever. 10 You, O king, have made a decree, that every man that shall hear the sound of the horn, flute, zither, lyre, harp, pipe, and all kinds of music, shall fall down and worship the golden image; 11 and whoever doesn’t fall down and worship shall be cast into the middle of a burning fiery furnace. 12 There are certain Jews whom you have appointed over the affairs of the province of Babylon: Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego; these men, O king, have not respected you. They don’t serve your gods, nor worship the golden image which you have set up.

13 Then Nebuchadnezzar in rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Then they brought these men before the king. 14 Nebuchadnezzar answered them, Is it on purpose, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, that you don’t serve my god, nor worship the golden image which I have set up? 15 Now if you are ready whenever you hear the sound of the horn, flute, zither, lyre, harp, pipe, and all kinds of music to fall down and worship the image which I have made, good: but if you don’t worship, you shall be cast the same hour into the middle of a burning fiery furnace; and who is that god that shall deliver you out of my hands?

16 Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered the king, Nebuchadnezzar, we have no need to answer you in this matter. 17 If it happens, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace; and he will deliver us out of your hand, O king. 18 But if not, let it be known to you, O king, that we will not serve your gods, nor worship the golden image which you have set up.

19 Then was Nebuchadnezzar full of fury, and the form of his appearance was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. He spoke, and commanded that they should heat the furnace seven times more than it was usually heated. 20 He commanded certain mighty men who were in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace. 21 Then these men were bound in their pants, their tunics, and their mantles, and their other clothes, and were cast into the middle of the burning fiery furnace. 22 Therefore because the king’s commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the flame of the fire killed those men who took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. 23 These three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell down bound into the middle of the burning fiery furnace.

24 Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonished, and rose up in haste: he spoke and said to his counselors, Didn’t we cast three men bound into the middle of the fire?

They answered the king, True, O king.

25 He answered, Look, I see four men loose, walking in the middle of the fire, and they are unharmed; and the aspect of the fourth is like a son of the gods.

26 Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the mouth of the burning fiery furnace: he spoke and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, you servants of the Most High God, come out, and come here.

Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego came out of the middle of the fire. 27 The satraps, the deputies, and the governors, and the king’s counselors, being gathered together, saw these men, that the fire had no power on their bodies, nor was the hair of their head singed, neither were their pants changed, nor had the smell of fire passed on them.

28 Nebuchadnezzar spoke and said, Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who has sent his angel, and delivered his servants who trusted in him, and have changed the king’s word, and have yielded their bodies, that they might not serve nor worship any god, except their own God. 29 Therefore I make a decree, that every people, nation, and language, which speak anything evil against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, shall be cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill; because there is no other god who is able to deliver after this sort.

30 Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego in the province of Babylon.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Daniel 4

1 Nebuchadnezzar the king,

to all the peoples, nations, and languages, who dwell in all the earth:

Peace be multiplied to you.

2 It has seemed good to me to show the signs and wonders that the Most High God has worked toward me.

3 How great are his signs!

and how mighty are his wonders!

his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom,

and his dominion is from generation to generation.

4 I, Nebuchadnezzar, was at rest in my house, and flourishing in my palace. 5 I saw a dream which made me afraid; and the thoughts on my bed and the visions of my head troubled me. 6 Therefore made I a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known to me the interpretation of the dream. 7 Then came in the magicians, the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers; and I told the dream before them; but they did not make known to me its interpretation. 8 But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name was Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods: and I told the dream before him, saying,

9 Belteshazzar, master of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in you, and no secret troubles you, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and its interpretation. 10 Thus were the visions of my head on my bed: I saw, and behold, a tree in the middle of the earth; and its height was great. 11 The tree grew, and was strong, and its height reached to the sky, and its sight to the end of all the earth. 12 The leaves of it were beautiful, and its fruit much, and in it was food for all: the animals of the field had shadow under it, and the birds of the sky lived in its branches, and all flesh was fed from it.

13 I saw in the visions of my head on my bed, and behold, a watcher and a holy one came down from the sky. 14 He cried aloud, and said thus, Cut down the tree, and cut off its branches, shake off its leaves, and scatter its fruit: let the animals get away from under it, and the fowls from its branches. 15 Nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of the sky:

and let his portion be with the animals in the grass of the earth: 16 let his heart be changed from man’s, and let an animal’s heart be given to him; and let seven times pass over him.

17 The sentence is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones; to the intent that the living may know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever he will, and sets up over it the lowest of men.

18 This dream I, king Nebuchadnezzar, have seen; and you, Belteshazzar, declare the interpretation, because all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known to me the interpretation; but you are able; for the spirit of the holy gods is in you.

19 Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was stricken mute for a while, and his thoughts troubled him. The king answered, Belteshazzar, don’t let the dream, or the interpretation, trouble you.

Belteshazzar answered, My lord, the dream be to those who hate you, and its interpretation to your adversaries. 20 The tree that you saw, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached to the sky, and its sight to all the earth; 21 whose leaves were beautiful, and its fruit much, and in it was food for all; under which the animals of the field lived, and on whose branches the birds of the sky had their habitation: 22 it is you, O king, that are grown and become strong; for your greatness is grown, and reaches to the sky, and your dominion to the end of the earth.

23 Whereas the king saw a watcher and a holy one coming down from the sky, and saying, Cut down the tree, and destroy it; nevertheless leave the stump of its roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field, and let it be wet with the dew of the sky: and let his portion be with the animals of the field, until seven times pass over him;

24 this is the interpretation, O king, and it is the decree of the Most High, which has come on my lord the king: 25 that you shall be driven from men, and your dwelling shall be with the animals of the field, and you shall be made to eat grass as oxen, and shall be wet with the dew of the sky, and seven times shall pass over you; until you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever he will. 26 Whereas they commanded to leave the stump of the roots of the tree; your kingdom shall be sure to you, after that you shall have known that the heavens do rule. 27 Therefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable to you, and break off your sins by righteousness, and your iniquities by showing mercy to the poor; if there may be a lengthening of your tranquility.

28 All this came on the king Nebuchadnezzar. 29 At the end of twelve months he was walking in the royal palace of Babylon. 30 The king spoke and said, Is not this great Babylon, which I have built for the royal dwelling place, by the might of my power and for the glory of my majesty?

31 While the word was in the king’s mouth, a voice came from the sky, saying, “O king Nebuchadnezzar, to you it is spoken: The kingdom has departed from you. 32 You shall be driven from men; and your dwelling shall be with the animals of the field. You shall be made to eat grass as oxen. Seven times shall pass over you, until you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men, and gives it to whomever he will.”

33 This was fulfilled the same hour on Nebuchadnezzar. He was driven from men, and ate grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of the sky, until his hair had grown like eagles’ feathers, and his nails like birds’ claws.

34 At the end of the days I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted up my eyes to heaven, and my understanding returned to me, and I blessed the Most High, and I praised and honored him who lives forever;

for his dominion is an everlasting dominion,

and his kingdom from generation to generation.

35 All the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing;

and he does according to his will in the army of heaven,

and among the inhabitants of the earth;

and no one can stop his hand,

or ask him, What are you doing?

36 At the same time my understanding returned to me; and for the glory of my kingdom, my majesty and brightness returned to me; and my counselors and my lords sought to me; and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent greatness was added to me. 37 Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and extol and honor the King of heaven; for all his works are truth, and his ways justice; and those who walk in pride he is able to abase.

Daniel 5

1 Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand. 2 Belshazzar, while he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which Nebuchadnezzar his father had taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem; that the king and his lords, his wives and his concubines, might drink from them. 3 Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of God’s house which was at Jerusalem; and the king and his lords, his wives and his concubines, drank from them. 4 They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone.

5 In the same hour, the fingers of a man’s hand came out and wrote near the lamp stand on the plaster of the wall of the king’s palace. The king saw the part of the hand that wrote. 6 Then the king’s face was changed in him, and his thoughts troubled him; and the joints of his thighs were loosened, and his knees struck one against another.

7 The king cried aloud to bring in the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. The king spoke and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whoever shall read this writing, and show me its interpretation, shall be clothed with purple, and have a chain of gold about his neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.

8 Then came in all the king’s wise men; but they could not read the writing, nor make known to the king the interpretation. 9 Then was king Belshazzar greatly troubled, and his face was changed in him, and his lords were perplexed.

10 The queen by reason of the words of the king and his lords came into the banquet house: the queen spoke and said, O king, live forever; don’t let your thoughts trouble you, nor let your face be changed. 11 There is a man in your kingdom, in whom is the spirit of the holy gods; and in the days of your father light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, were found in him; and the king Nebuchadnezzar your father, the king, your father, made him master of the magicians, enchanters, Chaldeans, and soothsayers; 12 because an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, interpreting of dreams, and showing of dark sentences, and dissolving of doubts, were found in the same Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar. Now let Daniel be called, and he will show the interpretation.

13 Then was Daniel brought in before the king. The king spoke and said to Daniel, Are you that Daniel, who are of the children of the captivity of Judah, whom the king my father brought out of Judah? 14 I have heard of you, that the spirit of the gods is in you, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom are found in you. 15 Now the wise men, the enchanters, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing, and make known to me its interpretation; but they could not show the interpretation of the thing. 16 But I have heard of you, that you can give interpretations, and dissolve doubts; now if you can read the writing, and make known to me its interpretation, you shall be clothed with purple, and have a chain of gold about your neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.

17 Then Daniel answered before the king, Let your gifts be to yourself, and give your rewards to another; nevertheless I will read the writing to the king, and make known to him the interpretation.

18 You, king, the Most High God gave Nebuchadnezzar your father the kingdom, and greatness, and glory, and majesty: 19 and because of the greatness that he gave him, all the peoples, nations, and languages trembled and feared before him: whom he would he killed, and whom he would he kept alive; and whom he would he raised up, and whom he would he put down. 20 But when his heart was lifted up, and his spirit was hardened so that he dealt proudly, he was deposed from his kingly throne, and they took his glory from him: 21 and he was driven from the sons of men, and his heart was made like the animals’, and his dwelling was with the wild donkeys; he was fed with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of the sky; until he knew that the Most High God rules in the kingdom of men, and that he sets up over it whomever he will.

22 You, his son, Belshazzar, have not humbled your heart, though you knew all this, 23 but have lifted up yourself against the Lord of heaven; and they have brought the vessels of his house before you, and you and your lords, your wives and your concubines, have drunk wine from them; and you have praised the gods of silver and gold, of brass, iron, wood, and stone, which don’t see, nor hear, nor know; and the God in whose hand your breath is, and whose are all your ways, you have not glorified. 24 Then was the part of the hand sent from before him, and this writing was inscribed.

25 This is the writing that was inscribed: MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN.

26 This is the interpretation of the thing:

MENE; God has counted your kingdom, and brought it to an end;

27 TEKEL; you are weighed in the balances, and are found wanting.

28 PERES; your kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and Persians.

29 Then commanded Belshazzar, and they clothed Daniel with purple, and put a chain of gold about his neck, and made proclamation concerning him, that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.

30 In that night Belshazzar the Chaldean King was slain. 31 Darius the Mede received the kingdom, being about sixty-two years old.

Daniel 6

1 It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom one hundred twenty satraps, who should be throughout the whole kingdom; 2 and over them three presidents, of whom Daniel was one; that these satraps might give account to them, and that the king should have no damage. 3 Then this Daniel was distinguished above the presidents and the satraps, because an excellent spirit was in him; and the king thought to set him over the whole realm. 4 Then the presidents and the satraps sought to find occasion against Daniel as touching the kingdom; but they could find no occasion nor fault, because he was faithful, neither was there any error or fault found in him. 5 Then these men said, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel, except we find it against him concerning the law of his God.

6 Then these presidents and satraps assembled together to the king, and said thus to him, King Darius, live forever. 7 All the presidents of the kingdom, the deputies and the satraps, the counselors and the governors, have consulted together to establish a royal statute, and to make a strong decree, that whoever shall ask a petition of any god or man for thirty days, except of you, O king, he shall be cast into the den of lions. 8 Now, O king, establish the decree, and sign the writing, that it not be changed, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which doesn’t alter. 9 Therefore king Darius signed the writing and the decree.

10 When Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went into his house (now his windows were open in his room toward Jerusalem) and he kneeled on his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he did before. 11 Then these men assembled together, and found Daniel making petition and supplication before his God. 12 Then they came near, and spoke before the king concerning the king’s decree: Haven’t you signed a decree that every man who makes a petition to any god or man within thirty days, except to you, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions?

The king answered, The thing is true, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which doesn’t alter.

13 Then answered they and said before the king, That Daniel, who is of the children of the captivity of Judah, doesn’t respect you, O king, nor the decree that you have signed, but makes his petition three times a day. 14 Then the king, when he heard these words, was very displeased, and set his heart on Daniel to deliver him; and he labored until the going down of the sun to rescue him.

15 Then these men assembled together to the king, and said to the king, Know, O king, that it is a law of the Medes and Persians, that no decree nor statute which the king establishes may be changed.

16 Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast him into the den of lions. The king spoke and said to Daniel, Your God whom you serve continually, he will deliver you.

17 A stone was brought, and laid on the mouth of the den; and the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords; that nothing might be changed concerning Daniel. 18 Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night fasting; neither were instruments of music brought before him: and his sleep fled from him.

19 Then the king arose very early in the morning, and went in haste to the den of lions. 20 When he came near to the den to Daniel, he cried with a lamentable voice; the king spoke and said to Daniel, Daniel, servant of the living God, is your God, whom you serve continually, able to deliver you from the lions?

21 Then Daniel said to the king, O king, live forever. 22 My God has sent his angel, and has shut the lions’ mouths, and they have not hurt me; because as before him innocence was found in me; and also before you, O king, I have done no hurt.

23 Then was the king exceeding glad, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no kind of harm was found on him, because he had trusted in his God.

24 The king commanded, and they brought those men who had accused Daniel, and they cast them into the den of lions, them, their children, and their wives; and the lions mauled them, and broke all their bones in pieces, before they came to the bottom of the den.

25 Then king Darius wrote to all the peoples, nations, and languages, who dwell in all the earth:

Peace be multiplied to you.

26 I make a decree, that in all the dominion of my kingdom men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel;

for he is the living God,

and steadfast forever,

His kingdom that which shall not be destroyed;

and his dominion shall be even to the end.

27 He delivers and rescues,

and he works signs and wonders in heaven and in earth,

who has delivered Daniel from the power of the lions.

28 So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of Cyrus the Persian.

Daniel 7

1 In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon Daniel had a dream and visions of his head on his bed: then he wrote the dream and told the sum of the matters.

2 Daniel spoke and said, I saw in my vision by night, and, behold, the four winds of the sky broke out on the great sea. 3 Four great animals came up from the sea, diverse one from another.

4 The first was like a lion, and had eagle’s wings: I saw until its wings were plucked, and it was lifted up from the earth, and made to stand on two feet as a man; and a man’s heart was given to it.

5 Behold, another animal, a second, like a bear; and it was raised up on one side, and three ribs were in its mouth between its teeth: and they said thus to it, Arise, devour much flesh.

6 After this I saw, and behold, another, like a leopard, which had on its back four wings of a bird; the animal had also four heads; and dominion was given to it.

7 After this I saw in the night visions, and, behold, a fourth animal, awesome and powerful, and strong exceedingly; and it had great iron teeth; it devoured and broke in pieces, and stamped the residue with its feet: and it was diverse from all the animals that were before it; and it had ten horns.

8 I considered the horns, and behold, there came up among them another horn, a little one, before which three of the first horns were plucked up by the roots: and behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of a man, and a mouth speaking great things.

9 I saw until thrones were placed,

and one who was ancient of days sat:

his clothing was white as snow,

and the hair of his head like pure wool;

his throne was fiery flames,

and its wheels burning fire.

10 A fiery stream issued and came out from before him:

thousands of thousands ministered to him,

and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him:

the judgment was set,

and the books were opened.

11 I saw at that time because of the voice of the great words which the horn spoke; I saw even until the animal was slain, and its body destroyed, and it was given to be burned with fire. 12 As for the rest of the animals, their dominion was taken away: yet their lives were prolonged for a season and a time.

13 I saw in the night visions, and behold, there came with the clouds of the sky one like a son of man, and he came even to the ancient of days, and they brought him near before him. 14 There was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, that all the peoples, nations, and languages should serve him: his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed.

15 As for me, Daniel, my spirit was grieved within my body, and the visions of my head troubled me. 16 I came near to one of those who stood by, and asked him the truth concerning all this.

So he told me, and made me know the interpretation of the things. 17 These great animals, which are four, are four kings, who shall arise out of the earth. 18 But the saints of the Most High shall receive the kingdom, and possess the kingdom forever, even forever and ever.

19 Then I desired to know the truth concerning the fourth animal, which was diverse from all of them, exceedingly terrible, whose teeth were of iron, and its nails of brass; which devoured, broke in pieces, and stamped the residue with its feet; 20 and concerning the ten horns that were on its head, and the other horn which came up, and before which three fell, even that horn that had eyes, and a mouth that spoke great things, whose look was more stout than its fellows. 21 I saw, and the same horn made war with the saints, and prevailed against them; 22 until the ancient of days came, and judgment was given to the saints of the Most High, and the time came that the saints possessed the kingdom.

23 Thus he said, The fourth animal shall be a fourth kingdom on earth, which shall be diverse from all the kingdoms, and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and break it in pieces. 24 As for the ten horns, out of this kingdom shall ten kings arise: and another shall arise after them; and he shall be diverse from the former, and he shall put down three kings. 25 He shall speak words against the Most High, and shall wear out the saints of the Most High; and he shall think to change the times and the law; and they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and half a time.

26 But the judgment shall be set, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume and to destroy it to the end. 27 The kingdom and the dominion, and the greatness of the kingdoms under the whole sky, shall be given to the people of the saints of the Most High: his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey him.

28 Here is the end of the matter. As for me, Daniel, my thoughts much troubled me, and my face was changed in me: but I kept the matter in my heart.

Daniel 8

1 In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared to me, even to me, Daniel, after that which appeared to me at the first. 2 I saw in the vision; now it was so, that when I saw, I was in the citadel of Susa, which is in the province of Elam; and I saw in the vision, and I was by the river Ulai. 3 Then I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns: and the two horns were high; but one was higher than the other, and the higher came up last. 4 I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward; and no animals could stand before him, neither was there any who could deliver out of his hand; but he did according to his will, and magnified himself.

5 As I was considering, behold, a male goat came from the west over the surface of the whole earth, and didn’t touch the ground: and the goat had a notable horn between his eyes. 6 He came to the ram that had the two horns, which I saw standing before the river, and ran on him in the fury of his power. 7 I saw him come close to the ram, and he was moved with anger against him, and struck the ram, and broke his two horns; and there was no power in the ram to stand before him; but he cast him down to the ground, and trampled on him; and there was no one who could deliver the ram out of his hand. 8 The male goat magnified himself exceedingly: and when he was strong, the great horn was broken; and instead of it there came up four notable horns toward the four winds of the sky.

9 Out of one of them came out a little horn, which grew exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the glorious land. 10 It grew great, even to the army of the sky; and some of the army and of the stars it cast down to the ground, and trampled on them. 11 Yes, it magnified itself, even to the prince of the army; and it took away from him the continual burnt offering, and the place of his sanctuary was cast down. 12 The army was given over to it together with the continual burnt offering through disobedience; and it cast down truth to the ground, and it did its pleasure and prospered.

13 Then I heard a holy one speaking; and another holy one said to that certain one who spoke, How long shall be the vision about the continual burnt offering, and the disobedience that makes desolate, to give both the sanctuary and the army to be trodden under foot?

14 He said to me, To two thousand and three hundred evenings and mornings; then shall the sanctuary be cleansed.

15 When I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, I sought to understand it; and behold, there stood before me as the appearance of a man. 16 I heard a man’s voice between the banks of the Ulai, which called, and said, Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision.

17 So he came near where I stood; and when he came, I was frightened, and fell on my face: but he said to me, Understand, son of man; for the vision belongs to the time of the end.

18 Now as he was speaking with me, I fell into a deep sleep with my face toward the ground; but he touched me, and set me upright.

19 He said, Behold, I will make you know what shall be in the latter time of the indignation; for it belongs to the appointed time of the end. 20 The ram which you saw, that had the two horns, they are the kings of Media and Persia. 21 The rough male goat is the king of Greece: and the great horn that is between his eyes is the first king. 22 As for that which was broken, in the place where four stood up, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not with his power.

23 In the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors have come to the full, a king of fierce face, and understanding dark sentences, shall stand up. 24 His power shall be mighty, but not by his own power; and he shall destroy wonderfully, and shall prosper in what he does; and he shall destroy the mighty ones and the holy people. 25 Through his policy he shall cause craft to prosper in his hand; and he shall magnify himself in his heart, and he shall destroy many in their security. He shall also stand up against the prince of princes; but he shall be broken without hand.

26 The vision of the evenings and mornings which has been told is true: but seal up the vision; for it belongs to many days to come.

27 I, Daniel, fainted, and was sick certain days; then I rose up, and did the king’s business: and I wondered at the vision, but no one understood it.

Daniel 9

1 In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the offspring[*] of the Medes, who was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans, 2 in the first year of his reign I, Daniel, understood by the books the number of the years about which Yahweh’s word[*] came to Jeremiah the prophet, for the accomplishing of the desolations of Jerusalem, even seventy years. 3 I set my face to the Lord God, to seek by prayer and petitions, with fasting and sackcloth and ashes.

4 I prayed to Yahweh my God, and made confession, and said,

Oh, Lord, the great and dreadful God, who keeps covenant and loving kindness with those who love him and keep his commandments, 5 we have sinned, and have dealt perversely, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even turning aside from your precepts and from your ordinances; 6 neither have we listened to your servants the prophets, who spoke in your name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land.

7 Lord, righteousness belongs to you, but to us confusion of face, as it is today; to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to all Israel, who are near, and who are far off, through all the countries where you have driven them, because of their trespass that they have trespassed against you. 8 Lord, to us belongs confusion of face, to our kings, to our princes, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against you. 9 To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgiveness; for we have rebelled against him; 10 neither have we obeyed Yahweh our God’s voice, to walk in his laws, which he set before us by his servants the prophets. 11 Yes, all Israel have transgressed your law, turning aside, that they should not obey your voice:

therefore the curse and the oath written in the law of Moses the servant of God has been poured out on us; for we have sinned against him. 12 He has confirmed his words, which he spoke against us, and against our judges who judged us, by bringing on us a great evil; for under the whole sky, such has not been done as has been done to Jerusalem. 13 As it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil has come on us: yet have we not entreated the favor of Yahweh our God, that we should turn from our iniquities, and have discernment in your truth. 14 Therefore has Yahweh watched over the evil, and brought it on us; for Yahweh our God is righteous in all his works which he does, and we have not obeyed his voice.

15 Now, Lord our God, who has brought your people out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and have gotten yourself renown, as it is today; we have sinned, we have done wickedly. 16 Lord, according to all your righteousness, let your anger and please let your wrath be turned away from your city Jerusalem, your holy mountain; because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and your people have become a reproach to all who are around us.

17 Now therefore, our God, listen to the prayer of your servant, and to his petitions, and cause your face to shine on your sanctuary that is desolate, for the Lord’s sake. 18 My God, turn your ear, and hear; open your eyes, and see our desolations, and the city which is called by your name: for we do not present our petitions before you for our righteousness, but for your great mercies’ sake. 19 Lord, hear; Lord, forgive; Lord, listen and do; don’t defer, for your own sake, my God, because your city and your people are called by your name.

20 While I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before Yahweh my God for the holy mountain of my God; 21 yes, while I was speaking in prayer, the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly swiftly, touched me about the time of the evening offering. 22 He instructed me, and talked with me, and said, Daniel, I have now come to give you wisdom and understanding. 23 At the beginning of your petitions the commandment went out, and I have come to tell you; for you are greatly beloved: therefore consider the matter, and understand the vision.

24 Seventy weeks are decreed on your people and on your holy city, to finish disobedience, and to make an end of sins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up vision and prophecy, and to anoint the most holy.

25 Know therefore and discern, that from the going out of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem to the Anointed One,[*] the prince, shall be seven weeks, and sixty-two weeks: it shall be built again, with street and moat, even in troubled times. 26 After the sixty-two weeks the Anointed One[*] shall be cut off, and shall have nothing: and the people of the prince who shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary; and its end shall be with a flood, and even to the end shall be war; desolations are determined. 27 He shall make a firm covenant with many for one week: and in the middle of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the offering to cease; and on the wing of abominations shall come one who makes desolate; and even to the full end, and that determined, shall wrath be poured out on the desolate.

or, seed

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Anointed One” can also be translated “Messiah” (same as “Christ”).

“Anointed One” can also be translated “Messiah” (same as “Christ”).

Daniel 10

1 In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed to Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and the thing was true, even a great warfare: and he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision.

2 In those days I, Daniel, was mourning three whole weeks. 3 I ate no pleasant bread, neither came meat nor wine into my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, until three whole weeks were fulfilled.

4 In the four and twentieth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel, 5 I lifted up my eyes, and looked, and behold, a man clothed in linen, whose thighs were adorned with pure gold of Uphaz: 6 his body also was like the beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as flaming torches, and his arms and his feet like burnished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude.

7 I, Daniel, alone saw the vision; for the men who were with me didn’t see the vision; but a great quaking fell on them, and they fled to hide themselves. 8 So I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me; for my comeliness was turned in me into corruption, and I retained no strength. 9 Yet heard I the voice of his words; and when I heard the voice of his words, then was I fallen into a deep sleep on my face, with my face toward the ground.

10 Behold, a hand touched me, which set me on my knees and on the palms of my hands. 11 He said to me, Daniel, you man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak to you, and stand upright; for am I now sent to you. When he had spoken this word to me, I stood trembling.

12 Then he said to me, Don’t be afraid, Daniel; for from the first day that you set your heart to understand, and to humble yourself before your God, your words were heard: and I have come for your words’ sake. 13 But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me twenty-one days; but, behold, Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me: and I remained there with the kings of Persia. 14 Now I have come to make you understand what shall happen to your people in the latter days; for the vision is yet for many days:

15 and when he had spoken to me according to these words, I set my face toward the ground, and was mute. 16 Behold, one in the likeness of the sons of men touched my lips: then I opened my mouth, and spoke and said to him who stood before me, my lord, by reason of the vision my sorrows are turned on me, and I retain no strength. 17 For how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? for as for me, immediately there remained no strength in me, neither was there breath left in me.

18 Then there touched me again one like the appearance of a man, and he strengthened me. 19 He said, “Greatly beloved man, don’t be afraid: peace be to you, be strong, yes, be strong.”

When he spoke to me, I was strengthened, and said, “Let my lord speak; for you have strengthened me.”

20 Then he said, “Do you know why I have come to you? Now I will return to fight with the prince of Persia. When I go out, behold, the prince of Greece shall come. 21 But I will tell you that which is inscribed in the writing of truth: and there is no one who holds with me against these, but Michael your prince.”

Daniel 11

1 “As for me, in the first year of Darius the Mede, I stood up to confirm and strengthen him.

2 Now will I show you the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia; and the fourth shall be far richer than they all: and when he has grown strong through his riches, he shall stir up all against the realm of Greece. 3 A mighty king shall stand up, who shall rule with great dominion, and do according to his will. 4 When he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken, and shall be divided toward the four winds of the sky, but not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion with which he ruled; for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even for others besides these.

5 The king of the south shall be strong, and one of his princes; and he shall be strong above him, and have dominion; his dominion shall be a great dominion. 6 At the end of years they shall join themselves together; and the daughter of the king of the south shall come to the king of the north to make an agreement: but she shall not retain the strength of her arm; neither shall he stand, nor his arm; but she shall be given up, and those who brought her, and he who became the father of her, and he who strengthened her in those times.

7 But out of a shoot from her roots shall one stand up in his place, who shall come to the army, and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them, and shall prevail. 8 Also their gods, with their molten images, and with their goodly vessels of silver and of gold, shall he carry captive into Egypt; and he shall refrain some years from the king of the north. 9 He shall come into the realm of the king of the south, but he shall return into his own land. 10 His sons shall war, and shall assemble a multitude of great forces, which shall come on, and overflow, and pass through; and they shall return and war, even to his fortress.

11 The king of the south shall be moved with anger, and shall come out and fight with him, even with the king of the north; and he shall send out a great multitude, and the multitude shall be given into his hand. 12 The multitude shall be lifted up, and his heart shall be exalted; and he shall cast down tens of thousands, but he shall not prevail. 13 The king of the north shall return, and shall send out a multitude greater than the former; and he shall come on at the end of the times, even of years, with a great army and with much substance.

14 In those times there shall many stand up against the king of the south: also the children of the violent among your people shall lift themselves up to establish the vision; but they shall fall. 15 So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mound, and take a well-fortified city: and the forces of the south shall not stand, neither his chosen people, neither shall there be any strength to stand. 16 But he who comes against him shall do according to his own will, and no one shall stand before him; and he shall stand in the glorious land, and in his hand shall be destruction. 17 He shall set his face to come with the strength of his whole kingdom, and with him equitable conditions; and he shall perform them: and he shall give him the daughter of women, to corrupt her; but she shall not stand, neither be for him. 18 After this shall he turn his face to the islands, and shall take many: but a prince shall cause the reproach offered by him to cease; yes, moreover, he shall cause his reproach to turn on him. 19 Then he shall turn his face toward the fortresses of his own land; but he shall stumble and fall, and shall not be found.

20 Then shall stand up in his place one who shall cause a tax collector to pass through the kingdom to maintain its glory; but within few days he shall be destroyed, neither in anger, nor in battle.

21 In his place shall stand up a contemptible person, to whom they had not given the honor of the kingdom: but he shall come in time of security, and shall obtain the kingdom by flatteries. 22 The overwhelming forces shall be overwhelmed from before him, and shall be broken; yes, also the prince of the covenant. 23 After the treaty made with him he shall work deceitfully; for he shall come up, and shall become strong, with a small people. 24 In time of security shall he come even on the fattest places of the province; and he shall do that which his fathers have not done, nor his fathers’ fathers; he shall scatter among them prey, and plunder, and substance: yes, he shall devise his devices against the strongholds, even for a time.

25 He shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the south with a great army; and the king of the south shall war in battle with an exceeding great and mighty army; but he shall not stand; for they shall devise devices against him. 26 Yes, they who eat of his dainties shall destroy him, and his army shall overflow; and many shall fall down slain. 27 As for both these kings, their hearts shall be to do mischief, and they shall speak lies at one table: but it shall not prosper; for yet the end shall be at the time appointed. 28 Then he will return into his land with great substance; and his heart will be against the holy covenant; and he will take action, and return to his own land.

29 At the time appointed he shall return, and come into the south; but it shall not be in the latter time as it was in the former. 30 For ships of Kittim shall come against him; therefore he shall be grieved, and shall return, and have indignation against the holy covenant, and shall take action: he shall even return, and have regard to those who forsake the holy covenant.

31 Forces shall stand on his part, and they shall profane the sanctuary, even the fortress, and shall take away the continual burnt offering, and they shall set up the abomination that makes desolate. 32 Such as do wickedly against the covenant shall he pervert by flatteries; but the people who know their God shall be strong, and take action.

33 Those who are wise among the people shall instruct many; yet they shall fall by the sword and by flame, by captivity and by plunder, many days. 34 Now when they shall fall, they shall be helped with a little help; but many shall join themselves to them with flatteries. 35 Some of those who are wise shall fall, to refine them, and to purify, and to make them white, even to the time of the end; because it is yet for the time appointed.

36 The king shall do according to his will; and he shall exalt himself, and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvelous things against the God of gods; and he shall prosper until the indignation be accomplished; for that which is determined shall be done. 37 Neither shall he regard the gods of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god; for he shall magnify himself above all. 38 But in his place shall he honor the god of fortresses; and a god whom his fathers didn’t know shall he honor with gold, and silver, and with precious stones, and pleasant things. 39 He shall deal with the strongest fortresses by the help of a foreign god: whoever acknowledges him he will increase with glory; and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for a price.

40 At the time of the end shall the king of the south contend with him; and the king of the north shall come against him like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with many ships; and he shall enter into the countries, and shall overflow and pass through. 41 He shall enter also into the glorious land, and many countries shall be overthrown; but these shall be delivered out of his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the children of Ammon. 42 He shall stretch out his hand also on the countries; and the land of Egypt shall not escape. 43 But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt; and the Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps. 44 But news out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him; and he shall go out with great fury to destroy and utterly to sweep away many. 45 He shall plant the tents of his palace between the sea and the glorious holy mountain; yet he shall come to his end, and no one shall help him.

Daniel 12

1 “At that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince who stands for the children of your people; and there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation even to that same time: and at that time your people shall be delivered, everyone who shall be found written in the book. 2 Many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame and everlasting contempt. 3 Those who are wise shall shine as the brightness of the expanse; and those who turn many to righteousness as the stars forever and ever. 4 But you, Daniel, shut up the words, and seal the book, even to the time of the end: many shall run back and forth, and knowledge shall be increased.”

5 Then I, Daniel, looked, and behold, two others stood, one on the river bank on this side, and the other on the river bank on that side. 6 One said to the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, How long shall it be to the end of these wonders?

7 I heard the man clothed in linen, who was above the waters of the river, when he held up his right hand and his left hand to heaven, and swore by him who lives forever that it shall be for a time, times, and a half; and when they have finished breaking in pieces the power of the holy people, all these things shall be finished.

8 I heard, but I didn’t understand: then I said, my lord, what shall be the issue of these things?

9 He said, Go your way, Daniel; for the words are shut up and sealed until the time of the end. 10 Many shall purify themselves, and make themselves white, and be refined; but the wicked shall do wickedly; and none of the wicked shall understand; but those who are wise shall understand.

11 From the time that the continual burnt offering shall be taken away, and the abomination that makes desolate set up, there shall be one thousand two hundred ninety days. 12 Blessed is he who waits, and comes to the one thousand three hundred thirty-five days.

13 But go you your way until the end; for you shall rest, and shall stand in your lot, at the end of the days.

Hosea 1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word that came to Hosea the son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel. 2 When Yahweh spoke at first by Hosea, Yahweh said to Hosea, “Go, take for yourself a wife of prostitution and children of unfaithfulness; for the land commits great adultery, forsaking Yahweh.”

3 So he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; and she conceived, and bore him a son.

4 Yahweh said to him, “Call his name Jezreel; for yet a little while, and I will avenge the blood of Jezreel on the house of Jehu, and will cause the kingdom of the house of Israel to cease. 5 It will happen in that day that I will break the bow of Israel in the valley of Jezreel.”

6 She conceived again, and bore a daughter.

Then he said to him, “Call her name Lo-Ruhamah[*] ; for I will no longer have mercy on the house of Israel, that I should in any way pardon them. 7 But I will have mercy on the house of Judah, and will save them by Yahweh their God,[*] and will not save them by bow, sword, battle, horses, or horsemen.”

8 Now when she had weaned Lo-Ruhamah, she conceived, and bore a son.

9 He said, “Call his name Lo-Ammi[*] ; for you are not my people, and I will not be yours. 10 Yet the number of the children of Israel will be as the sand of the sea, which can’t be measured or counted; and it will come to pass that, in the place where it was said to them, ‘You are not my people,’ they will be called ‘sons of the living God.’ 11 The children of Judah and the children of Israel will be gathered together, and they will appoint themselves one head, and will go up from the land; for great will be the day of Jezreel.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

Lo-Ruhamah means “not loved”.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Lo-Ammi means “not my people”.

Hosea 2

1 “Say to your brothers, ‘My people!’[*]

and to your sisters, ‘My loved one!’[*]

2 Contend with your mother!

Contend, for she is not my wife,

neither am I her husband;

and let her put away her prostitution from her face,

and her adulteries from between her breasts;

3 Lest I strip her naked,

and make her bare as in the day that she was born,

and make her like a wilderness,

and set her like a dry land,

and kill her with thirst.

4 Indeed, on her children I will have no mercy;

for they are children of unfaithfulness;

5 For their mother has played the prostitute.

She who conceived them has done shamefully;

for she said, ‘I will go after my lovers,

who give me my bread and my water,

my wool and my flax,

my oil and my drink.’

6 Therefore behold,[*] I will hedge up your way with thorns,

and I will build a wall against her,

that she can’t find her way.

7 She will follow after her lovers,

but she won’t overtake them;

and she will seek them,

but won’t find them.

Then she will say, ‘I will go and return to my first husband;

for then was it better with me than now.’

8 For she did not know that I gave her the grain, the new wine, and the oil,

and multiplied to her silver and gold, which they used for Baal.

9 Therefore I will take back my grain in its time,

and my new wine in its season,

and will pluck away my wool and my flax which should have covered her nakedness.

10 Now I will uncover her lewdness in the sight of her lovers,

and no one will deliver her out of my hand.

11 I will also cause all her celebrations to cease:

her feasts, her new moons, her Sabbaths, and all her solemn assemblies.

12 I will lay waste her vines and her fig trees,

about which she has said, ‘These are my wages that my lovers have given me;

and I will make them a forest,’

and the animals of the field shall eat them.

13 I will visit on her the days of the Baals,

to which she burned incense,

when she decked herself with her earrings and her jewels,

and went after her lovers,

and forgot me,” says Yahweh.

14 “Therefore behold, I will allure her,

and bring her into the wilderness,

and speak tenderly to her.

15 I will give her vineyards from there,

and the valley of Achor for a door of hope;

and she will respond there,

as in the days of her youth,

and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt.

16 It will be in that day,” says Yahweh,

“that you will call me ‘my husband,’

and no longer call me ‘my master.’

17 For I will take away the names of the Baals out of her mouth,

and they will no longer be mentioned by name.

18 In that day I will make a covenant for them with the animals of the field,

and with the birds of the sky,

and with the creeping things of the ground.

I will break the bow, the sword, and the battle out of the land,

and will make them lie down safely.

19 I will betroth you to me forever.

Yes, I will betroth you to me in righteousness, in justice, in loving kindness, and in compassion.

20 I will even betroth you to me in faithfulness;

and you shall know Yahweh.

21 It will happen in that day, I will respond,” says Yahweh,

“I will respond to the heavens,

and they will respond to the earth;

22 and the earth will respond to the grain, and the new wine, and the oil;

and they will respond to Jezreel.

23 I will sow her to me in the earth;

and I will have mercy on her who had not obtained mercy;

and I will tell those who were not my people, ‘You are my people;’

and they will say, ‘My God!’”

‘Ammi’ in Hebrew

‘Ruhamah’ in Hebrew

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Hosea 4

1 Hear Yahweh’s word, you children of Israel;

for Yahweh has a charge against the inhabitants of the land:

“Indeed there is no truth,

nor goodness,

nor knowledge of God in the land.

2 There is cursing, lying, murder, stealing, and committing adultery;

they break boundaries, and bloodshed causes bloodshed.

3 Therefore the land will mourn,

and everyone who dwells therein will waste away.

all living things in her,

even the animals of the field and the birds of the sky;

yes, the fish of the sea also die.

4 “Yet let no man bring a charge, neither let any man accuse; For your people are like those who bring charges against a priest.

5 You will stumble in the day,

and the prophet will also stumble with you in the night;

and I will destroy your mother.

6 My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge.

Because you have rejected knowledge, I will also reject you,

that you may be no priest to me.

Because you have forgotten your God’s law,

I will also forget your children.

7 As they were multiplied, so they sinned against me.

I will change their glory into shame.

8 They feed on the sin of my people,

and set their heart on their iniquity.

9 It will be, like people, like priest;

and I will punish them for their ways,

and will repay them for their deeds.

10 They will eat, and not have enough.

They will play the prostitute, and will not increase;

because they have abandoned giving to Yahweh.

11 Prostitution, wine, and new wine take away understanding.

12 My people consult with their wooden idol,

and answer to a stick of wood.

Indeed the spirit of prostitution has led them astray,

and they have been unfaithful to their God.

13 They sacrifice on the tops of the mountains,

and burn incense on the hills, under oaks and poplars and terebinths,

because its shade is good.

Therefore your daughters play the prostitute,

and your brides commit adultery.

14 I will not punish your daughters when they play the prostitute,

nor your brides when they commit adultery;

because the men consort with prostitutes,

and they sacrifice with the shrine prostitutes;

so the people without understanding will come to ruin.

15 “Though you, Israel, play the prostitute,

yet don’t let Judah offend;

and don’t come to Gilgal,

neither go up to Beth Aven,

nor swear, ‘As Yahweh lives.’

16 For Israel has behaved extremely stubbornly, like a stubborn heifer.

Then how will Yahweh feed them like a lamb in a meadow.

17 Ephraim is joined to idols.

Leave him alone!

18 Their drink has become sour.

They play the prostitute continually.

Her rulers dearly love their shameful way.

19 The wind has wrapped her up in its wings;

and they shall be disappointed because of their sacrifices.

Hosea 5

1 “Listen to this, you priests!

Listen, house of Israel,

and give ear, house of the king!

For the judgment is against you;

for you have been a snare at Mizpah,

and a net spread on Tabor.

2 The rebels are deep in slaughter;

but I discipline all of them.

3 I know Ephraim,

and Israel is not hidden from me;

for now, Ephraim, you have played the prostitute.

Israel is defiled.

4 Their deeds won’t allow them to turn to their God;

for the spirit of prostitution is within them,

and they don’t know Yahweh.

5 The pride of Israel testifies to his face.

Therefore Israel and Ephraim will stumble in their iniquity.

Judah also will stumble with them.

6 They will go with their flocks and with their herds to seek Yahweh;

but they won’t find him.

He has withdrawn himself from them.

7 They are unfaithful to Yahweh;

for they have borne illegitimate children.

Now the new moon will devour them with their fields.

8 “Blow the cornet in Gibeah,

and the trumpet in Ramah!

Sound a battle cry at Beth Aven, behind you, Benjamin!

9 Ephraim will become a desolation in the day of rebuke.

Among the tribes of Israel, I have made known that which will surely be.

10 The princes of Judah are like those who remove a landmark.

I will pour out my wrath on them like water.

11 Ephraim is oppressed,

he is crushed in judgment;

Because he is intent in his pursuit of idols.

12 Therefore I am to Ephraim like a moth,

and to the house of Judah like rottenness.

13 “When Ephraim saw his sickness,

and Judah his wound,

Then Ephraim went to Assyria,

and sent to king Jareb:

but he is not able to heal you,

neither will he cure you of your wound.

14 For I will be to Ephraim like a lion,

and like a young lion to the house of Judah.

I myself will tear in pieces and go away.

I will carry off, and there will be no one to deliver.

15 I will go and return to my place,

until they acknowledge their offense,

and seek my face.

In their affliction they will seek me earnestly.”

Hosea 6

1 “Come, and let us return to Yahweh;

for he has torn us to pieces,

and he will heal us;

he has injured us,

and he will bind up our wounds.

2 After two days he will revive us.

On the third day he will raise us up,

and we will live before him.

3 Let us acknowledge Yahweh.

Let us press on to know Yahweh.

As surely as the sun rises,

Yahweh will appear.

He will come to us like the rain,

like the spring rain that waters the earth.”

4 “Ephraim, what shall I do to you?

Judah, what shall I do to you?

For your love is like a morning cloud,

and like the dew that disappears early.

5 Therefore I have cut them to pieces with the prophets;

I killed them with the words of my mouth.

Your judgments are like a flash of lightning.

6 For I desire mercy, and not sacrifice;

and the knowledge of God more than burnt offerings.

7 But they, like Adam, have broken the covenant.

They were unfaithful to me, there.

8 Gilead is a city of those who work iniquity;

it is stained with blood.

9 As gangs of robbers wait to ambush a man,

so the company of priests murder on the path toward Shechem,

committing shameful crimes.

10 In the house of Israel I have seen a horrible thing.

There is prostitution in Ephraim.

Israel is defiled.

11 “Also, Judah, there is a harvest appointed for you,

when I restore the fortunes of my people.

Hosea 7

1 When I would heal Israel,

then the iniquity of Ephraim is uncovered,

also the wickedness of Samaria;

for they commit falsehood,

and the thief enters in,

and the gang of robbers ravages outside.

2 They don’t consider in their hearts that I remember all their wickedness.

Now their own deeds have engulfed them.

They are before my face.

3 They make the king glad with their wickedness,

and the princes with their lies.

4 They are all adulterers.

They are burning like an oven that the baker stops stirring,

from the kneading of the dough, until it is leavened.

5 On the day of our king, the princes made themselves sick with the heat of wine.

He joined his hand with mockers.

6 For they have prepared their heart like an oven,

while they lie in wait.

Their baker sleeps all the night.

In the morning it burns as a flaming fire.

7 They are all hot as an oven,

and devour their judges.

All their kings have fallen.

There is no one among them who calls to me.

8 Ephraim, he mixes himself among the nations.

Ephraim is a pancake not turned over.

9 Strangers have devoured his strength,

and he doesn’t realize it.

Indeed, gray hairs are here and there on him,

and he doesn’t realize it.

10 The pride of Israel testifies to his face;

yet they haven’t returned to Yahweh their God,

nor sought him, for all this.

11 “Ephraim is like an easily deceived dove, without understanding.

They call to Egypt.

They go to Assyria.

12 When they go, I will spread my net on them.

I will bring them down like the birds of the sky.

I will chastise them, as their congregation has heard.

13 Woe to them!

For they have wandered from me.

Destruction to them!

For they have trespassed against me.

Though I would redeem them,

yet they have spoken lies against me.

14 They haven’t cried to me with their heart,

but they howl on their beds.

They assemble themselves for grain and new wine.

They turn away from me.

15 Though I have taught and strengthened their arms,

yet they plot evil against me.

16 They return, but not to the Most High.

They are like a faulty bow.

Their princes will fall by the sword for the rage of their tongue.

This will be their derision in the land of Egypt.

Hosea 8

1 “Put the trumpet to your lips!

Something like an eagle is over Yahweh’s house,

because they have broken my covenant,

and rebelled against my law.

2 They cry to me, ‘My God, we Israel acknowledge you!’

3 Israel has cast off that which is good.

The enemy will pursue him.

4 They have set up kings, but not by me.

They have made princes, and I didn’t approve.

Of their silver and their gold they have made themselves idols,

that they may be cut off.

5 Let Samaria throw out his calf idol!

My anger burns against them!

How long will it be until they are capable of purity?

6 For this is even from Israel!

The workman made it, and it is no God;

indeed, the calf of Samaria shall be broken in pieces.

7 For they sow the wind,

and they will reap the whirlwind.

He has no standing grain.

The stalk will yield no head.

If it does yield, strangers will swallow it up.

8 Israel is swallowed up.

Now they are among the nations like a worthless thing.

9 For they have gone up to Assyria,

like a wild donkey wandering alone.

Ephraim has hired lovers for himself.

10 But although they sold themselves among the nations,

I will now gather them;

and they begin to waste away because of the oppression of the king of mighty ones.

11 Because Ephraim has multiplied altars for sinning,

they became for him altars for sinning.

12 I wrote for him the many things of my law;

but they were regarded as a strange thing.

13 As for the sacrifices of my offerings,

they sacrifice meat and eat it;

But Yahweh doesn’t accept them.

Now he will remember their iniquity,

and punish their sins.

They will return to Egypt.

14 For Israel has forgotten his Maker and built palaces;

and Judah has multiplied fortified cities;

but I will send a fire on his cities,

and it will devour its fortresses.”

Hosea 9

1 Don’t rejoice, Israel, to jubilation like the nations;

for you were unfaithful to your God.

You love the wages of a prostitute at every grain threshing floor.

2 The threshing floor and the wine press won’t feed them,

and the new wine will fail her.

3 They won’t dwell in Yahweh’s land;

but Ephraim will return to Egypt,

and they will eat unclean food in Assyria.

4 They won’t pour out wine offerings to Yahweh,

neither will they be pleasing to him.

Their sacrifices will be to them like the bread of mourners;

all who eat of it will be polluted;

for their bread will be for their appetite.

It will not come into Yahweh’s house.

5 What will you do in the day of solemn assembly,

and in the day of the feast of Yahweh?

6 For, behold, they have gone away from destruction.

Egypt will gather them up.

Memphis will bury them.

Nettles will possess their pleasant things of silver.

Thorns will be in their tents.

7 The days of visitation have come.

The days of reckoning have come.

Israel will consider the prophet to be a fool,

and the man who is inspired to be insane,

because of the abundance of your sins,

and because your hostility is great.

8 A prophet watches over Ephraim with my God.

A fowler’s snare is on all of his paths,

and hostility in the house of his God.

9 They have deeply corrupted themselves,

as in the days of Gibeah.

He will remember their iniquity.

He will punish them for their sins.

10 I found Israel like grapes in the wilderness.

I saw your fathers as the first ripe in the fig tree at its first season;

but they came to Baal Peor, and consecrated themselves to the shameful thing,

and became abominable like that which they loved.

11 As for Ephraim, their glory will fly away like a bird.

There will be no birth, no one with child, and no conception.

12 Though they bring up their children,

yet I will bereave them, so that not a man shall be left.

Indeed, woe also to them when I depart from them!

13 I have seen Ephraim, like Tyre, planted in a pleasant place;

but Ephraim will bring out his children to the murderer.

14 Give them—Yahweh what will you give?

Give them a miscarrying womb and dry breasts.

15 “All their wickedness is in Gilgal;

for there I hated them.

Because of the wickedness of their deeds I will drive them out of my house!

I will love them no more.

All their princes are rebels.

16 Ephraim is struck.

Their root has dried up.

They will bear no fruit.

Even though they give birth, yet I will kill the beloved ones of their womb.”

17 My God will cast them away, because they did not listen to him;

and they will be wanderers among the nations.

Hosea 10

1 Israel is a luxuriant vine that produces his fruit.

According to the abundance of his fruit he has multiplied his altars.

As their land has prospered, they have adorned their sacred stones.

2 Their heart is divided.

Now they will be found guilty.

He will demolish their altars.

He will destroy their sacred stones.

3 Surely now they will say, “We have no king; for we don’t fear Yahweh;

and the king, what can he do for us?”

4 They make promises, swearing falsely in making covenants.

Therefore judgment springs up like poisonous weeds in the furrows of the field.

5 The inhabitants of Samaria will be in terror for the calves of Beth Aven;

for its people will mourn over it,

Along with its priests who rejoiced over it,

for its glory, because it has departed from it.

6 It also will be carried to Assyria for a present to a great king.

Ephraim will receive shame,

and Israel will be ashamed of his own counsel.

7 Samaria and her king float away,

like a twig on the water.

8 The high places also of Aven, the sin of Israel, will be destroyed.

The thorn and the thistle will come up on their altars.

They will tell the mountains, “Cover us!” and the hills, “Fall on us!”

9 “Israel, you have sinned from the days of Gibeah.

There they remained.

The battle against the children of iniquity doesn’t overtake them in Gibeah.

10 When it is my desire, I will chastise them;

and the nations will be gathered against them,

when they are bound to their two transgressions.

11 Ephraim is a trained heifer that loves to thresh;

so I will put a yoke on her beautiful neck.

I will set a rider on Ephraim.

Judah will plow.

Jacob will break his clods.

12 Sow to yourselves in righteousness,

reap according to kindness.

Break up your fallow ground;

for it is time to seek Yahweh,

until he comes and rains righteousness on you.

13 You have plowed wickedness.

You have reaped iniquity.

You have eaten the fruit of lies,

for you trusted in your way, in the multitude of your mighty men.

14 Therefore a battle roar will arise among your people,

and all your fortresses will be destroyed,

as Shalman destroyed Beth Arbel in the day of battle.

The mother was dashed in pieces with her children.

15 So Bethel will do to you because of your great wickedness.

At daybreak the king of Israel will be destroyed.

Hosea 11

1 “When Israel was a child, then I loved him,

and called my son out of Egypt.

2 They called to them, so they went from them.

They sacrificed to the Baals,

and burned incense to engraved images.

3 Yet I taught Ephraim to walk.

I took them by his arms;

but they didn’t know that I healed them.

4 I drew them with cords of a man, with ties of love;

and I was to them like those who lift up the yoke on their necks;

and I bent down to him and I fed him.

5 “They won’t return into the land of Egypt;

but the Assyrian will be their king,

because they refused to repent.

6 The sword will fall on their cities,

and will destroy the bars of their gates,

and will put an end to their plans.

7 My people are determined to turn from me.

Though they call to the Most High,

he certainly won’t exalt them.

8 “How can I give you up, Ephraim?

How can I hand you over, Israel?

How can I make you like Admah?

How can I make you like Zeboiim?

My heart is turned within me,

my compassion is aroused.

9 I will not execute the fierceness of my anger.

I will not return to destroy Ephraim:

for I am God, and not man; the Holy One among you;

and I will not come in wrath.

10 They will walk after Yahweh,

who will roar like a lion;

for he will roar, and the children will come trembling from the west.

11 They will come trembling like a bird out of Egypt,

and like a dove out of the land of Assyria;

and I will settle them in their houses,” says Yahweh.

12 Ephraim surrounds me with falsehood,

and the house of Israel with deceit.

Judah still strays from God,

and is unfaithful to the Holy One.

Hosea 12

1 Ephraim feeds on wind,

and chases the east wind.

He continually multiplies lies and desolation.

They make a covenant with Assyria,

and oil is carried into Egypt.

2 Yahweh also has a controversy with Judah,

and will punish Jacob according to his ways;

according to his deeds he will repay him.

3 In the womb he took his brother by the heel;

and in his manhood he contended with God.

4 Indeed, he struggled with the angel, and prevailed;

he wept, and made supplication to him.

He found him at Bethel, and there he spoke with us,

5 even Yahweh, the God of Armies;

Yahweh is his name of renown!

6 Therefore turn to your God.

Keep kindness and justice,

and wait continually for your God.

7 A merchant has dishonest scales in his hand.

He loves to defraud.

8 Ephraim said, “Surely I have become rich,

I have found myself wealth.

In all my wealth they won’t find in me any iniquity that is sin.”

9 “But I am Yahweh your God from the land of Egypt.

I will yet again make you dwell in tents,

as in the days of the solemn feast.

10 I have also spoken to the prophets,

and I have multiplied visions;

and by the ministry of the prophets I have used parables.

11 If Gilead is wicked,

surely they are worthless.

In Gilgal they sacrifice bulls.

Indeed, their altars are like heaps in the furrows of the field.

12 Jacob fled into the country of Aram,

and Israel served to get a wife,

and for a wife he tended flocks and herds.

13 By a prophet Yahweh brought Israel up out of Egypt,

and by a prophet he was preserved.

14 Ephraim has bitterly provoked anger.

Therefore his blood will be left on him,

and his Lord[*] will repay his contempt.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Hosea 13

1 When Ephraim spoke, there was trembling.

He exalted himself in Israel,

but when he became guilty in Baal, he died.

2 Now they sin more and more,

and have made themselves molten images of their silver,

even idols according to their own understanding,

all of them the work of the craftsmen.

They say of them, ‘They offer human sacrifice and kiss the calves.’

3 Therefore they will be like the morning mist,

and like the dew that passes away early,

like the chaff that is driven with the whirlwind out of the threshing floor,

and like the smoke out of the chimney.

4 “Yet I am Yahweh your God from the land of Egypt;

and you shall acknowledge no god but me,

and besides me there is no savior.

5 I knew you in the wilderness,

in the land of great drought.

6 According to their pasture, so were they filled;

they were filled, and their heart was exalted.

Therefore they have forgotten me.

7 Therefore I am like a lion to them.

Like a leopard, I will lurk by the path.

8 I will meet them like a bear that is bereaved of her cubs,

and will tear the covering of their heart.

There I will devour them like a lioness.

The wild animal will tear them.

9 You are destroyed, Israel, because you are against me,

against your help.

10 Where is your king now, that he may save you in all your cities?

And your judges, of whom you said, ‘Give me a king and princes?’

11 I have given you a king in my anger,

and have taken him away in my wrath.

12 The guilt of Ephraim is stored up.

His sin is stored up.

13 The sorrows of a travailing woman will come on him.

He is an unwise son;

for when it is time, he doesn’t come to the opening of the womb.

14 I will ransom them from the power of Sheol.[*]

I will redeem them from death!

Death, where are your plagues?

Sheol, where is your destruction?

“Compassion will be hidden from my eyes.

15 Though he is fruitful among his brothers, an east wind will come,

the breath of Yahweh coming up from the wilderness;

and his spring will become dry,

and his fountain will be dried up.

He will plunder the storehouse of treasure.

16 Samaria will bear her guilt;

for she has rebelled against her God.

They will fall by the sword.

Their infants will be dashed in pieces,

and their pregnant women will be ripped open.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Hosea 14

1 Israel, return to Yahweh your God;

for you have fallen because of your sin.

2 Take words with you, and return to Yahweh.

Tell him, “Forgive all our sins,

and accept that which is good:

so we offer our lips like bulls.

3 Assyria can’t save us.

We won’t ride on horses;

neither will we say any more to the work of our hands, ‘Our gods!’

for in you the fatherless finds mercy.”

4 “I will heal their waywardness.

I will love them freely;

for my anger is turned away from him.

5 I will be like the dew to Israel.

He will blossom like the lily,

and send down his roots like Lebanon.

6 His branches will spread,

and his beauty will be like the olive tree,

and his fragrance like Lebanon.

7 Men will dwell in his shade.

They will revive like the grain,

and blossom like the vine.

Their fragrance will be like the wine of Lebanon.

8 Ephraim, what have I to do any more with idols?

I answer, and will take care of him.

I am like a green cypress tree;

from me your fruit is found.”

9 Who is wise, that he may understand these things?

Who is prudent, that he may know them?

For the ways of Yahweh are right,

and the righteous walk in them;

But the rebellious stumble in them.

Joel 1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word that came to Joel, the son of Pethuel.

2 Hear this, you elders,

And listen, all you inhabitants of the land.

Has this ever happened in your days,

or in the days of your fathers?

3 Tell your children about it,

and have your children tell their children,

and their children, another generation.

4 What the swarming locust has left, the great locust has eaten.

What the great locust has left, the grasshopper has eaten.

What the grasshopper has left, the caterpillar has eaten.

5 Wake up, you drunkards, and weep!

Wail, all you drinkers of wine, because of the sweet wine;

for it is cut off from your mouth.

6 For a nation has come up on my land, strong, and without number.

His teeth are the teeth of a lion,

and he has the fangs of a lioness.

7 He has laid my vine waste,

and stripped my fig tree.

He has stripped its bark, and thrown it away.

Its branches are made white.

8 Mourn like a virgin dressed in sackcloth for the husband of her youth! 9 The meal offering and the drink offering are cut off from Yahweh’s house.

The priests, Yahweh’s ministers, mourn.

10 The field is laid waste.

The land mourns, for the grain is destroyed,

The new wine has dried up,

and the oil languishes.

11 Be confounded, you farmers!

Wail, you vineyard keepers;

for the wheat and for the barley;

for the harvest of the field has perished.

12 The vine has dried up, and the fig tree withered;

the pomegranate tree, the palm tree also, and the apple tree,

even all of the trees of the field are withered;

for joy has withered away from the sons of men.

13 Put on sackcloth and mourn, you priests!

Wail, you ministers of the altar.

Come, lie all night in sackcloth, you ministers of my God,[*]

for the meal offering and the drink offering are withheld from your God’s house.

14 Sanctify a fast.

Call a solemn assembly.

Gather the elders,

and all the inhabitants of the land, to the house of Yahweh, your God,

and cry to Yahweh.

15 Alas for the day!

For the day of Yahweh is at hand,

and it will come as destruction from the Almighty.

16 Isn’t the food cut off before our eyes;

joy and gladness from the house of our God?

17 The seeds rot under their clods.

The granaries are laid desolate.

The barns are broken down, for the grain has withered.

18 How the animals groan!

The herds of livestock are perplexed, because they have no pasture.

Yes, the flocks of sheep are made desolate.

19 Yahweh, I cry to you,

For the fire has devoured the pastures of the wilderness,

and the flame has burned all the trees of the field.

20 Yes, the animals of the field pant to you,

for the water brooks have dried up,

And the fire has devoured the pastures of the wilderness.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Joel 2

1 Blow the trumpet in Zion,

and sound an alarm in my holy mountain!

Let all the inhabitants of the land tremble,

for the day of Yahweh comes,

for it is close at hand:

2 A day of darkness and gloominess,

a day of clouds and thick darkness.

As the dawn spreading on the mountains,

a great and strong people;

there has never been the like,

neither will there be any more after them,

even to the years of many generations.

3 A fire devours before them,

and behind them, a flame burns.

The land is as the garden of Eden before them,

and behind them, a desolate wilderness.

Yes, and no one has escaped them.

4 Their appearance is as the appearance of horses,

and as horsemen, so do they run.

5 Like the noise of chariots on the tops of the mountains do they leap,

like the noise of a flame of fire that devours the stubble,

as a strong people set in battle array.

6 At their presence the peoples are in anguish.

All faces have grown pale.

7 They run like mighty men.

They climb the wall like warriors.

They each march in his line, and they don’t swerve off course.

8 Neither does one jostle another;

they march everyone in his path,

and they burst through the defenses,

and don’t break ranks.

9 They rush on the city.

They run on the wall.

They climb up into the houses.

They enter in at the windows like thieves.

10 The earth quakes before them.

The heavens tremble.

The sun and the moon are darkened,

and the stars withdraw their shining.

11 Yahweh thunders his voice before his army;

for his forces are very great;

for he is strong who obeys his command;

for the day of Yahweh is great and very awesome,

and who can endure it?

12 “Yet even now,” says Yahweh, “turn to me with all your heart,

and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning.”

13 Tear your heart, and not your garments,

and turn to Yahweh, your God;

for he is gracious and merciful,

slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness,

and relents from sending calamity.

14 Who knows? He may turn and relent,

and leave a blessing behind him,

even a meal offering and a drink offering to Yahweh, your God.

15 Blow the trumpet in Zion!

Sanctify a fast.

Call a solemn assembly.

16 Gather the people.

Sanctify the assembly.

Assemble the elders.

Gather the children, and those who nurse from breasts.

Let the bridegroom go out of his room,

and the bride out of her room.

17 Let the priests, the ministers of Yahweh, weep between the porch and the altar,

and let them say, “Spare your people, Yahweh,

and don’t give your heritage to reproach,

that the nations should rule over them.

Why should they say among the peoples,

‘Where is their God?’”

18 Then Yahweh was jealous for his land,

And had pity on his people.

19 Yahweh answered his people,

“Behold,[*] I will send you grain, new wine, and oil,

and you will be satisfied with them;

and I will no more make you a reproach among the nations.

20 But I will remove the northern army far away from you,

and will drive it into a barren and desolate land,

its front into the eastern sea,

and its back into the western sea;

and its stench will come up,

and its bad smell will rise.”

Surely he has done great things.

21 Land, don’t be afraid.

Be glad and rejoice, for Yahweh has done great things.

22 Don’t be afraid, you animals of the field;

for the pastures of the wilderness spring up,

for the tree bears its fruit.

The fig tree and the vine yield their strength.

23 “Be glad then, you children of Zion,

and rejoice in Yahweh, your God;

for he gives you the former rain in just measure,

and he causes the rain to come down for you,

the former rain and the latter rain,

as before.

24 The threshing floors will be full of wheat,

and the vats will overflow with new wine and oil.

25 I will restore to you the years that the swarming locust has eaten,

the great locust, the grasshopper, and the caterpillar,

my great army, which I sent among you.

26 You will have plenty to eat, and be satisfied,

and will praise the name of Yahweh, your God,

who has dealt wondrously with you;

and my people will never again be disappointed.

27 You will know that I am among Israel,

and that I am Yahweh, your God, and there is no one else;

and my people will never again be disappointed.

28 “It will happen afterward, that I will pour out my Spirit on all flesh;

and your sons and your daughters will prophesy.

Your old men will dream dreams.

Your young men will see visions.

29 And also on the servants and on the handmaids in those days,

I will pour out my Spirit.

30 I will show wonders in the heavens and in the earth:

blood, fire, and pillars of smoke.

31 The sun will be turned into darkness,

and the moon into blood,

before the great and terrible day of Yahweh comes.

32 It will happen that whoever will call on Yahweh’s name shall be saved;

for in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there will be those who escape,

as Yahweh has said,

and among the remnant, those whom Yahweh calls.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Joel 3

1 “For, behold, in those days,

and in that time,

when I restore the fortunes of Judah and Jerusalem,

2 I will gather all nations,

and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat;

and I will execute judgment on them there for my people,

and for my heritage, Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations.

They have divided my land,

3 and have cast lots for my people,

and have given a boy for a prostitute,

and sold a girl for wine, that they may drink.

4 “Yes, and what are you to me, Tyre, and Sidon,

and all the regions of Philistia?

Will you repay me?

And if you repay me,

I will swiftly and speedily return your repayment on your own head.

5 Because you have taken my silver and my gold,

and have carried my finest treasures into your temples,

6 and have sold the children of Judah and the children of Jerusalem to the sons of the Greeks,

that you may remove them far from their border.

7 Behold, I will stir them up out of the place where you have sold them,

and will return your repayment on your own head;

8 and I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hands of the children of Judah,

and they will sell them to the men of Sheba,

to a faraway nation,

for Yahweh has spoken it.”

9 Proclaim this among the nations:

“Prepare for war!

Stir up the mighty men.

Let all the warriors draw near.

Let them come up. 10 Beat your plowshares into swords,

and your pruning hooks into spears.

Let the weak say, ‘I am strong.’

11 Hurry and come, all you surrounding nations,

and gather yourselves together.”

Cause your mighty ones to come down there, Yahweh.

12 “Let the nations arouse themselves,

and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat;

for there will I sit to judge all the surrounding nations.

13 Put in the sickle;

for the harvest is ripe.

Come, tread, for the wine press is full,

the vats overflow, for their wickedness is great.”

14 Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision!

For the day of Yahweh is near, in the valley of decision.

15 The sun and the moon are darkened,

and the stars withdraw their shining.

16 Yahweh will roar from Zion,

and thunder from Jerusalem;

and the heavens and the earth will shake;

but Yahweh will be a refuge to his people,

and a stronghold to the children of Israel.

17 “So you will know that I am Yahweh, your God,

dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain.

Then Jerusalem will be holy,

and no strangers will pass through her any more.

18 It will happen in that day,

that the mountains will drop down sweet wine,

the hills will flow with milk,

all the brooks of Judah will flow with waters,

and a fountain will flow out from Yahweh’s house,

and will water the valley of Shittim.

19 Egypt will be a desolation,

and Edom will be a desolate wilderness,

for the violence done to the children of Judah,

because they have shed innocent blood in their land.

20 But Judah will be inhabited forever,

and Jerusalem from generation to generation.

21 I will cleanse their blood,

that I have not cleansed:

for Yahweh dwells in Zion.”

Amos 1

1 The words of Amos, who was among the herdsmen of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel, two years before the earthquake. 2 He said:

“Yahweh[*] will roar from Zion,

and utter his voice from Jerusalem;

and the pastures of the shepherds will mourn,

and the top of Carmel will wither.”

3 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Damascus, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because they have threshed Gilead with threshing instruments of iron;

4 but I will send a fire into the house of Hazael,

and it will devour the palaces of Ben Hadad.

5 I will break the bar of Damascus,

and cut off the inhabitant from the valley of Aven,

and him who holds the scepter from the house of Eden;

and the people of Syria shall go into captivity to Kir,”

says Yahweh.

6 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Gaza, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because they carried away captive the whole community,

to deliver them up to Edom;

7 but I will send a fire on the wall of Gaza,

and it will devour its palaces.

8 I will cut off the inhabitant from Ashdod,

and him who holds the scepter from Ashkelon;

and I will turn my hand against Ekron;

and the remnant of the Philistines will perish,”

says the Lord[*] Yahweh.

9 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Tyre, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because they delivered up the whole community to Edom,

and didn’t remember the brotherly covenant;

10 but I will send a fire on the wall of Tyre,

and it will devour its palaces.”

11 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Edom, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because he pursued his brother with the sword,

and cast off all pity,

and his anger raged continually,

and he kept his wrath forever;

12 but I will send a fire on Teman,

and it will devour the palaces of Bozrah.”

13 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of the children of Ammon, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because they have ripped open the pregnant women of Gilead,

that they may enlarge their border.

14 But I will kindle a fire in the wall of Rabbah,

and it will devour its palaces,

with shouting in the day of battle,

with a storm in the day of the whirlwind;

15 and their king will go into captivity,

he and his princes together,”

says Yahweh.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Amos 2

1 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Moab, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because he burned the bones of the king of Edom into lime;

2 but I will send a fire on Moab,

and it will devour the palaces of Kerioth;

and Moab will die with tumult, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet;

3 and I will cut off the judge from among them,

and will kill all its princes with him,”

says Yahweh.

4 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Judah, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because they have rejected Yahweh’s law,

and have not kept his statutes,

and their lies have led them astray,

after which their fathers walked;

5 But I will send a fire on Judah,

and it will devour the palaces of Jerusalem.”

6 Yahweh says:

“For three transgressions of Israel, yes, for four,

I will not turn away its punishment;

because they have sold the righteous for silver,

and the needy for a pair of shoes;

7 They trample on the dust of the earth on the head of the poor,

and deny justice to the oppressed;

and a man and his father use the same maiden, to profane my holy name;

8 and they lay themselves down beside every altar on clothes taken in pledge;

and in the house of their God[*] they drink the wine of those who have been fined.

9 Yet I destroyed the Amorite before them,

whose height was like the height of the cedars,

and he was strong as the oaks;

yet I destroyed his fruit from above,

and his roots from beneath.

10 Also I brought you up out of the land of Egypt,

and led you forty years in the wilderness,

to possess the land of the Amorite.

11 I raised up some of your sons for prophets,

and some of your young men for Nazirites.

Isn’t this true,

you children of Israel?” says Yahweh.

12 “But you gave the Nazirites wine to drink,

and commanded the prophets, saying, ‘Don’t prophesy!’

13 Behold,[*] I will crush you in your place,

as a cart crushes that is full of grain.

14 Flight will perish from the swift;

and the strong won’t strengthen his force;

neither shall the mighty deliver himself;

15 neither shall he stand who handles the bow;

and he who is swift of foot won’t escape;

neither shall he who rides the horse deliver himself;

16 and he who is courageous among the mighty will flee away naked on that day,”

says Yahweh.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Amos 3

1 Hear this word that Yahweh has spoken against you, children of Israel, against the whole family which I brought up out of the land of Egypt, saying:

2 “I have only chosen you of all the families of the earth.

Therefore I will punish you for all of your sins.”

3 Do two walk together,

unless they have agreed?

4 Will a lion roar in the thicket,

when he has no prey?

Does a young lion cry out of his den,

if he has caught nothing?

5 Can a bird fall in a trap on the earth,

where no snare is set for him?

Does a snare spring up from the ground,

when there is nothing to catch?

6 Does the trumpet alarm sound in a city,

without the people being afraid?

Does evil happen to a city,

and Yahweh hasn’t done it?

7 Surely the Lord Yahweh will do nothing,

unless he reveals his secret to his servants the prophets.

8 The lion has roared.

Who will not fear?

The Lord Yahweh has spoken.

Who can but prophesy?

9 Proclaim in the palaces at Ashdod,

and in the palaces in the land of Egypt,

and say, “Assemble yourselves on the mountains of Samaria,

and see what unrest is in her,

and what oppression is among them.”

10 “Indeed they don’t know to do right,” says Yahweh,

“Who hoard plunder and loot in their palaces.”

11 Therefore thus says the Lord Yahweh:

“An adversary will overrun the land;

and he will pull down your strongholds,

and your fortresses will be plundered.”

12 Yahweh says:

“As the shepherd rescues out of the mouth of the lion two legs,

or a piece of an ear,

so shall the children of Israel be rescued who sit in Samaria on the corner of a couch,

and on the silken cushions of a bed.”

13 “Listen, and testify against the house of Jacob,” says the Lord Yahweh, the God of Armies.

14 “For in the day that I visit the transgressions of Israel on him,

I will also visit the altars of Bethel;

and the horns of the altar will be cut off,

and fall to the ground.

15 I will strike the winter house with the summer house;

and the houses of ivory will perish,

and the great houses will have an end,”

says Yahweh.

Amos 4

1 Listen to this word, you cows of Bashan, who are on the mountain of Samaria, who oppress the poor, who crush the needy, who tell their husbands, “Bring us drinks!”

2 The Lord Yahweh has sworn by his holiness that behold,

“The days shall come on you that they will take you away with hooks,

and the last of you with fish hooks.

3 You will go out at the breaks in the wall,

everyone straight before her;

and you will cast yourselves into Harmon,” says Yahweh.

4 “Go to Bethel, and sin;

to Gilgal, and sin more.

Bring your sacrifices every morning,

your tithes every three days,

5 offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving of that which is leavened,

and proclaim free will offerings and brag about them:

for this pleases you, you children of Israel,” says the Lord Yahweh.

6 “I also have given you cleanness of teeth in all your cities,

and lack of bread in every town;

yet you haven’t returned to me,” says Yahweh.

7 “I also have withheld the rain from you,

when there were yet three months to the harvest;

and I caused it to rain on one city,

and caused it not to rain on another city.

One place was rained on,

and the piece where it didn’t rain withered.

8 So two or three cities staggered to one city to drink water,

and were not satisfied:

yet you haven’t returned to me,” says Yahweh.

9 “I struck you with blight and mildew many times in your gardens and your vineyards;

and your fig trees and your olive trees have the swarming locust devoured:

yet you haven’t returned to me,” says Yahweh.

10 “I sent plagues among you like I did Egypt.

I have slain your young men with the sword,

and have carried away your horses;

and I filled your nostrils with the stench of your camp,

yet you haven’t returned to me,” says Yahweh.

11 “I have overthrown some of you,

as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah,

and you were like a burning stick plucked out of the fire;

yet you haven’t returned to me,” says Yahweh.

12 “Therefore thus will I do to you, Israel;

because I will do this to you,

prepare to meet your God, Israel.

13 For, behold, he who forms the mountains,

and creates the wind,

and declares to man what is his thought;

who makes the morning darkness,

and treads on the high places of the earth:

Yahweh, the God of Armies, is his name.”

Amos 5

1 Listen to this word which I take up for a lamentation over you, O house of Israel.

2 “The virgin of Israel has fallen;

She shall rise no more.

She is cast down on her land;

there is no one to raise her up.”

3 For thus says the Lord Yahweh:

“The city that went out a thousand shall have a hundred left,

and that which went out one hundred shall have ten left to the house of Israel.”

4 For Yahweh says to the house of Israel:

“Seek me, and you will live;

5 but don’t seek Bethel,

nor enter into Gilgal,

and don’t pass to Beersheba:

for Gilgal shall surely go into captivity,

and Bethel shall come to nothing.

6 Seek Yahweh, and you will live;

lest he break out like fire in the house of Joseph,

and it devour, and there be no one to quench it in Bethel.

7 You who turn justice to wormwood,

and cast down righteousness to the earth:

8 seek him who made the Pleiades and Orion,

and turns the shadow of death into the morning,

and makes the day dark with night;

who calls for the waters of the sea,

and pours them out on the surface of the earth, Yahweh is his name,

9 who brings sudden destruction on the strong,

so that destruction comes on the fortress.

10 They hate him who reproves in the gate,

and they abhor him who speaks blamelessly.

11 Therefore, because you trample on the poor,

and take taxes from him of wheat:

You have built houses of cut stone,

but you will not dwell in them.

You have planted pleasant vineyards,

but you shall not drink their wine.

12 For I know how many your offenses,

and how great are your sins—

you who afflict the just,

who take a bribe,

and who turn aside the needy in the courts.

13 Therefore a prudent person keeps silent in such a time,

for it is an evil time.

14 Seek good, and not evil,

that you may live;

and so Yahweh, the God of Armies, will be with you,

as you say.

15 Hate evil, love good,

and establish justice in the courts.

It may be that Yahweh, the God of Armies, will be gracious to the remnant of Joseph.”

16 Therefore Yahweh, the God of Armies, the Lord, says:

“Wailing will be in all the wide ways;

and they will say in all the streets, ‘Alas! Alas!’

and they will call the farmer to mourning,

and those who are skillful in lamentation to wailing.

17 In all vineyards there will be wailing;

for I will pass through the middle of you,” says Yahweh.

18 “Woe to you who desire the day of Yahweh!

Why do you long for the day of Yahweh?

It is darkness,

and not light.

19 As if a man fled from a lion,

and a bear met him;

Or he went into the house and leaned his hand on the wall,

and a snake bit him.

20 Won’t the day of Yahweh be darkness, and not light?

Even very dark, and no brightness in it?

21 I hate, I despise your feasts,

and I can’t stand your solemn assemblies.

22 Yes, though you offer me your burnt offerings and meal offerings,

I will not accept them;

neither will I regard the peace offerings of your fat animals.

23 Take away from me the noise of your songs!

I will not listen to the music of your harps.

24 But let justice roll on like rivers,

and righteousness like a mighty stream.

25 “Did you bring to me sacrifices and offerings in the wilderness forty years, house of Israel? 26 You also carried the tent of your king and the shrine of your images, the star of your god, which you made for yourselves. 27 Therefore will I cause you to go into captivity beyond Damascus,” says Yahweh, whose name is the God of Armies.

Amos 6

1 Woe to those who are at ease in Zion,

and to those who are secure on the mountain of Samaria,

the notable men of the chief of the nations,

to whom the house of Israel come!

2 Go to Calneh, and see;

and from there go to Hamath the great;

then go down to Gath of the Philistines.

are they better than these kingdoms?

or is their border greater than your border?

3 Those who put far away the evil day,

and cause the seat of violence to come near;

4 Who lie on beds of ivory,

and stretch themselves on their couches,

and eat the lambs out of the flock,

and the calves out of the middle of the stall;

5 who strum on the strings of a harp;

who invent for themselves instruments of music, like David;

6 who drink wine in bowls,

and anoint themselves with the best oils;

but they are not grieved for the affliction of Joseph.

7 Therefore they will now go captive with the first who go captive;

and the feasting and lounging will end.

8 “The Lord Yahweh has sworn by himself,” says Yahweh, the God of Armies:

“I abhor the pride of Jacob,

and detest his fortresses.

Therefore I will deliver up the city with all that is in it.

9 It will happen, if there remain ten men in one house,

that they shall die.

10 “When a man’s relative carries him, even he who burns him, to bring bodies out of the house, and asks him who is in the innermost parts of the house, ‘Is there yet any with you?’ And he says, ‘No;’ then he will say, ‘Hush! Indeed we must not mention Yahweh’s name.’

11 “For, behold, Yahweh commands, and the great house will be smashed to pieces,

and the little house into bits.

12 Do horses run on the rocky crags?

Does one plow there with oxen?

But you have turned justice into poison,

and the fruit of righteousness into bitterness;

13 you who rejoice in a thing of nothing, who say,

‘Haven’t we taken for ourselves horns by our own strength?’

14 For, behold, I will raise up against you a nation, house of Israel,”

says Yahweh, the God of Armies;

“and they will afflict you from the entrance of Hamath to the brook of the Arabah.”

Amos 7

1 Thus the Lord Yahweh showed me: and behold, he formed locusts in the beginning of the shooting up of the latter growth; and behold, it was the latter growth after the king’s harvest. 2 When they finished eating the grass of the land, then I said, “Lord Yahweh, forgive, I beg you! How could Jacob stand? For he is small.”

3 Yahweh relented concerning this. “It shall not be,” says Yahweh.

4 Thus the Lord Yahweh showed me and behold, the Lord Yahweh called for judgment by fire; and it dried up the great deep, and would have devoured the land. 5 Then I said, “Lord Yahweh, stop, I beg you! How could Jacob stand? For he is small.”

6 Yahweh relented concerning this. “This also shall not be,” says the Lord Yahweh.

7 Thus he showed me and behold, the Lord stood beside a wall made by a plumb line, with a plumb line in his hand. 8 Yahweh said to me, “Amos, what do you see?”

I said, “A plumb line.”

Then the Lord said, “Behold, I will set a plumb line in the middle of my people Israel. I will not again pass by them any more. 9 The high places of Isaac will be desolate, the sanctuaries of Israel will be laid waste; and I will rise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.”

10 Then Amaziah the priest of Bethel sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying, “Amos has conspired against you in the middle of the house of Israel. The land is not able to bear all his words. 11 For Amos says, ‘Jeroboam will die by the sword, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of his land.’”

12 Amaziah also said to Amos, “You seer, go, flee away into the land of Judah, and there eat bread, and prophesy there: 13 but don’t prophesy again any more at Bethel; for it is the king’s sanctuary, and it is a royal house!”

14 Then Amos answered Amaziah, “I was no prophet, neither was I a prophet’s son; but I was a herdsman, and a farmer of sycamore figs; 15 and Yahweh took me from following the flock, and Yahweh said to me, ‘Go, prophesy to my people Israel.’ 16 Now therefore listen to Yahweh’s word: ‘You say, Don’t prophesy against Israel, and don’t preach against the house of Isaac.’ 17 Therefore Yahweh says: ‘Your wife shall be a prostitute in the city, and your sons and your daughters shall fall by the sword, and your land shall be divided by line; and you yourself shall die in a land that is unclean, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of his land.’”

Amos 8

1 Thus the Lord Yahweh showed me: behold, a basket of summer fruit.

2 He said, “Amos, what do you see?”

I said, “A basket of summer fruit.”

Then Yahweh said to me,

“The end has come on my people Israel.

I will not again pass by them any more.

3 The songs of the temple will be wailings in that day,” says the Lord Yahweh.

“The dead bodies will be many. In every place they will throw them out with silence.

4 Hear this, you who desire to swallow up the needy,

and cause the poor of the land to fail,

5 Saying, ‘When will the new moon be gone, that we may sell grain?

And the Sabbath, that we may market wheat,

making the ephah[*] small, and the shekel[*] large,

and dealing falsely with balances of deceit;

6 that we may buy the poor for silver,

and the needy for a pair of shoes,

and sell the sweepings with the wheat?’”

7 Yahweh has sworn by the pride of Jacob,

“Surely I will never forget any of their works.

8 Won’t the land tremble for this,

and everyone mourn who dwells in it?

Yes, it will rise up wholly like the River;

and it will be stirred up and sink again, like the River of Egypt.

9 It will happen in that day,” says the Lord Yahweh,

“that I will cause the sun to go down at noon,

and I will darken the earth in the clear day.

10 I will turn your feasts into mourning,

and all your songs into lamentation;

and I will make you wear sackcloth on all your bodies,

and baldness on every head.

I will make it like the mourning for an only son,

and its end like a bitter day.

11 Behold, the days come,” says the Lord Yahweh,

“that I will send a famine in the land,

not a famine of bread,

nor a thirst for water,

but of hearing Yahweh’s words.

12 They will wander from sea to sea,

and from the north even to the east;

they will run back and forth to seek Yahweh’s word,

and will not find it.

13 In that day the beautiful virgins

and the young men will faint for thirst.

14 Those who swear by the sin of Samaria,

and say, ‘As your god, Dan, lives;’

and, ‘As the way of Beersheba lives;’

they will fall, and never rise up again.”

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

a normal shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

Obadiah 1

1 The vision of Obadiah. This is what the Lord[*] Yahweh[*] says about Edom. We have heard news from Yahweh, and an ambassador is sent among the nations, saying, “Arise, and let’s rise up against her in battle. 2 Behold,[*] I have made you small among the nations. You are greatly despised. 3 The pride of your heart has deceived you, you who dwell in the clefts of the rock, whose habitation is high, who says in his heart, ‘Who will bring me down to the ground?’ 4 Though you mount on high as the eagle, and though your nest is set among the stars, I will bring you down from there,” says Yahweh. 5 “If thieves came to you, if robbers by night—oh, what disaster awaits you—wouldn’t they only steal until they had enough? If grape pickers came to you, wouldn’t they leave some gleaning grapes? 6 How Esau will be ransacked! How his hidden treasures are sought out! 7 All the men of your alliance have brought you on your way, even to the border. The men who were at peace with you have deceived you, and prevailed against you. Friends who eat your bread lay a snare under you. There is no understanding in him.”

8 “Won’t I in that day”, says Yahweh, “destroy the wise men out of Edom, and understanding out of the mountain of Esau? 9 Your mighty men, Teman, will be dismayed, to the end that everyone may be cut off from the mountain of Esau by slaughter. 10 For the violence done to your brother Jacob, shame will cover you, and you will be cut off forever. 11 In the day that you stood on the other side, in the day that strangers carried away his substance, and foreigners entered into his gates, and cast lots for Jerusalem, even you were like one of them. 12 But don’t look down on your brother in the day of his disaster, and don’t rejoice over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction. Don’t speak proudly in the day of distress. 13 Don’t enter into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity. Don’t look down on their affliction in the day of their calamity, neither seize their wealth on the day of their calamity. 14 Don’t stand in the crossroads to cut off those of his who escape. Don’t deliver up those of his who remain in the day of distress. 15 For the day of Yahweh is near all the nations! As you have done, it will be done to you. Your deeds will return upon your own head. 16 For as you have drunk on my holy mountain, so will all the nations drink continually. Yes, they will drink, swallow down, and will be as though they had not been. 17 But in Mount Zion, there will be those who escape, and it will be holy. The house of Jacob will possess their possessions. 18 The house of Jacob will be a fire, the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau for stubble. They will burn among them, and devour them. There will not be any remaining to the house of Esau.” Indeed, Yahweh has spoken.

19 Those of the South will possess the mountain of Esau, and those of the lowland, the Philistines. They will possess the field of Ephraim, and the field of Samaria. Benjamin will possess Gilead. 20 The captives of this army of the children of Israel, who are among the Canaanites, will possess even to Zarephath; and the captives of Jerusalem, who are in Sepharad, will possess the cities of the Negev. 21 Saviors will go up on Mount Zion to judge the mountains of Esau, and the kingdom will be Yahweh’s.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Jonah 1

1 Now Yahweh’s[*] word came to Jonah the son of Amittai, saying, 2 “Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach against it, for their wickedness has come up before me.”

3 But Jonah rose up to flee to Tarshish from the presence of Yahweh. He went down to Joppa, and found a ship going to Tarshish; so he paid its fare, and went down into it, to go with them to Tarshish from the presence of Yahweh. 4 But Yahweh sent out a great wind on the sea, and there was a mighty storm on the sea, so that the ship was likely to break up. 5 Then the mariners were afraid, and every man cried to his god. They threw the cargo that was in the ship into the sea to lighten the ship. But Jonah had gone down into the innermost parts of the ship, and he was laying down, and was fast asleep. 6 So the ship master came to him, and said to him, “What do you mean, sleeper? Arise, call on your God![*] Maybe your God[*] will notice us, so that we won’t perish.”

7 They all said to each other, “Come, let us cast lots, that we may know who is responsible for this evil that is on us.” So they cast lots, and the lot fell on Jonah. 8 Then they asked him, “Tell us, please, for whose cause this evil is on us. What is your occupation? Where do you come from? What is your country? Of what people are you?”

9 He said to them, “I am a Hebrew, and I fear Yahweh, the God[*] of heaven, who has made the sea and the dry land.”

10 Then were the men exceedingly afraid, and said to him, “What is this that you have done?” For the men knew that he was fleeing from the presence of Yahweh, because he had told them. 11 Then they said to him, “What shall we do to you, that the sea may be calm to us?” For the sea grew more and more stormy. 12 He said to them, “Take me up, and throw me into the sea. Then the sea will be calm for you; for I know that because of me this great storm is on you.”

13 Nevertheless the men rowed hard to get them back to the land; but they could not, for the sea grew more and more stormy against them. 14 Therefore they cried to Yahweh, and said, “We beg you, Yahweh, we beg you, don’t let us die for this man’s life, and don’t lay on us innocent blood; for you, Yahweh, have done as it pleased you.” 15 So they took up Jonah, and threw him into the sea; and the sea ceased its raging. 16 Then the men feared Yahweh exceedingly; and they offered a sacrifice to Yahweh, and made vows.

17 Yahweh prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah, and Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

or, gods

or, gods

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Jonah 2

1 Then Jonah prayed to Yahweh, his God, out of the fish’s belly. 2 He said,

“I called because of my affliction to Yahweh.

He answered me.

Out of the belly of Sheol[*] I cried.

You heard my voice.

3 For you threw me into the depths,

in the heart of the seas.

The flood was all around me.

All your waves and your billows passed over me.

4 I said, ‘I have been banished from your sight;

yet I will look again toward your holy temple.’

5 The waters surrounded me,

even to the soul.

The deep was around me.

The weeds were wrapped around my head.

6 I went down to the bottoms of the mountains.

The earth barred me in forever:

yet have you brought up my life from the pit, Yahweh my God.

7 “When my soul fainted within me, I remembered Yahweh.

My prayer came in to you, into your holy temple.

8 Those who regard lying vanities forsake their own mercy.

9 But I will sacrifice to you with the voice of thanksgiving.

I will pay that which I have vowed.

Salvation belongs to Yahweh.”

10 Yahweh spoke to the fish, and it vomited out Jonah on the dry land.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Jonah 3

1 Yahweh’s word came to Jonah the second time, saying, 2 “Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach to it the message that I give you.”

3 So Jonah arose, and went to Nineveh, according to Yahweh’s word. Now Nineveh was an exceedingly great city, three days’ journey across. 4 Jonah began to enter into the city a day’s journey, and he cried out, and said, “In forty days, Nineveh will be overthrown!”

5 The people of Nineveh believed God; and they proclaimed a fast, and put on sackcloth, from their greatest even to their least. 6 The news reached the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne, and took off his royal robe, covered himself with sackcloth, and sat in ashes. 7 He made a proclamation and published through Nineveh by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying, “Let neither man nor animal, herd nor flock, taste anything; let them not feed, nor drink water; 8 but let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and animal, and let them cry mightily to God. Yes, let them turn everyone from his evil way, and from the violence that is in his hands. 9 Who knows whether God will not turn and relent, and turn away from his fierce anger, so that we might not perish?”

10 God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way. God relented of the disaster which he said he would do to them, and he didn’t do it.

Jonah 4

1 But it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he was angry. 2 He prayed to Yahweh, and said, “Please, Yahweh, wasn’t this what I said when I was still in my own country? Therefore I hurried to flee to Tarshish, for I knew that you are a gracious God, and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness, and you relent of doing harm. 3 Therefore now, Yahweh, take, I beg you, my life from me; for it is better for me to die than to live.”

4 Yahweh said, “Is it right for you to be angry?”

5 Then Jonah went out of the city, and sat on the east side of the city, and there made himself a booth, and sat under it in the shade, until he might see what would become of the city. 6 Yahweh God prepared a vine, and made it to come up over Jonah, that it might be a shade over his head, to deliver him from his discomfort. So Jonah was exceedingly glad because of the vine. 7 But God prepared a worm at dawn the next day, and it chewed on the vine, so that it withered. 8 When the sun arose, God prepared a sultry east wind; and the sun beat on Jonah’s head, so that he fainted, and requested for himself that he might die, and said, “It is better for me to die than to live.”

9 God said to Jonah, “Is it right for you to be angry about the vine?”

He said, “I am right to be angry, even to death.”

10 Yahweh said, “You have been concerned for the vine, for which you have not labored, neither made it grow; which came up in a night, and perished in a night. 11 Shouldn’t I be concerned for Nineveh, that great city, in which are more than one hundred twenty thousand persons who can’t discern between their right hand and their left hand; and also much livestock?”

Micah 1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word that came to Micah the Morashtite in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem.

2 Hear, you peoples, all of you.

Listen, O earth, and all that is therein:

and let the Lord[*] Yahweh be witness against you,

the Lord from his holy temple.

3 For, behold,[*] Yahweh comes out of his place,

and will come down and tread on the high places of the earth.

4 The mountains melt under him,

and the valleys split apart,

like wax before the fire,

like waters that are poured down a steep place.

5 “All this is for the disobedience of Jacob,

and for the sins of the house of Israel.

What is the disobedience of Jacob?

Isn’t it Samaria?

And what are the high places of Judah?

Aren’t they Jerusalem?

6 Therefore I will make Samaria like a rubble heap of the field,

like places for planting vineyards;

and I will pour down its stones into the valley,

and I will uncover its foundations.

7 All her idols will be beaten to pieces,

and all her temple gifts will be burned with fire,

and all her images I will destroy;

for of the hire of a prostitute has she gathered them,

and to the hire of a prostitute shall they return.”

8 For this I will lament and wail;

I will go stripped and naked;

I will howl like the jackals,

and moan like the daughters of owls.

9 For her wounds are incurable;

for it has come even to Judah.

It reaches to the gate of my people,

even to Jerusalem.

10 Don’t tell it in Gath.

Don’t weep at all.

At Beth Ophrah[*] I have rolled myself in the dust.

11 Pass on, inhabitant of Shaphir, in nakedness and shame.

The inhabitant of Zaanan won’t come out.

The wailing of Beth Ezel will take from you his protection.

12 For the inhabitant of Maroth waits anxiously for good,

because evil has come down from Yahweh to the gate of Jerusalem.

13 Harness the chariot to the swift steed, inhabitant of Lachish.

She was the beginning of sin to the daughter of Zion;

For the transgressions of Israel were found in you.

14 Therefore you will give a parting gift to Moresheth Gath.

The houses of Achzib will be a deceitful thing to the kings of Israel.

15 I will yet bring to you, inhabitant of Mareshah.

He who is the glory of Israel will come to Adullam.

16 Shave your heads,

and cut off your hair for the children of your delight.

Enlarge your baldness like the vulture;

for they have gone into captivity from you!

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Beth Ophrah means literally “House of Dust.”

Micah 2

1 Woe to those who devise iniquity

and work evil on their beds!

When the morning is light, they practice it,

because it is in the power of their hand.

2 They covet fields, and seize them;

and houses, and take them away:

and they oppress a man and his house,

even a man and his heritage.

3 Therefore Yahweh says:

“Behold, I am planning against these people a disaster,

from which you will not remove your necks,

neither will you walk haughtily;

for it is an evil time.

4 In that day they will take up a parable against you,

and lament with a doleful lamentation, saying,

‘We are utterly ruined!

My people’s possession is divided up.

Indeed he takes it from me and assigns our fields to traitors!’”

5 Therefore you will have no one who divides the land by lot in Yahweh’s assembly.

6 “Don’t prophesy!”

They prophesy.

“Don’t prophesy about these things.

Disgrace won’t overtake us.”

7 Shall it be said, O house of Jacob:

“Is Yahweh’s Spirit angry?

Are these his doings?

Don’t my words do good to him who walks blamelessly?”

8 But lately my people have risen up as an enemy.

You strip the robe and clothing from those who pass by without a care, returning from battle.

9 You drive the women of my people out from their pleasant houses;

from their young children you take away my blessing forever.

10 Arise, and depart!

For this is not your resting place,

because of uncleanness that destroys,

even with a grievous destruction.

11 If a man walking in a spirit of falsehood lies:

“I will prophesy to you of wine and of strong drink”;

he would be the prophet of this people.

12 I will surely assemble, Jacob, all of you;

I will surely gather the remnant of Israel;

I will put them together as the sheep of Bozrah,

as a flock in the middle of their pasture;

they will swarm with people.

13 He who breaks open the way goes up before them.

They break through the gate, and go out.

And their king passes on before them,

with Yahweh at their head.

Micah 3

1 I said,

“Please listen, you heads of Jacob,

and rulers of the house of Israel:

Isn’t it for you to know justice?

2 You who hate the good,

and love the evil;

who tear off their skin,

and their flesh from off their bones;

3 who also eat the flesh of my people,

and flay their skin from off them,

and break their bones,

and chop them in pieces, as for the pot,

and as meat within the cauldron.

4 Then they will cry to Yahweh,

but he will not answer them.

Yes, he will hide his face from them at that time,

because they made their deeds evil.”

5 Yahweh says concerning the prophets who lead my people astray; for those who feed their teeth, they proclaim, “Peace!” and whoever doesn’t provide for their mouths, they prepare war against him:

6 “Therefore night is over you, with no vision,

and it is dark to you, that you may not divine;

and the sun will go down on the prophets,

and the day will be black over them.

7 The seers shall be disappointed,

and the diviners confounded.

Yes, they shall all cover their lips;

for there is no answer from God.”[*]

8 But as for me, I am full of power by Yahweh’s Spirit,

and of judgment, and of might,

to declare to Jacob his disobedience,

and to Israel his sin.

9 Please listen to this, you heads of the house of Jacob,

and rulers of the house of Israel,

who abhor justice,

and pervert all equity.

10 They build up Zion with blood,

and Jerusalem with iniquity.

11 Her leaders judge for bribes,

and her priests teach for a price,

and her prophets of it tell fortunes for money:

yet they lean on Yahweh, and say,

“Isn’t Yahweh among us?

No disaster will come on us.”

12 Therefore Zion for your sake will be plowed like a field,

and Jerusalem will become heaps of rubble,

and the mountain of the temple like the high places of a forest.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Micah 4

1 But in the latter days,

it will happen that the mountain of Yahweh’s temple will be established on the top of the mountains,

and it will be exalted above the hills;

and peoples will stream to it.

2 Many nations will go and say,

“Come, and let us go up to the mountain of Yahweh,

and to the house of the God of Jacob;

and he will teach us of his ways,

and we will walk in his paths.”

For the law will go out of Zion,

and Yahweh’s word from Jerusalem;

3 and he will judge between many peoples,

and will decide concerning strong nations afar off.

They will beat their swords into plowshares,

and their spears into pruning hooks.

Nation will not lift up sword against nation,

neither will they learn war any more.

4 But they will sit every man under his vine and under his fig tree;

and no one will make them afraid:

For the mouth of Yahweh of Armies has spoken. 5 Indeed all the nations may walk in the name of their gods;

but we will walk in the name of Yahweh our God forever and ever.

6 “In that day,” says Yahweh,

“I will assemble that which is lame,

and I will gather that which is driven away,

and that which I have afflicted;

7 and I will make that which was lame a remnant,

and that which was cast far off a strong nation:

and Yahweh will reign over them on Mount Zion from then on, even forever.”

8 You, tower of the flock, the hill of the daughter of Zion,

to you it will come,

yes, the former dominion will come,

the kingdom of the daughter of Jerusalem.

9 Now why do you cry out aloud?

Is there no king in you?

Has your counselor perished,

that pains have taken hold of you as of a woman in travail?

10 Be in pain, and labor to give birth, daughter of Zion,

like a woman in travail;

for now you will go out of the city,

and will dwell in the field,

and will come even to Babylon.

There you will be rescued.

There Yahweh will redeem you from the hand of your enemies.

11 Now many nations have assembled against you, that say,

“Let her be defiled,

and let our eye gloat over Zion.”

12 But they don’t know the thoughts of Yahweh,

neither do they understand his counsel;

for he has gathered them like the sheaves to the threshing floor.

13 Arise and thresh, daughter of Zion;

for I will make your horn iron,

and I will make your hoofs brass;

and you will beat in pieces many peoples:

and I will devote their gain to Yahweh,

and their substance to the Lord of the whole earth.

Micah 5

1 Now you shall gather yourself in troops,

daughter of troops.

He has laid siege against us.

They will strike the judge of Israel with a rod on the cheek.

2 But you, Bethlehem Ephrathah,

being small among the clans of Judah,

out of you one will come out to me that is to be ruler in Israel;

whose goings out are from of old, from ancient times.

3 Therefore he will abandon them until the time that she who is in labor gives birth.

Then the rest of his brothers will return to the children of Israel.

4 He shall stand, and shall shepherd in the strength of Yahweh,

in the majesty of the name of Yahweh his God:

and they will live, for then he will be great to the ends of the earth.

5 He will be our peace when Assyria invades our land,

and when he marches through our fortresses,

then we will raise against him seven shepherds,

and eight leaders of men.

6 They will rule the land of Assyria with the sword,

and the land of Nimrod in its gates.

He will deliver us from the Assyrian,

when he invades our land,

and when he marches within our border.

7 The remnant of Jacob will be among many peoples,

like dew from Yahweh,

like showers on the grass,

that don’t wait for man,

nor wait for the sons of men.

8 The remnant of Jacob will be among the nations,

among many peoples,

like a lion among the animals of the forest,

like a young lion among the flocks of sheep;

who, if he goes through, treads down and tears in pieces,

and there is no one to deliver.

9 Let your hand be lifted up above your adversaries,

and let all of your enemies be cut off.

10 “It will happen in that day”, says Yahweh,

“that I will cut off your horses out from among you,

and will destroy your chariots.

11 I will cut off the cities of your land,

and will tear down all your strongholds.

12 I will destroy witchcraft from your hand;

and you shall have no soothsayers.

13 I will cut off your engraved images and your pillars out from among you;

and you shall no more worship the work of your hands.

14 I will uproot your Asherah poles out from among you;

and I will destroy your cities.

15 I will execute vengeance in anger,

and wrath on the nations that didn’t listen.”

Micah 6

1 Listen now to what Yahweh says:

“Arise, plead your case before the mountains,

and let the hills hear what you have to say.

2 Hear, you mountains, Yahweh’s controversy,

and you enduring foundations of the earth;

for Yahweh has a controversy with his people,

and he will contend with Israel.

3 My people, what have I done to you?

How have I burdened you?

Answer me!

4 For I brought you up out of the land of Egypt,

and redeemed you out of the house of bondage.

I sent before you Moses, Aaron, and Miriam.

5 My people, remember now what Balak king of Moab devised,

and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him from Shittim to Gilgal,

that you may know the righteous acts of Yahweh.”

6 How shall I come before Yahweh,

and bow myself before the exalted God?

Shall I come before him with burnt offerings,

with calves a year old?

7 Will Yahweh be pleased with thousands of rams?

With tens of thousands of rivers of oil?

Shall I give my firstborn for my disobedience?

The fruit of my body for the sin of my soul?

8 He has shown you, O man, what is good.

What does Yahweh require of you, but to act justly,

to love mercy, and to walk humbly with your God?

9 Yahweh’s voice calls to the city,

and wisdom sees your name:

“Listen to the rod,

and he who appointed it.

10 Are there yet treasures of wickedness in the house of the wicked,

and a short ephah[*] that is accursed?

11 Shall I be pure with dishonest scales,

and with a bag of deceitful weights?

12 Her rich men are full of violence,

her inhabitants speak lies,

and their tongue is deceitful in their speech.

13 Therefore I also have struck you with a grievous wound.

I have made you desolate because of your sins.

14 You shall eat, but not be satisfied.

Your humiliation will be within you.

You will store up, but not save;

and that which you save I will give up to the sword.

15 You will sow, but won’t reap.

You will tread the olives, but won’t anoint yourself with oil;

and crush grapes, but won’t drink the wine.

16 For the statutes of Omri are kept,

and all the works of Ahab’s house.

You walk in their counsels,

that I may make you a ruin,

and her inhabitants a hissing;

And you will bear the reproach of my people.”

An ephah is a measure of volume (about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel), and a short ephah is made smaller than a full ephah for the purpose of cheating customers.

Micah 7

1 Misery is mine!

Indeed, I am like one who gathers the summer fruits, as gleanings of the vineyard:

There is no cluster of grapes to eat.

My soul desires to eat the early fig.

2 The godly man has perished out of the earth,

and there is no one upright among men.

They all lie in wait for blood;

every man hunts his brother with a net.

3 Their hands are on that which is evil to do it diligently.

The ruler and judge ask for a bribe;

and the powerful man dictates the evil desire of his soul.

Thus they conspire together.

4 The best of them is like a brier.

The most upright is worse than a thorn hedge.

The day of your watchmen,

even your visitation, has come;

now is the time of their confusion.

5 Don’t trust in a neighbor.

Don’t put confidence in a friend.

With the woman lying in your embrace,

be careful of the words of your mouth!

6 For the son dishonors the father,

the daughter rises up against her mother,

the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law;

a man’s enemies are the men of his own house.

7 But as for me, I will look to Yahweh.

I will wait for the God of my salvation.

My God will hear me.

8 Don’t rejoice against me, my enemy.

When I fall, I will arise.

When I sit in darkness, Yahweh will be a light to me.

9 I will bear the indignation of Yahweh,

because I have sinned against him,

until he pleads my case, and executes judgment for me.

He will bring me out to the light.

I will see his righteousness.

10 Then my enemy will see it,

and shame will cover her who said to me,

where is Yahweh your God?

Then my enemy will see me and will cover her shame.

Now she will be trodden down like the mire of the streets.

11 A day to build your walls—

In that day, he will extend your boundary.

12 In that day they will come to you from Assyria and the cities of Egypt,

and from Egypt even to the River,

and from sea to sea,

and mountain to mountain.

13 Yet the land will be desolate because of those who dwell therein,

for the fruit of their doings.

14 Shepherd your people with your staff,

the flock of your heritage,

who dwell by themselves in a forest,

in the middle of fertile pasture land, let them feed;

in Bashan and Gilead, as in the days of old.

15 “As in the days of your coming out of the land of Egypt,

I will show them marvelous things.”

16 The nations will see and be ashamed of all their might.

They will lay their hand on their mouth.

Their ears will be deaf.

17 They will lick the dust like a serpent.

Like crawling things of the earth they shall come trembling out of their dens.

They will come with fear to Yahweh our God,

and will be afraid because of you.

18 Who is a God like you, who pardons iniquity,

and passes over the disobedience of the remnant of his heritage?

He doesn’t retain his anger forever,

because he delights in loving kindness.

19 He will again have compassion on us.

He will tread our iniquities under foot;

and you will cast all their sins into the depths of the sea.

20 You will give truth to Jacob,

and mercy to Abraham,

as you have sworn to our fathers from the days of old.

Nahum 1

1 A revelation about Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite. 2 Yahweh[*] is a jealous God[*] and avenges. Yahweh avenges and is full of wrath. Yahweh takes vengeance on his adversaries, and he maintains wrath against his enemies. 3 Yahweh is slow to anger, and great in power, and will by no means leave the guilty unpunished. Yahweh has his way in the whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds are the dust of his feet. 4 He rebukes the sea, and makes it dry, and dries up all the rivers. Bashan languishes, and Carmel; and the flower of Lebanon languishes. 5 The mountains quake before him, and the hills melt away. The earth trembles at his presence, yes, the world, and all who dwell in it. 6 Who can stand before his indignation? Who can endure the fierceness of his anger? His wrath is poured out like fire, and the rocks are broken apart by him. 7 Yahweh is good, a stronghold in the day of trouble; and he knows those who take refuge in him. 8 But with an overflowing flood, he will make a full end of her place, and will pursue his enemies into darkness. 9 What do you plot against Yahweh? He will make a full end. Affliction won’t rise up the second time. 10 For entangled like thorns, and drunken as with their drink, they are consumed utterly like dry stubble. 11 There is one gone out of you, who devises evil against Yahweh, who counsels wickedness. 12 Yahweh says: “Though they be in full strength, and likewise many, even so they will be cut down, and he shall pass away. Though I have afflicted you, I will afflict you no more. 13 Now will I break his yoke from off you, and will burst your bonds apart.” 14 Yahweh has commanded concerning you: “No more descendants will bear your name. Out of the house of your gods, will I cut off the engraved image and the molten image. I will make your grave, for you are vile.”

15 Behold,[*] on the mountains the feet of him who brings good news, who publishes peace! Keep your feasts, Judah! Perform your vows, for the wicked one will no more pass through you. He is utterly cut off.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Nahum 2

1 He who dashes in pieces has come up against you. Keep the fortress! Watch the way! Strengthen your waist! Fortify your power mightily! 2 For Yahweh restores the excellency of Jacob, as the excellency of Israel; for the destroyers have destroyed them, and ruined their vine branches. 3 The shield of his mighty men is made red. The valiant men are in scarlet. The chariots flash with steel in the day of his preparation, and the pine spears are brandished. 4 The chariots rage in the streets. They rush back and forth in the wide ways. Their appearance is like torches. They run like the lightnings. 5 He summons his picked troops. They stumble on their way. They dash to its wall, and the protective shield is put in place. 6 The gates of the rivers are opened, and the palace is dissolved. 7 It is decreed: she is uncovered, she is carried away; and her servants moan as with the voice of doves, beating on their breasts. 8 But Nineveh has been from of old like a pool of water, yet they flee away. “Stop! Stop!” they cry, but no one looks back. 9 Take the plunder of silver. Take the plunder of gold, for there is no end of the store, the glory of all goodly furniture. 10 She is empty, void, and waste. The heart melts, the knees knock together, their bodies and faces have grown pale. 11 Where is the den of the lions, and the feeding place of the young lions, where the lion and the lioness walked, the lion’s cubs, and no one made them afraid? 12 The lion tore in pieces enough for his cubs, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his caves with the kill, and his dens with prey. 13 “Behold, I am against you,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and I will burn her chariots in the smoke, and the sword will devour your young lions; and I will cut off your prey from the earth, and the voice of your messengers will no longer be heard.”

Nahum 3

1 Woe to the bloody city! It is all full of lies and robbery. The prey doesn’t depart. 2 The noise of the whip, the noise of the rattling of wheels, prancing horses, and bounding chariots, 3 the horseman mounting, and the flashing sword, the glittering spear, and a multitude of slain, and a great heap of corpses, and there is no end of the bodies. They stumble on their bodies, 4 because of the multitude of the prostitution of the alluring prostitute, the mistress of witchcraft, who sells nations through her prostitution, and families through her witchcraft. 5 “Behold, I am against you,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and I will lift your skirts over your face. I will show the nations your nakedness, and the kingdoms your shame. 6 I will throw abominable filth on you, and make you vile, and will set you a spectacle. 7 It will happen that all those who look at you will flee from you, and say, ‘Nineveh is laid waste! Who will mourn for her?’ Where will I seek comforters for you?”

8 Are you better than No-Amon,[*] who was situated among the rivers, who had the waters around her; whose rampart was the sea, and her wall was of the sea? 9 Cush and Egypt were her boundless strength. Put and Libya were her helpers. 10 Yet was she carried away. She went into captivity. Her young children also were dashed in pieces at the head of all the streets, and they cast lots for her honorable men, and all her great men were bound in chains. 11 You also will be drunken. You will be hidden. You also will seek a stronghold because of the enemy. 12 All your fortresses will be like fig trees with the first-ripe figs: if they are shaken, they fall into the mouth of the eater. 13 Behold, your troops among you are women. The gates of your land are set wide open to your enemies. The fire has devoured your bars. 14 Draw water for the siege. Strengthen your fortresses. Go into the clay, and tread the mortar. Make the brick kiln strong. 15 There the fire will devour you. The sword will cut you off. It will devour you like the grasshopper. Multiply like grasshoppers. Multiply like the locust. 16 You have increased your merchants more than the stars of the skies. The grasshopper strips, and flees away. 17 Your guards are like the locusts, and your officials like the swarms of locusts, which settle on the walls on a cold day, but when the sun appears, they flee away, and their place is not known where they are. 18 Your shepherds slumber, king of Assyria. Your nobles lie down. Your people are scattered on the mountains, and there is no one to gather them. 19 There is no healing your wound, for your injury is fatal. All who hear the report of you clap their hands over you; for who hasn’t felt your endless cruelty?

or, Thebes

Habakkuk 1

1 The revelation which Habakkuk the prophet saw. 2 Yahweh,[*] how long will I cry, and you will not hear? I cry out to you “Violence!” and will you not save? 3 Why do you show me iniquity, and look at perversity? For destruction and violence are before me. There is strife, and contention rises up. 4 Therefore the law is paralyzed, and justice never prevails; for the wicked surround the righteous; therefore justice comes out perverted.

5 “Look among the nations, watch, and wonder marvelously; for I am working a work in your days, which you will not believe though it is told you. 6 For, behold,[*] I raise up the Chaldeans, that bitter and hasty nation, that march through the width of the earth, to possess dwelling places that are not theirs. 7 They are feared and dreaded. Their judgment and their dignity proceed from themselves. 8 Their horses also are swifter than leopards, and are more fierce than the evening wolves. Their horsemen press proudly on. Yes, their horsemen come from afar. They fly as an eagle that hurries to devour. 9 All of them come for violence. Their hordes face the desert. He gathers prisoners like sand. 10 Yes, he scoffs at kings, and princes are a derision to him. He laughs at every stronghold, for he builds up an earthen ramp, and takes it. 11 Then he sweeps by like the wind, and goes on. He is indeed guilty, whose strength is his god.”

12 Aren’t you from everlasting, Yahweh my God,[*] my Holy One? We will not die. Yahweh, you have appointed him for judgment. You, Rock, have established him to punish. 13 You who have purer eyes than to see evil, and who cannot look on perversity, why do you tolerate those who deal treacherously, and keep silent when the wicked swallows up the man who is more righteous than he, 14 and make men like the fish of the sea, like the creeping things, that have no ruler over them? 15 He takes up all of them with the hook. He catches them in his net, and gathers them in his dragnet. Therefore he rejoices and is glad. 16 Therefore he sacrifices to his net, and burns incense to his dragnet, because by them his life is luxurious, and his food is good. 17 Will he therefore continually empty his net, and kill the nations without mercy?

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Habakkuk 2

1 I will stand at my watch, and set myself on the ramparts, and will look out to see what he will say to me, and what I will answer concerning my complaint.

2 Yahweh answered me, “Write the vision, and make it plain on tablets, that he who runs may read it. 3 For the vision is yet for the appointed time, and it hurries toward the end, and won’t prove false. Though it takes time, wait for it; because it will surely come. It won’t delay. 4 Behold, his soul is puffed up. It is not upright in him, but the righteous will live by his faith. 5 Yes, moreover, wine is treacherous. A haughty man who doesn’t stay at home, who enlarges his desire as Sheol,[*] and he is like death, and can’t be satisfied, but gathers to himself all nations, and heaps to himself all peoples. 6 Won’t all these take up a parable against him, and a taunting proverb against him, and say, ‘Woe to him who increases that which is not his, and who enriches himself by extortion! How long?’ 7 Won’t your debtors rise up suddenly, and wake up those who make you tremble, and you will be their victim? 8 Because you have plundered many nations, all the remnant of the peoples will plunder you, because of men’s blood, and for the violence done to the land, to the city and to all who dwell in it. 9 Woe to him who gets an evil gain for his house, that he may set his nest on high, that he may be delivered from the hand of evil! 10 You have devised shame to your house, by cutting off many peoples, and have sinned against your soul. 11 For the stone will cry out of the wall, and the beam out of the woodwork will answer it. 12 Woe to him who builds a town with blood, and establishes a city by iniquity! 13 Behold, isn’t it of Yahweh of Armies that the peoples labor for the fire, and the nations weary themselves for vanity? 14 For the earth will be filled with the knowledge of Yahweh’s glory, as the waters cover the sea.

15 “Woe to him who gives his neighbor drink, pouring your inflaming wine until they are drunk, so that you may gaze at their naked bodies! 16 You are filled with shame, and not glory. You will also drink, and be exposed! The cup of Yahweh’s right hand will come around to you, and disgrace will cover your glory. 17 For the violence done to Lebanon will overwhelm you, and the destruction of the animals, which made them afraid; because of men’s blood, and for the violence done to the land, to every city and to those who dwell in them.

18 “What value does the engraved image have, that its maker has engraved it; the molten image, even the teacher of lies, that he who fashions its form trusts in it, to make mute idols? 19 Woe to him who says to the wood, ‘Awake!’ or to the mute stone, ‘Arise!’ Shall this teach? Behold, it is overlaid with gold and silver, and there is no breath at all within it. 20 But Yahweh is in his holy temple. Let all the earth be silent before him!”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Habakkuk 3

1 A prayer of Habakkuk, the prophet, set to victorious music.

2 Yahweh, I have heard of your fame.

I stand in awe of your deeds, Yahweh.

Renew your work in the middle of the years.

In the middle of the years make it known.

In wrath, you remember mercy.

3 God came from Teman,

the Holy One from Mount Paran. Selah.

His glory covered the heavens,

and his praise filled the earth.

4 His splendor is like the sunrise.

Rays shine from his hand, where his power is hidden.

5 Plague went before him,

and pestilence followed his feet.

6 He stood, and shook the earth.

He looked, and made the nations tremble.

The ancient mountains were crumbled.

The age-old hills collapsed.

His ways are eternal.

7 I saw the tents of Cushan in affliction.

The dwellings of the land of Midian trembled.

8 Was Yahweh displeased with the rivers?

Was your anger against the rivers,

or your wrath against the sea,

that you rode on your horses,

on your chariots of salvation?

9 You uncovered your bow.

You called for your sworn arrows. Selah.

You split the earth with rivers.

10 The mountains saw you, and were afraid.

The storm of waters passed by.

The deep roared and lifted up its hands on high.

11 The sun and moon stood still in the sky,

at the light of your arrows as they went,

at the shining of your glittering spear.

12 You marched through the land in wrath.

You threshed the nations in anger.

13 You went out for the salvation of your people,

for the salvation of your anointed.

You crushed the head of the land of wickedness.

You stripped them head to foot. Selah.

14 You pierced the heads of his warriors with their own spears.

They came as a whirlwind to scatter me,

gloating as if to devour the wretched in secret.

15 You trampled the sea with your horses,

churning mighty waters.

16 I heard, and my body trembled.

My lips quivered at the voice.

Rottenness enters into my bones, and I tremble in my place,

because I must wait quietly for the day of trouble,

for the coming up of the people who invade us.

17 For though the fig tree doesn’t flourish,

nor fruit be in the vines;

the labor of the olive fails,

the fields yield no food;

the flocks are cut off from the fold,

and there is no herd in the stalls:

18 yet I will rejoice in Yahweh.

I will be joyful in the God of my salvation!

19 Yahweh, the Lord,[*] is my strength.

He makes my feet like deer’s feet,

and enables me to go in high places.

For the music director, on my stringed instruments.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Zephaniah 1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word which came to Zephaniah, the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hezekiah, in the days of Josiah, the son of Amon, king of Judah. 2 I will utterly sweep away everything off of the surface of the earth, says Yahweh. 3 I will sweep away man and animal. I will sweep away the birds of the sky, the fish of the sea, and the heaps of rubble with the wicked. I will cut off man from the surface of the earth, says Yahweh. 4 I will stretch out my hand against Judah, and against all the inhabitants of Jerusalem. I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place: the name of the idolatrous and pagan priests, 5 those who worship the army of the sky on the housetops, those who worship and swear by Yahweh and also swear by Malcam, 6 those who have turned back from following Yahweh, and those who haven’t sought Yahweh nor inquired after him. 7 Be silent at the presence of the Lord[*] Yahweh, for the day of Yahweh is at hand. For Yahweh has prepared a sacrifice. He has consecrated his guests. 8 It will happen in the day of Yahweh’s sacrifice, that I will punish the princes, the king’s sons, and all those who are clothed with foreign clothing. 9 In that day, I will punish all those who leap over the threshold, who fill their master’s house with violence and deceit. 10 In that day, says Yahweh, there will be the noise of a cry from the fish gate, a wailing from the second quarter, and a great crashing from the hills. 11 Wail, you inhabitants of Maktesh, for all the people of Canaan are undone! All those who were loaded with silver are cut off. 12 It will happen at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with lamps, and I will punish the men who are settled on their dregs, who say in their heart, “Yahweh will not do good, neither will he do evil.” 13 Their wealth will become a plunder, and their houses a desolation. Yes, they will build houses, but won’t inhabit them. They will plant vineyards, but won’t drink their wine. 14 The great day of Yahweh is near. It is near, and hurries greatly, the voice of the day of Yahweh. The mighty man cries there bitterly. 15 That day is a day of wrath, a day of distress and anguish, a day of trouble and ruin, a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and blackness, 16 a day of the trumpet and alarm, against the fortified cities, and against the high battlements. 17 I will bring distress on men, that they will walk like blind men, because they have sinned against Yahweh, and their blood will be poured out like dust, and their flesh like dung. 18 Neither their silver nor their gold will be able to deliver them in the day of Yahweh’s wrath, but the whole land will be devoured by the fire of his jealousy; for he will make an end, yes, a terrible end, of all those who dwell in the land.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Haggai 1

1 In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, Yahweh’s[*] word came by Haggai, the prophet, to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying, 2 “This is what Yahweh of Armies says: These people say, ‘The time hasn’t yet come, the time for Yahweh’s house to be built.’”

3 Then Yahweh’s word came by Haggai, the prophet, saying, 4 “Is it a time for you yourselves to dwell in your paneled houses, while this house lies waste? 5 Now therefore this is what Yahweh of Armies says: Consider your ways. 6 You have sown much, and bring in little. You eat, but you don’t have enough. You drink, but you aren’t filled with drink. You clothe yourselves, but no one is warm, and he who earns wages earns wages to put them into a bag with holes in it.”

7 This is what Yahweh of Armies says: “Consider your ways. 8 Go up to the mountain, bring wood, and build the house. I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified,” says Yahweh. 9 “You looked for much, and, behold,[*] it came to little; and when you brought it home, I blew it away. Why?” says Yahweh of Armies, “Because of my house that lies waste, while each of you is busy with his own house. 10 Therefore for your sake the heavens withhold the dew, and the earth withholds its fruit. 11 I called for a drought on the land, on the mountains, on the grain, on the new wine, on the oil, on that which the ground produces, on men, on livestock, and on all the labor of the hands.”

12 Then Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed Yahweh, their God’s[*] voice, and the words of Haggai, the prophet, as Yahweh, their God, had sent him; and the people feared Yahweh.

13 Then Haggai, Yahweh’s messenger, spoke Yahweh’s message to the people, saying, “I am with you,” says Yahweh.

14 Yahweh stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and worked on the house of Yahweh of Armies, their God, 15 in the twenty-fourth day of the month, in the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Haggai 2

1 In the seventh month, in the twenty-first day of the month, Yahweh’s word came by Haggai the prophet, saying, 2 “Speak now to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying, 3 ‘Who is left among you who saw this house in its former glory? How do you see it now? Isn’t it in your eyes as nothing? 4 Yet now be strong, Zerubbabel,’ says Yahweh. ‘Be strong, Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest. Be strong, all you people of the land,’ says Yahweh, ‘and work, for I am with you,’ says Yahweh of Armies. 5 This is the word that I covenanted with you when you came out of Egypt, and my Spirit lived among you. ‘Don’t be afraid.’ 6 For this is what Yahweh of Armies says: ‘Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, the earth, the sea, and the dry land; 7 and I will shake all nations. The precious things of all nations will come, and I will fill this house with glory, says Yahweh of Armies. 8 The silver is mine, and the gold is mine,’ says Yahweh of Armies. 9 ‘The latter glory of this house will be greater than the former,’ says Yahweh of Armies; ‘and in this place will I give peace,’ says Yahweh of Armies.”

10 In the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, Yahweh’s word came by Haggai the prophet, saying, 11 “Yahweh of Armies says: Ask now the priests concerning the law, saying, 12 ‘If someone carries holy meat in the fold of his garment, and with his fold touches bread, stew, wine, oil, or any food, will it become holy?’”

The priests answered, “No.”

13 Then Haggai said, “If one who is unclean by reason of a dead body touch any of these, will it be unclean?”

The priests answered, “It will be unclean.”

14 Then Haggai answered, “‘So is this people, and so is this nation before me,’ says Yahweh; ‘and so is every work of their hands. That which they offer there is unclean. 15 Now, please consider from this day and backward, before a stone was laid on a stone in Yahweh’s temple. 16 Through all that time, when one came to a heap of twenty measures, there were only ten. When one came to the wine vat to draw out fifty, there were only twenty. 17 I struck you with blight, mildew, and hail in all the work of your hands; yet you didn’t turn to me,’ says Yahweh. 18 ‘Consider, please, from this day and backward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, since the day that the foundation of Yahweh’s temple was laid, consider it. 19 Is the seed yet in the barn? Yes, the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate, and the olive tree haven’t produced. From today I will bless you.’”

20 Yahweh’s word came the second time to Haggai in the twenty-fourth day of the month, saying, 21 “Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying, ‘I will shake the heavens and the earth. 22 I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms. I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations. I will overthrow the chariots, and those who ride in them. The horses and their riders will come down, everyone by the sword of his brother. 23 In that day, says Yahweh of Armies, will I take you, Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of Shealtiel,’ says Yahweh, ‘and will make you as a signet, for I have chosen you,’ says Yahweh of Armies.”

Zechariah 1

1 In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, Yahweh’s[*] word came to Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, the prophet, saying, 2 “Yahweh was very displeased with your fathers. 3 Therefore tell them: Yahweh of Armies says: ‘Return to me,’ says Yahweh of Armies, ‘and I will return to you,’ says Yahweh of Armies. 4 Don’t you be like your fathers, to whom the former prophets proclaimed, saying: Yahweh of Armies says, ‘Return now from your evil ways, and from your evil doings;’ but they did not hear, nor listen to me, says Yahweh. 5 Your fathers, where are they? And the prophets, do they live forever? 6 But my words and my decrees, which I commanded my servants the prophets, didn’t they overtake your fathers?

“Then they repented and said, ‘Just as Yahweh of Armies determined to do to us, according to our ways, and according to our practices, so he has dealt with us.’” 7 On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Shebat, in the second year of Darius, Yahweh’s word came to Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo, the prophet, saying, 8 “I had a vision in the night, and behold,[*] a man riding on a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle trees that were in a ravine; and behind him there were red, brown, and white horses. 9 Then I asked, ‘My lord, what are these?’”

The angel who talked with me said to me, “I will show you what these are.”

10 The man who stood among the myrtle trees answered, “They are the ones Yahweh has sent to go back and forth through the earth.”

11 They reported to Yahweh’s angel who stood among the myrtle trees, and said, “We have walked back and forth through the earth, and behold, all the earth is at rest and in peace.”

12 Then Yahweh’s angel replied, “O Yahweh of Armies, how long will you not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which you have had indignation these seventy years?”

13 Yahweh answered the angel who talked with me with kind and comforting words. 14 So the angel who talked with me said to me, “Proclaim, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says: “I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great jealousy. 15 I am very angry with the nations that are at ease; for I was but a little displeased, but they added to the calamity.” 16 Therefore Yahweh says: “I have returned to Jerusalem with mercy. My house shall be built in it,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and a line shall be stretched out over Jerusalem.”’

17 “Proclaim further, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says: “My cities will again overflow with prosperity, and Yahweh will again comfort Zion, and will again choose Jerusalem.”’”

18 I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, four horns. 19 I asked the angel who talked with me, “What are these?”

He answered me, “These are the horns which have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.”

20 Yahweh showed me four craftsmen. 21 Then I asked, “What are these coming to do?”

He said, “These are the horns which scattered Judah, so that no man lifted up his head; but these have come to terrify them, to cast down the horns of the nations, which lifted up their horn against the land of Judah to scatter it.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Zechariah 2

1 I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, a man with a measuring line in his hand. 2 Then I asked, “Where are you going?”

He said to me, “To measure Jerusalem, to see what is its width and what is its length.”

3 Behold, the angel who talked with me went out, and another angel went out to meet him, 4 and said to him, “Run, speak to this young man, saying, ‘Jerusalem will be inhabited as villages without walls, because of the multitude of men and livestock in it. 5 For I,’ says Yahweh, ‘will be to her a wall of fire around it, and I will be the glory in the middle of her. 6 Come! Come! Flee from the land of the north,’ says Yahweh; ‘for I have spread you abroad as the four winds of the sky,’ says Yahweh. 7 ‘Come, Zion! Escape, you who dwell with the daughter of Babylon.’ 8 For Yahweh of Armies says: ‘For honor he has sent me to the nations which plundered you; for he who touches you touches the apple of his eye. 9 For, behold, I will shake my hand over them, and they will be a plunder to those who served them; and you will know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me. 10 Sing and rejoice, daughter of Zion; for, behold, I come, and I will dwell within you,’ says Yahweh. 11 Many nations shall join themselves to Yahweh in that day, and shall be my people; and I will dwell among you, and you shall know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me to you. 12 Yahweh will inherit Judah as his portion in the holy land, and will again choose Jerusalem. 13 Be silent, all flesh, before Yahweh; for he has roused himself from his holy habitation!”

Zechariah 3

1 He showed me Joshua the high priest standing before Yahweh’s angel, and Satan standing at his right hand to be his adversary. 2 Yahweh said to Satan, “Yahweh rebuke you, Satan! Yes, Yahweh who has chosen Jerusalem rebuke you! Isn’t this a burning stick plucked out of the fire?”

3 Now Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and was standing before the angel. 4 He answered and spoke to those who stood before him, saying, “Take the filthy garments off of him.” To him he said, “Behold, I have caused your iniquity to pass from you, and I will clothe you with rich clothing.”

5 I said, “Let them set a clean turban on his head.”

So they set a clean turban on his head, and clothed him; and Yahweh’s angel was standing by. 6 Yahweh’s angel protested to Joshua, saying, 7 “Yahweh of Armies says: ‘If you will walk in my ways, and if you will follow my instructions, then you also shall judge my house, and shall also keep my courts, and I will give you a place of access among these who stand by. 8 Hear now, Joshua the high priest, you and your fellows who sit before you; for they are men who are a sign: for, behold, I will bring out my servant, the Branch. 9 For, behold, the stone that I have set before Joshua; on one stone are seven eyes: behold, I will engrave its engraving,’ says Yahweh of Armies, ‘and I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day. 10 In that day,’ says Yahweh of Armies, ‘you will invite every man his neighbor under the vine and under the fig tree.’”

Zechariah 5

1 Then again I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, a flying scroll. 2 He said to me, “What do you see?”

I answered, “I see a flying scroll; its length is twenty cubits,[*] and its width ten cubits.”

3 Then he said to me, “This is the curse that goes out over the surface of the whole land; for everyone who steals shall be cut off according to it on the one side; and everyone who swears falsely shall be cut off according to it on the other side. 4 I will cause it to go out,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and it will enter into the house of the thief, and into the house of him who swears falsely by my name; and it will remain in the middle of his house, and will destroy it with its timber and its stones.”

5 Then the angel who talked with me came forward, and said to me, “Lift up now your eyes, and see what is this that is appearing.”

6 I said, “What is it?”

He said, “This is the ephah[*] basket that is appearing.” He said moreover, “This is their appearance in all the land 7 (and behold, a talent[*] of lead was lifted up); and this is a woman sitting in the middle of the ephah[*] basket.” 8 He said, “This is Wickedness”; and he threw her down into the middle of the ephah basket; and he threw the weight of lead on its mouth.

9 Then lifted I up my eyes, and saw, and behold, there were two women, and the wind was in their wings. Now they had wings like the wings of a stork, and they lifted up the ephah basket between earth and the sky. 10 Then I said to the angel who talked with me, “Where are these carrying the ephah basket?”

11 He said to me, “To build her a house in the land of Shinar. When it is prepared, she will be set there in her own place.”

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

An ephah is a measure of volume of about 22 liters, 5.8 U. S. gallons, or about 2/3 of a bushel.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds.

1 ephah is about 22 liters or about 2/3 of a bushel

Zechariah 6

1 Again I lifted up my eyes, and saw, and behold, four chariots came out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of brass. 2 In the first chariot were red horses; in the second chariot black horses; 3 in the third chariot white horses; and in the fourth chariot dappled horses, all of them powerful. 4 Then I asked the angel who talked with me, “What are these, my lord?”

5 The angel answered me, “These are the four winds of the sky, which go out from standing before the Lord of all the earth. 6 The one with the black horses goes out toward the north country; and the white went out after them; and the dappled went out toward the south country.” 7 The strong went out, and sought to go that they might walk back and forth through the earth: and he said, “Go around and through the earth!” So they walked back and forth through the earth.

8 Then he called to me, and spoke to me, saying, “Behold, those who go toward the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country.”

9 Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, 10 “Take of them of the captivity, even of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah; and come the same day, and go into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah, where they have come from Babylon. 11 Yes, take silver and gold, and make crowns, and set them on the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest; 12 and speak to him, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies says, “Behold, the man whose name is the Branch: and he shall grow up out of his place; and he shall build Yahweh’s temple; 13 even he shall build Yahweh’s temple; and he shall bear the glory, and shall sit and rule on his throne; and he shall be a priest on his throne; and the counsel of peace shall be between them both. 14 The crowns shall be to Helem, and to Tobijah, and to Jedaiah, and to Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in Yahweh’s temple. 15 Those who are far off shall come and build in Yahweh’s temple; and you shall know that Yahweh of Armies has sent me to you. This will happen, if you will diligently obey Yahweh your God’s voice.”’”[*]

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Zechariah 7

1 In the fourth year of king Darius, Yahweh’s word came to Zechariah in the fourth day of the ninth month, the month of Chislev. 2 The people of Bethel sent Sharezer and Regem Melech, and their men, to entreat Yahweh’s favor, 3 and to speak to the priests of the house of Yahweh of Armies, and to the prophets, saying, “Should I weep in the fifth month, separating myself, as I have done these so many years?”

4 Then the word of Yahweh of Armies came to me, saying, 5 “Speak to all the people of the land, and to the priests, saying, ‘When you fasted and mourned in the fifth and in the seventh month for these seventy years, did you at all fast to me, really to me? 6 When you eat, and when you drink, don’t you eat for yourselves, and drink for yourselves? 7 Aren’t these the words which Yahweh proclaimed by the former prophets, when Jerusalem was inhabited and in prosperity, and its cities around her, and the South and the lowland were inhabited?’”

8 Yahweh’s word came to Zechariah, saying, 9 “Thus has Yahweh of Armies spoken, saying, ‘Execute true judgment, and show kindness and compassion every man to his brother. 10 Don’t oppress the widow, nor the fatherless, the foreigner, nor the poor; and let none of you devise evil against his brother in your heart.’ 11 But they refused to listen, and turned their backs, and stopped their ears, that they might not hear. 12 Yes, they made their hearts as hard as flint, lest they might hear the law, and the words which Yahweh of Armies had sent by his Spirit by the former prophets. Therefore great wrath came from Yahweh of Armies. 13 It has come to pass that, as he called, and they refused to listen, so they will call, and I will not listen,” said Yahweh of Armies; 14 “but I will scatter them with a whirlwind among all the nations which they have not known. Thus the land was desolate after them, so that no man passed through nor returned: for they made the pleasant land desolate.”

Zechariah 9

1 A revelation.

Yahweh’s word is against the land of Hadrach,

and will rest upon Damascus;

for the eye of man

and of all the tribes of Israel is toward Yahweh;

2 and Hamath, also, which borders on it;

Tyre and Sidon, because they are very wise.

3 Tyre built herself a stronghold,

and heaped up silver like the dust,

and fine gold like the mire of the streets.

4 Behold, the Lord will dispossess her,

and he will strike her power in the sea;

and she will be devoured with fire.

5 Ashkelon will see it, and fear;

Gaza also, and will writhe in agony;

as will Ekron, for her expectation will be disappointed;

and the king will perish from Gaza,

and Ashkelon will not be inhabited.

6 Foreigners will dwell in Ashdod,

and I will cut off the pride of the Philistines.

7 I will take away his blood out of his mouth,

and his abominations from between his teeth;

and he also will be a remnant for our God;

and he will be as a chieftain in Judah,

and Ekron as a Jebusite.

8 I will encamp around my house against the army,

that no one pass through or return;

and no oppressor will pass through them any more:

for now I have seen with my eyes.

9 Rejoice greatly, daughter of Zion!

Shout, daughter of Jerusalem!

Behold, your King comes to you!

He is righteous, and having salvation;

lowly, and riding on a donkey,

even on a colt, the foal of a donkey.

10 I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim,

and the horse from Jerusalem;

and the battle bow will be cut off;

and he will speak peace to the nations:

and his dominion will be from sea to sea,

and from the River to the ends of the earth.

11 As for you also,

because of the blood of your covenant,

I have set free your prisoners from the pit in which is no water.

12 Turn to the stronghold, you prisoners of hope!

Even today I declare that I will restore double to you.

13 For indeed I bend Judah as a bow for me.

I have filled the bow with Ephraim;

and I will stir up your sons, Zion,

against your sons, Greece,

and will make you like the sword of a mighty man.

14 Yahweh will be seen over them;

and his arrow will go flash like lightning;

and the Lord Yahweh will blow the trumpet,

and will go with whirlwinds of the south.

15 Yahweh of Armies will defend them;

and they will destroy and overcome with sling stones;

and they will drink, and roar as through wine;

and they will be filled like bowls,

like the corners of the altar.

16 Yahweh their God will save them in that day as the flock of his people;

for they are like the jewels of a crown,

lifted on high over his land.

17 For how great is his goodness,

and how great is his beauty!

Grain will make the young men flourish,

and new wine the virgins.

Zechariah 10

1 Ask of Yahweh rain in the spring time,

Yahweh who makes storm clouds,

and he gives rain showers to everyone for the plants in the field.

2 For the teraphim[*] have spoken vanity,

and the diviners have seen a lie;

and they have told false dreams.

They comfort in vain.

Therefore they go their way like sheep.

They are oppressed, because there is no shepherd.

3 My anger is kindled against the shepherds,

and I will punish the male goats;

For Yahweh of Armies has visited his flock, the house of Judah,

and will make them as his majestic horse in the battle.

4 From him will come the cornerstone,

from him the nail,

from him the battle bow,

from him every ruler together.

5 They shall be as mighty men,

treading down muddy streets in the battle;

and they shall fight, because Yahweh is with them;

and the riders on horses will be confounded.

6 “I will strengthen the house of Judah,

and I will save the house of Joseph,

and I will bring them back;

for I have mercy on them;

and they will be as though I had not cast them off:

for I am Yahweh their God, and I will hear them.

7 Ephraim will be like a mighty man,

and their heart will rejoice as through wine;

yes, their children will see it, and rejoice.

Their heart will be glad in Yahweh.

8 I will signal for them, and gather them;

for I have redeemed them;

and they will increase as they have increased.

9 I will sow them among the peoples;

and they will remember me in far countries;

and they will live with their children, and will return.

10 I will bring them again also out of the land of Egypt,

and gather them out of Assyria;

and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon;

and there won’t be room enough for them.

11 He will pass through the sea of affliction,

and will strike the waves in the sea,

and all the depths of the Nile will dry up;

and the pride of Assyria will be brought down,

and the scepter of Egypt will depart.

12 I will strengthen them in Yahweh;

and they will walk up and down in his name,” says Yahweh.

teraphim were household idols that may have been associated with inheritance rights to the household property.

Zechariah 11

1 Open your doors, Lebanon,

that the fire may devour your cedars.

2 Wail, cypress tree, for the cedar has fallen,

because the stately ones are destroyed.

Wail, you oaks of Bashan,

for the strong forest has come down.

3 A voice of the wailing of the shepherds!

For their glory is destroyed: a voice of the roaring of young lions!

For the pride of the Jordan is ruined.

4 Yahweh my God says: “Feed the flock of slaughter. 5 Their buyers slaughter them, and go unpunished. Those who sell them say, ‘Blessed be Yahweh, for I am rich;’ and their own shepherds don’t pity them. 6 For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land,” says Yahweh; “but, behold, I will deliver the men everyone into his neighbor’s hand, and into the hand of his king. They will strike the land, and out of their hand I will not deliver them.”

7 So I fed the flock of slaughter, especially the oppressed of the flock. I took for myself two staffs. The one I called “Favor”, and the other I called “Union”, and I fed the flock. 8 I cut off the three shepherds in one month; for my soul was weary of them, and their soul also loathed me. 9 Then I said, “I will not feed you. That which dies, let it die; and that which is to be cut off, let it be cut off; and let those who are left eat each other’s flesh.” 10 I took my staff Favor, and cut it apart, that I might break my covenant that I had made with all the peoples. 11 It was broken in that day; and thus the poor of the flock that listened to me knew that it was Yahweh’s word. 12 I said to them, “If you think it best, give me my wages; and if not, keep them.” So they weighed for my wages thirty pieces of silver. 13 Yahweh said to me, “Throw it to the potter, the handsome price that I was valued at by them!” I took the thirty pieces of silver, and threw them to the potter, in Yahweh’s house. 14 Then I cut apart my other staff, even Union, that I might break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 Yahweh said to me, “Take for yourself yet again the equipment of a foolish shepherd. 16 For, behold, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, who will not visit those who are cut off, neither will seek those who are scattered, nor heal that which is broken, nor feed that which is sound; but he will eat the meat of the fat sheep, and will tear their hoofs in pieces. 17 Woe to the worthless shepherd who leaves the flock! The sword will be on his arm, and on his right eye. His arm will be completely withered, and his right eye will be totally blinded!”

Zechariah 13

1 “In that day there will be a spring opened to David’s house and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, for sin and for uncleanness. 2 It will come to pass in that day, says Yahweh of Armies, that I will cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they will be remembered no more. I will also cause the prophets and the spirit of impurity to pass out of the land. 3 It will happen that, when anyone still prophesies, then his father and his mother who bore him will tell him, ‘You must die, because you speak lies in Yahweh’s name;’ and his father and his mother who bore him will stab him when he prophesies. 4 It will happen in that day, that the prophets will each be ashamed of his vision, when he prophesies; neither will they wear a hairy mantle to deceive: 5 but he will say, ‘I am no prophet, I am a tiller of the ground; for I have been made a bondservant from my youth.’ 6 One will say to him, ‘What are these wounds between your arms?’ Then he will answer, ‘Those with which I was wounded in the house of my friends.’

7 “Awake, sword, against my shepherd,

and against the man who is close to me,” says Yahweh of Armies.

“Strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered;

and I will turn my hand against the little ones.

8 It shall happen that in all the land,” says Yahweh,

“two parts in it will be cut off and die;

but the third will be left in it.

9 I will bring the third part into the fire,

and will refine them as silver is refined,

and will test them like gold is tested.

They will call on my name, and I will hear them.

I will say, ‘It is my people;’

and they will say, ‘Yahweh is my God.’”

Zechariah 14

1 Behold, a day of Yahweh comes, when your plunder will be divided within you. 2 For I will gather all nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city will be taken, the houses rifled, and the women ravished. Half of the city will go out into captivity, and the rest of the people will not be cut off from the city. 3 Then Yahweh will go out and fight against those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle. 4 His feet will stand in that day on the Mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem on the east; and the Mount of Olives will be split in two, from east to west, making a very great valley. Half of the mountain will move toward the north, and half of it toward the south. 5 You shall flee by the valley of my mountains; for the valley of the mountains shall reach to Azel; yes, you shall flee, just like you fled from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah. Yahweh my God will come, and all the holy ones with you.[*] 6 It will happen in that day, that there will not be light, cold, or frost. 7 It will be a unique day which is known to Yahweh; not day, and not night; but it will come to pass, that at evening time there will be light.

8 It will happen in that day, that living waters will go out from Jerusalem; half of them toward the eastern sea, and half of them toward the western sea; in summer and in winter will it be.

9 Yahweh will be King over all the earth. In that day Yahweh will be one, and his name one. 10 All the land will be made like the Arabah, from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem; and she will be lifted up, and will dwell in her place, from Benjamin’s gate to the place of the first gate, to the corner gate, and from the tower of Hananel to the king’s wine presses. 11 Men will dwell therein, and there will be no more curse; but Jerusalem will dwell safely. 12 This will be the plague with which Yahweh will strike all the peoples who have fought against Jerusalem: their flesh will consume away while they stand on their feet, and their eyes will consume away in their sockets, and their tongue will consume away in their mouth. 13 It will happen in that day, that a great panic from Yahweh will be among them; and they will lay hold everyone on the hand of his neighbor, and his hand will rise up against the hand of his neighbor. 14 Judah also will fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the surrounding nations will be gathered together: gold, and silver, and clothing, in great abundance.

15 So will be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camel, and of the donkey, and of all the animals that will be in those camps, as that plague. 16 It will happen that everyone who is left of all the nations that came against Jerusalem will go up from year to year to worship the King, Yahweh of Armies, and to keep the feast of tents. 17 It will be, that whoever of all the families of the earth doesn’t go up to Jerusalem to worship the King, Yahweh of Armies, on them there will be no rain. 18 If the family of Egypt doesn’t go up, and doesn’t come, neither will it rain on them. This will be the plague with which Yahweh will strike the nations that don’t go up to keep the feast of tents. 19 This will be the punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all the nations that don’t go up to keep the feast of tents. 20 In that day there will be on the bells of the horses, “HOLY TO YAHWEH”; and the pots in Yahweh’s house will be like the bowls before the altar. 21 Yes, every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah will be holy to Yahweh of Armies; and all those who sacrifice will come and take of them, and cook in them. In that day there will no longer be a Canaanite in the house of Yahweh of Armies.

Septuagint reads “him” instead of “you”.

Malachi 1

1 A revelation, Yahweh’s[*] word to Israel by Malachi.

2 “I have loved you,” says Yahweh.

Yet you say, “How have you loved us?”

“Wasn’t Esau Jacob’s brother?” says Yahweh, “Yet I loved Jacob; 3 but Esau I hated, and made his mountains a desolation, and gave his heritage to the jackals of the wilderness.” 4 Whereas Edom says, “We are beaten down, but we will return and build the waste places”; Yahweh of Armies says, “They shall build, but I will throw down; and men will call them ‘The Wicked Land,’ even the people against whom Yahweh shows wrath forever.”

5 Your eyes will see, and you will say, “Yahweh is great—even beyond the border of Israel!”

6 “A son honors his father, and a servant his master. If I am a father, then where is my honor? And if I am a master, where is the respect due me? Says Yahweh of Armies to you, priests, who despise my name. You say, ‘How have we despised your name?’ 7 You offer polluted bread on my altar. You say, ‘How have we polluted you?’ In that you say, ‘Yahweh’s table is contemptible.’ 8 When you offer the blind for sacrifice, isn’t that evil? And when you offer the lame and sick, isn’t that evil? Present it now to your governor! Will he be pleased with you? Or will he accept your person?” says Yahweh of Armies.

9 “Now, please entreat the favor of God,[*] that he may be gracious to us. With this, will he accept any of you?” says Yahweh of Armies.

10 “Oh that there were one among you who would shut the doors, that you might not kindle fire on my altar in vain! I have no pleasure in you,” says Yahweh of Armies, “neither will I accept an offering at your hand. 11 For from the rising of the sun even to the going down of the same, my name is great among the nations, and in every place incense will be offered to my name, and a pure offering: for my name is great among the nations,” says Yahweh of Armies. 12 “But you profane it, in that you say, ‘Yahweh’s table is polluted, and its fruit, even its food, is contemptible.’ 13 You say also, ‘Behold,[*] what a weariness it is!’ and you have sniffed at it”, says Yahweh of Armies; “and you have brought that which was taken by violence, the lame, and the sick; thus you bring the offering. Should I accept this at your hand?” says Yahweh.

14 “But the deceiver is cursed, who has in his flock a male, and vows, and sacrifices to the Lord[*] a defective thing; for I am a great King,” says Yahweh of Armies, “and my name is awesome among the nations.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Malachi 2

1 “Now, you priests, this commandment is for you. 2 If you will not listen, and if you will not lay it to heart, to give glory to my name,” says Yahweh of Armies, “then will I send the curse on you, and I will curse your blessings. Indeed, I have cursed them already, because you do not lay it to heart. 3 Behold, I will rebuke your offspring,[*] and will spread dung on your faces, even the dung of your feasts; and you will be taken away with it. 4 You will know that I have sent this commandment to you, that my covenant may be with Levi,” says Yahweh of Armies. 5 “My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him that he might be reverent toward me; and he was reverent toward me, and stood in awe of my name. 6 The law of truth was in his mouth, and unrighteousness was not found in his lips. He walked with me in peace and uprightness, and turned many away from iniquity. 7 For the priest’s lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth; for he is the messenger of Yahweh of Armies. 8 But you have turned aside out of the way. You have caused many to stumble in the law. You have corrupted the covenant of Levi,” says Yahweh of Armies. 9 “Therefore I have also made you contemptible and base before all the people, according to the way you have not kept my ways, but have had respect for persons in the law. 10 Don’t we all have one father? Hasn’t one God created us? Why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, profaning the covenant of our fathers? 11 Judah has dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah has profaned the holiness of Yahweh which he loves, and has married the daughter of a foreign god. 12 Yahweh will cut off, to the man who does this, him who wakes and him who answers, out of the tents of Jacob, and him who offers an offering to Yahweh of Armies. 13 This again you do: you cover Yahweh’s altar with tears, with weeping, and with sighing, because he doesn’t regard the offering any more, neither receives it with good will at your hand. 14 Yet you say, ‘Why?’ Because Yahweh has been witness between you and the wife of your youth, against whom you have dealt treacherously, though she is your companion, and the wife of your covenant. 15 Did he not make you one, although he had the residue of the Spirit? Why one? He sought godly offspring.[*] Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let no one deal treacherously against the wife of his youth. 16 For I hate divorce”, says Yahweh, the God of Israel, “and him who covers his garment with violence!” says Yahweh of Armies. “Therefore take heed to your spirit, that you don’t deal treacherously. 17 You have wearied Yahweh with your words. Yet you say, ‘How have we wearied him?’ In that you say, ‘Everyone who does evil is good in Yahweh’s sight, and he delights in them;’ or ‘Where is the God of justice?’

or, seed

or, seed

Malachi 3

1 “Behold, I send my messenger, and he will prepare the way before me; and the Lord, whom you seek, will suddenly come to his temple; and the messenger of the covenant, whom you desire, behold, he comes!” says Yahweh of Armies. 2 “But who can endure the day of his coming? And who will stand when he appears? For he is like a refiner’s fire, and like launderer’s soap; 3 and he will sit as a refiner and purifier of silver, and he will purify the sons of Levi, and refine them as gold and silver; and they shall offer to Yahweh offerings in righteousness. 4 Then the offering of Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasant to Yahweh, as in the days of old, and as in ancient years. 5 I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against the perjurers, and against those who oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and who deprive the foreigner of justice, and don’t fear me,” says Yahweh of Armies. 6 “For I, Yahweh, don’t change; therefore you, sons of Jacob, are not consumed. 7 From the days of your fathers you have turned aside from my ordinances, and have not kept them. Return to me, and I will return to you,” says Yahweh of Armies. “But you say, ‘How shall we return?’ 8 Will a man rob God? Yet you rob me! But you say, ‘How have we robbed you?’ In tithes and offerings. 9 You are cursed with the curse; for you rob me, even this whole nation. 10 Bring the whole tithe into the storehouse, that there may be food in my house, and test me now in this,” says Yahweh of Armies, “if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there will not be room enough for. 11 I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast its fruit before its time in the field,” says Yahweh of Armies. 12 “All nations shall call you blessed, for you will be a delightful land,” says Yahweh of Armies.

13 “Your words have been stout against me,” says Yahweh. “Yet you say, ‘What have we spoken against you?’ 14 You have said, ‘It is vain to serve God;’ and ‘What profit is it that we have followed his instructions, and that we have walked mournfully before Yahweh of Armies? 15 Now we call the proud happy; yes, those who work wickedness are built up; yes, they tempt God, and escape.’ 16 Then those who feared Yahweh spoke one with another; and Yahweh listened, and heard, and a book of memory was written before him, for those who feared Yahweh, and who honored his name. 17 They shall be mine,” says Yahweh of Armies, “my own possession in the day that I make, and I will spare them, as a man spares his own son who serves him. 18 Then you shall return and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him who serves God and him who doesn’t serve him.

Matthew 1

1 The book of the genealogy of Jesus Christ,[*] the son of David, the son of Abraham. 2 Abraham became the father of Isaac. Isaac became the father of Jacob. Jacob became the father of Judah and his brothers. 3 Judah became the father of Perez and Zerah by Tamar. Perez became the father of Hezron. Hezron became the father of Ram. 4 Ram became the father of Amminadab. Amminadab became the father of Nahshon. Nahshon became the father of Salmon. 5 Salmon became the father of Boaz by Rahab. Boaz became the father of Obed by Ruth. Obed became the father of Jesse. 6 Jesse became the father of King David. David became the father of Solomon by her who had been Uriah’s wife. 7 Solomon became the father of Rehoboam. Rehoboam became the father of Abijah. Abijah became the father of Asa. 8 Asa became the father of Jehoshaphat. Jehoshaphat became the father of Joram. Joram became the father of Uzziah. 9 Uzziah became the father of Jotham. Jotham became the father of Ahaz. Ahaz became the father of Hezekiah. 10 Hezekiah became the father of Manasseh. Manasseh became the father of Amon. Amon became the father of Josiah. 11 Josiah became the father of Jechoniah and his brothers, at the time of the exile to Babylon. 12 After the exile to Babylon, Jechoniah became the father of Shealtiel. Shealtiel became the father of Zerubbabel. 13 Zerubbabel became the father of Abiud. Abiud became the father of Eliakim. Eliakim became the father of Azor. 14 Azor became the father of Zadok. Zadok became the father of Achim. Achim became the father of Eliud. 15 Eliud became the father of Eleazar. Eleazar became the father of Matthan. Matthan became the father of Jacob. 16 Jacob became the father of Joseph, the husband of Mary, from whom was born Jesus,[*] who is called Christ. 17 So all the generations from Abraham to David are fourteen generations; from David to the exile to Babylon fourteen generations; and from the carrying away to Babylon to the Christ, fourteen generations.

18 Now the birth of Jesus Christ was like this; for after his mother, Mary, was engaged to Joseph, before they came together, she was found pregnant by the Holy Spirit. 19 Joseph, her husband, being a righteous man, and not willing to make her a public example, intended to put her away secretly. 20 But when he thought about these things, behold,[*] an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, “Joseph, son of David, don’t be afraid to take to yourself Mary, your wife, for that which is conceived in her is of the Holy Spirit. 21 She shall give birth to a son. You shall call his name Jesus, for it is he who shall save his people from their sins.”

22 Now all this has happened, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the Lord through the prophet, saying,

23 “Behold, the virgin shall be with child,

and shall give birth to a son.

They shall call his name Immanuel”;

which is, being interpreted, “God with us.”[*]

24 Joseph arose from his sleep, and did as the angel of the Lord commanded him, and took his wife to himself; 25 and didn’t know her sexually until she had given birth to her firstborn son. He named him Jesus.

Messiah (Hebrew) and Christ (Greek) both mean “Anointed One”

“Jesus” means “Salvation”.

“Behold”, from “ἰδοὺ”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Isaiah 7:14

Matthew 2

1 Now when Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea in the days of King Herod, behold, wise men[*] from the east came to Jerusalem, saying, 2 “Where is he who is born King of the Jews? For we saw his star in the east, and have come to worship him.” 3 When King Herod heard it, he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him. 4 Gathering together all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he asked them where the Christ would be born. 5 They said to him, “In Bethlehem of Judea, for this is written through the prophet,

6 ‘You Bethlehem, land of Judah,

are in no way least among the princes of Judah:

for out of you shall come a governor,

who shall shepherd my people, Israel.’”[*]

7 Then Herod secretly called the wise men, and learned from them exactly what time the star appeared. 8 He sent them to Bethlehem, and said, “Go and search diligently for the young child. When you have found him, bring me word, so that I also may come and worship him.”

9 They, having heard the king, went their way; and behold, the star, which they saw in the east, went before them, until it came and stood over where the young child was. 10 When they saw the star, they rejoiced with exceedingly great joy. 11 They came into the house and saw the young child with Mary, his mother, and they fell down and worshiped him. Opening their treasures, they offered to him gifts: gold, frankincense, and myrrh. 12 Being warned in a dream that they shouldn’t return to Herod, they went back to their own country another way.

13 Now when they had departed, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared to Joseph in a dream, saying, “Arise and take the young child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and stay there until I tell you, for Herod will seek the young child to destroy him.”

14 He arose and took the young child and his mother by night, and departed into Egypt, 15 and was there until the death of Herod; that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the Lord through the prophet, saying, “Out of Egypt I called my son.”[*]

16 Then Herod, when he saw that he was mocked by the wise men, was exceedingly angry, and sent out, and killed all the male children who were in Bethlehem and in all the surrounding countryside, from two years old and under, according to the exact time which he had learned from the wise men. 17 Then that which was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled, saying,

18 “A voice was heard in Ramah,

lamentation, weeping and great mourning,

Rachel weeping for her children;

she wouldn’t be comforted,

because they are no more.”[*]

19 But when Herod was dead, behold, an angel of the Lord appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, saying, 20 “Arise and take the young child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel, for those who sought the young child’s life are dead.”

21 He arose and took the young child and his mother, and came into the land of Israel. 22 But when he heard that Archelaus was reigning over Judea in the place of his father, Herod, he was afraid to go there. Being warned in a dream, he withdrew into the region of Galilee, 23 and came and lived in a city called Nazareth; that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophets: “He will be called a Nazarene.”

The word for “wise men” (magoi) can also mean teachers, scientists, physicians, astrologers, seers, interpreters of dreams, or sorcerers.

Micah 5:2

Hosea 11:1

Jeremiah 31:15

Matthew 3

1 In those days, John the Baptizer came, preaching in the wilderness of Judea, saying, 2 “Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand!” 3 For this is he who was spoken of by Isaiah the prophet, saying,

“The voice of one crying in the wilderness,

make ready the way of the Lord.

Make his paths straight.”[*]

4 Now John himself wore clothing made of camel’s hair, with a leather belt around his waist. His food was locusts and wild honey. 5 Then people from Jerusalem, all of Judea, and all the region around the Jordan went out to him. 6 They were baptized[*] by him in the Jordan, confessing their sins. 7 But when he saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming for his baptism,[*] he said to them, “You offspring of vipers, who warned you to flee from the wrath to come? 8 Therefore produce fruit worthy of repentance! 9 Don’t think to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham for our father,’ for I tell you that God is able to raise up children to Abraham from these stones.

10 “Even now the ax lies at the root of the trees. Therefore every tree that doesn’t produce good fruit is cut down, and cast into the fire. 11 I indeed baptize[*] you in water for repentance, but he who comes after me is mightier than I, whose shoes I am not worthy to carry. He will baptize you in the Holy Spirit.[*] 12 His winnowing fork is in his hand, and he will thoroughly cleanse his threshing floor. He will gather his wheat into the barn, but the chaff he will burn up with unquenchable fire.”

13 Then Jesus came from Galilee to the Jordan[*] to John, to be baptized by him. 14 But John would have hindered him, saying, “I need to be baptized by you, and you come to me?”

15 But Jesus, answering, said to him, “Allow it now, for this is the fitting way for us to fulfill all righteousness.” Then he allowed him. 16 Jesus, when he was baptized, went up directly from the water: and behold, the heavens were opened to him. He saw the Spirit of God descending as a dove, and coming on him. 17 Behold, a voice out of the heavens said, “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased.”

Isaiah 40:3

or, immersed

or, immersion

or, immerse

TR and NU add “and with fire”

i.e., the Jordan River

Matthew 4

1 Then Jesus was led up by the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted by the devil. 2 When he had fasted forty days and forty nights, he was hungry afterward. 3 The tempter came and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, command that these stones become bread.”

4 But he answered, “It is written, ‘Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceeds out of the mouth of God.’”[*]

5 Then the devil took him into the holy city. He set him on the pinnacle of the temple, 6 and said to him, “If you are the Son of God, throw yourself down, for it is written, ‘He will put his angels in charge of you.’ and,

‘On their hands they will bear you up,

so that you don’t dash your foot against a stone.’”[*]

7 Jesus said to him, “Again, it is written, ‘You shall not test the Lord, your God.’”[*]

8 Again, the devil took him to an exceedingly high mountain, and showed him all the kingdoms of the world, and their glory. 9 He said to him, “I will give you all of these things, if you will fall down and worship me.”

10 Then Jesus said to him, “Get behind me,[*] Satan! For it is written, ‘You shall worship the Lord your God, and you shall serve him only.’”[*]

11 Then the devil left him, and behold, angels came and served him. 12 Now when Jesus heard that John was delivered up, he withdrew into Galilee. 13 Leaving Nazareth, he came and lived in Capernaum, which is by the sea, in the region of Zebulun and Naphtali, 14 that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying,

15 “The land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali,

toward the sea, beyond the Jordan,

Galilee of the Gentiles,

16 the people who sat in darkness saw a great light,

to those who sat in the region and shadow of death,

to them light has dawned.”[*]

17 From that time, Jesus began to preach, and to say, “Repent! For the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand.”

18 Walking by the sea of Galilee, he[*] saw two brothers: Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew, his brother, casting a net into the sea; for they were fishermen. 19 He said to them, “Come after me, and I will make you fishers for men.”

20 They immediately left their nets and followed him. 21 Going on from there, he saw two other brothers, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in the boat with Zebedee their father, mending their nets. He called them. 22 They immediately left the boat and their father, and followed him.

23 Jesus went about in all Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, preaching the Good News of the Kingdom, and healing every disease and every sickness among the people. 24 The report about him went out into all Syria. They brought to him all who were sick, afflicted with various diseases and torments, possessed with demons, epileptics, and paralytics; and he healed them. 25 Great multitudes from Galilee, Decapolis, Jerusalem, Judea and from beyond the Jordan followed him.

Deuteronomy 8:3

Psalm 91:11-12

Deuteronomy 6:16

TR and NU read “Go away” instead of “Get behind me”

Deuteronomy 6:13

Isaiah 9:1-2

TR reads “Jesus” instead of “he”

Matthew 5

1 Seeing the multitudes, he went up onto the mountain. When he had sat down, his disciples came to him. 2 He opened his mouth and taught them, saying,

3 “Blessed are the poor in spirit,

for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.[*]

4 Blessed are those who mourn,

for they shall be comforted.[*]

5 Blessed are the gentle,

for they shall inherit the earth.[*][*]

6 Blessed are those who hunger and thirst after righteousness,

for they shall be filled.

7 Blessed are the merciful,

for they shall obtain mercy.

8 Blessed are the pure in heart,

for they shall see God.

9 Blessed are the peacemakers,

for they shall be called children of God.

10 Blessed are those who have been persecuted for righteousness’ sake,

for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.

11 “Blessed are you when people reproach you, persecute you, and say all kinds of evil against you falsely, for my sake. 12 Rejoice, and be exceedingly glad, for great is your reward in heaven. For that is how they persecuted the prophets who were before you.

13 “You are the salt of the earth, but if the salt has lost its flavor, with what will it be salted? It is then good for nothing, but to be cast out and trodden under the feet of men. 14 You are the light of the world. A city located on a hill can’t be hidden. 15 Neither do you light a lamp, and put it under a measuring basket, but on a stand; and it shines to all who are in the house. 16 Even so, let your light shine before men; that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father who is in heaven.

17 “Don’t think that I came to destroy the law or the prophets. I didn’t come to destroy, but to fulfill. 18 For most certainly, I tell you, until heaven and earth pass away, not even one smallest letter[*] or one tiny pen stroke[*] shall in any way pass away from the law, until all things are accomplished. 19 Whoever, therefore, shall break one of these least commandments, and teach others to do so, shall be called least in the Kingdom of Heaven; but whoever shall do and teach them shall be called great in the Kingdom of Heaven. 20 For I tell you that unless your righteousness exceeds that of the scribes and Pharisees, there is no way you will enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.

21 “You have heard that it was said to the ancient ones, ‘You shall not murder;’[*] and ‘Whoever murders will be in danger of the judgment.’ 22 But I tell you, that everyone who is angry with his brother without a cause[*] will be in danger of the judgment; and whoever says to his brother, ‘Raca!’[*] will be in danger of the council; and whoever says, ‘You fool!’ will be in danger of the fire of Gehenna.[*]

23 “If therefore you are offering your gift at the altar, and there remember that your brother has anything against you, 24 leave your gift there before the altar, and go your way. First be reconciled to your brother, and then come and offer your gift. 25 Agree with your adversary quickly, while you are with him on the way; lest perhaps the prosecutor deliver you to the judge, and the judge deliver you to the officer, and you be cast into prison. 26 Most certainly I tell you, you shall by no means get out of there, until you have paid the last penny.[*]

27 “You have heard that it was said,[*] ‘You shall not commit adultery;’[*] 28 but I tell you that everyone who gazes at a woman to lust after her has committed adultery with her already in his heart. 29 If your right eye causes you to stumble, pluck it out and throw it away from you. For it is more profitable for you that one of your members should perish, than for your whole body to be cast into Gehenna.[*] 30 If your right hand causes you to stumble, cut it off, and throw it away from you. For it is more profitable for you that one of your members should perish, than for your whole body to be cast into Gehenna.[*]

31 “It was also said, ‘Whoever shall put away his wife, let him give her a writing of divorce,’[*] 32 but I tell you that whoever puts away his wife, except for the cause of sexual immorality, makes her an adulteress; and whoever marries her when she is put away commits adultery.

33 “Again you have heard that it was said to them of old time, ‘You shall not make false vows, but shall perform to the Lord your vows,’ 34 but I tell you, don’t swear at all: neither by heaven, for it is the throne of God; 35 nor by the earth, for it is the footstool of his feet; nor by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great King. 36 Neither shall you swear by your head, for you can’t make one hair white or black. 37 But let your ‘Yes’ be ‘Yes’ and your ‘No’ be ‘No.’ Whatever is more than these is of the evil one.

38 “You have heard that it was said, ‘An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth.’[*] 39 But I tell you, don’t resist him who is evil; but whoever strikes you on your right cheek, turn to him the other also. 40 If anyone sues you to take away your coat, let him have your cloak also. 41 Whoever compels you to go one mile, go with him two. 42 Give to him who asks you, and don’t turn away him who desires to borrow from you.

43 “You have heard that it was said, ‘You shall love your neighbor[*] and hate your enemy.’[*] 44 But I tell you, love your enemies, bless those who curse you, do good to those who hate you, and pray for those who mistreat you and persecute you, 45 that you may be children of your Father who is in heaven. For he makes his sun to rise on the evil and the good, and sends rain on the just and the unjust. 46 For if you love those who love you, what reward do you have? Don’t even the tax collectors do the same? 47 If you only greet your friends, what more do you do than others? Don’t even the tax collectors[*] do the same? 48 Therefore you shall be perfect, just as your Father in heaven is perfect.

Isaiah 57:15; 66:2

Isaiah 61:2; 66:10,13

or, land.

Psalm 37:11

literally, iota

or, serif

Exodus 20:13

NU omits “without a cause”.

“Raca” is an Aramaic insult, related to the word for “empty” and conveying the idea of empty-headedness.

or, Hell

literally, kodrantes. A kodrantes was a small copper coin worth about 2 lepta (widow’s mites)—not enough to buy very much of anything.

TR adds “to the ancients”.

Exodus 20:14

or, Hell

or, Hell

Deuteronomy 24:1

Exodus 21:24; Leviticus 24:20; Deuteronomy 19:21

Leviticus 19:18

not in the Bible, but see Qumran Manual of Discipline Ix, 21-26

NU reads “Gentiles” instead of “tax collectors”.

Matthew 6

1 “Be careful that you don’t do your charitable giving before men, to be seen by them, or else you have no reward from your Father who is in heaven. 2 Therefore when you do merciful deeds, don’t sound a trumpet before yourself, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, that they may get glory from men. Most certainly I tell you, they have received their reward. 3 But when you do merciful deeds, don’t let your left hand know what your right hand does, 4 so that your merciful deeds may be in secret, then your Father who sees in secret will reward you openly.

5 “When you pray, you shall not be as the hypocrites, for they love to stand and pray in the synagogues and in the corners of the streets, that they may be seen by men. Most certainly, I tell you, they have received their reward. 6 But you, when you pray, enter into your inner room, and having shut your door, pray to your Father who is in secret, and your Father who sees in secret will reward you openly. 7 In praying, don’t use vain repetitions, as the Gentiles do; for they think that they will be heard for their much speaking. 8 Therefore don’t be like them, for your Father knows what things you need, before you ask him. 9 Pray like this: ‘Our Father in heaven, may your name be kept holy. 10 Let your Kingdom come. Let your will be done, as in heaven, so on earth. 11 Give us today our daily bread. 12 Forgive us our debts, as we also forgive our debtors. 13 Bring us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one. For yours is the Kingdom, the power, and the glory forever. Amen.’[*]

14 “For if you forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you. 15 But if you don’t forgive men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.

16 “Moreover when you fast, don’t be like the hypocrites, with sad faces. For they disfigure their faces, that they may be seen by men to be fasting. Most certainly I tell you, they have received their reward. 17 But you, when you fast, anoint your head, and wash your face; 18 so that you are not seen by men to be fasting, but by your Father who is in secret, and your Father, who sees in secret, will reward you.

19 “Don’t lay up treasures for yourselves on the earth, where moth and rust consume, and where thieves break through and steal; 20 but lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust consume, and where thieves don’t break through and steal; 21 for where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.

22 “The lamp of the body is the eye. If therefore your eye is sound, your whole body will be full of light. 23 But if your eye is evil, your whole body will be full of darkness. If therefore the light that is in you is darkness, how great is the darkness!

24 “No one can serve two masters, for either he will hate the one and love the other; or else he will be devoted to one and despise the other. You can’t serve both God and Mammon. 25 Therefore I tell you, don’t be anxious for your life: what you will eat, or what you will drink; nor yet for your body, what you will wear. Isn’t life more than food, and the body more than clothing? 26 See the birds of the sky, that they don’t sow, neither do they reap, nor gather into barns. Your heavenly Father feeds them. Aren’t you of much more value than they?

27 “Which of you, by being anxious, can add one moment[*] to his lifespan? 28 Why are you anxious about clothing? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow. They don’t toil, neither do they spin, 29 yet I tell you that even Solomon in all his glory was not dressed like one of these. 30 But if God so clothes the grass of the field, which today exists, and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, won’t he much more clothe you, you of little faith?

31 “Therefore don’t be anxious, saying, ‘What will we eat?’, ‘What will we drink?’ or, ‘With what will we be clothed?’ 32 For the Gentiles seek after all these things; for your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 But seek first God’s Kingdom, and his righteousness; and all these things will be given to you as well. 34 Therefore don’t be anxious for tomorrow, for tomorrow will be anxious for itself. Each day’s own evil is sufficient.

NU omits “For yours is the Kingdom, the power, and the glory forever. Amen.”

literally, cubit

Matthew 7

1 “Don’t judge, so that you won’t be judged. 2 For with whatever judgment you judge, you will be judged; and with whatever measure you measure, it will be measured to you. 3 Why do you see the speck that is in your brother’s eye, but don’t consider the beam that is in your own eye? 4 Or how will you tell your brother, ‘Let me remove the speck from your eye;’ and behold, the beam is in your own eye? 5 You hypocrite! First remove the beam out of your own eye, and then you can see clearly to remove the speck out of your brother’s eye.

6 “Don’t give that which is holy to the dogs, neither throw your pearls before the pigs, lest perhaps they trample them under their feet, and turn and tear you to pieces.

7 “Ask, and it will be given you. Seek, and you will find. Knock, and it will be opened for you. 8 For everyone who asks receives. He who seeks finds. To him who knocks it will be opened. 9 Or who is there among you, who, if his son asks him for bread, will give him a stone? 10 Or if he asks for a fish, who will give him a serpent? 11 If you then, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will your Father who is in heaven give good things to those who ask him! 12 Therefore whatever you desire for men to do to you, you shall also do to them; for this is the law and the prophets.

13 “Enter in by the narrow gate; for wide is the gate and broad is the way that leads to destruction, and many are those who enter in by it. 14 How[*] narrow is the gate, and restricted is the way that leads to life! Few are those who find it.

15 “Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep’s clothing, but inwardly are ravening wolves. 16 By their fruits you will know them. Do you gather grapes from thorns, or figs from thistles? 17 Even so, every good tree produces good fruit; but the corrupt tree produces evil fruit. 18 A good tree can’t produce evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree produce good fruit. 19 Every tree that doesn’t grow good fruit is cut down, and thrown into the fire. 20 Therefore by their fruits you will know them. 21 Not everyone who says to me, ‘Lord, Lord,’ will enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; but he who does the will of my Father who is in heaven. 22 Many will tell me in that day, ‘Lord, Lord, didn’t we prophesy in your name, in your name cast out demons, and in your name do many mighty works?’ 23 Then I will tell them, ‘I never knew you. Depart from me, you who work iniquity.’

24 “Everyone therefore who hears these words of mine, and does them, I will liken him to a wise man, who built his house on a rock. 25 The rain came down, the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat on that house; and it didn’t fall, for it was founded on the rock. 26 Everyone who hears these words of mine, and doesn’t do them will be like a foolish man, who built his house on the sand. 27 The rain came down, the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat on that house; and it fell—and great was its fall.”

28 When Jesus had finished saying these things, the multitudes were astonished at his teaching, 29 for he taught them with authority, and not like the scribes.

TR reads “Because” instead of “How”

Matthew 8

1 When he came down from the mountain, great multitudes followed him. 2 Behold, a leper came to him and worshiped him, saying, “Lord, if you want to, you can make me clean.”

3 Jesus stretched out his hand, and touched him, saying, “I want to. Be made clean.” Immediately his leprosy was cleansed. 4 Jesus said to him, “See that you tell nobody, but go, show yourself to the priest, and offer the gift that Moses commanded, as a testimony to them.”

5 When he came into Capernaum, a centurion came to him, asking him, 6 and saying, “Lord, my servant lies in the house paralyzed, grievously tormented.”

7 Jesus said to him, “I will come and heal him.”

8 The centurion answered, “Lord, I’m not worthy for you to come under my roof. Just say the word, and my servant will be healed. 9 For I am also a man under authority, having under myself soldiers. I tell this one, ‘Go,’ and he goes; and tell another, ‘Come,’ and he comes; and tell my servant, ‘Do this,’ and he does it.”

10 When Jesus heard it, he marveled, and said to those who followed, “Most certainly I tell you, I haven’t found so great a faith, not even in Israel. 11 I tell you that many will come from the east and the west, and will sit down with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob in the Kingdom of Heaven, 12 but the children of the Kingdom will be thrown out into the outer darkness. There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.” 13 Jesus said to the centurion, “Go your way. Let it be done for you as you have believed.” His servant was healed in that hour.

14 When Jesus came into Peter’s house, he saw his wife’s mother lying sick with a fever. 15 He touched her hand, and the fever left her. She got up and served him.[*] 16 When evening came, they brought to him many possessed with demons. He cast out the spirits with a word, and healed all who were sick; 17 that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying, “He took our infirmities, and bore our diseases.”[*] 18 Now when Jesus saw great multitudes around him, he gave the order to depart to the other side.

19 A scribe came, and said to him, “Teacher, I will follow you wherever you go.”

20 Jesus said to him, “The foxes have holes, and the birds of the sky have nests, but the Son of Man has nowhere to lay his head.”

21 Another of his disciples said to him, “Lord, allow me first to go and bury my father.”

22 But Jesus said to him, “Follow me, and leave the dead to bury their own dead.”

23 When he got into a boat, his disciples followed him. 24 Behold, a violent storm came up on the sea, so much that the boat was covered with the waves, but he was asleep. 25 They came to him, and woke him up, saying, “Save us, Lord! We are dying!”

26 He said to them, “Why are you fearful, O you of little faith?” Then he got up, rebuked the wind and the sea, and there was a great calm.

27 The men marveled, saying, “What kind of man is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?”

28 When he came to the other side, into the country of the Gergesenes,[*] two people possessed by demons met him there, coming out of the tombs, exceedingly fierce, so that nobody could pass that way. 29 Behold, they cried out, saying, “What do we have to do with you, Jesus, Son of God? Have you come here to torment us before the time?” 30 Now there was a herd of many pigs feeding far away from them. 31 The demons begged him, saying, “If you cast us out, permit us to go away into the herd of pigs.”

32 He said to them, “Go!”

They came out, and went into the herd of pigs: and behold, the whole herd of pigs rushed down the cliff into the sea, and died in the water. 33 Those who fed them fled, and went away into the city, and told everything, including what happened to those who were possessed with demons. 34 Behold, all the city came out to meet Jesus. When they saw him, they begged that he would depart from their borders.

TR reads “them” instead of “him”

Isaiah 53:4

NU reads “Gadarenes”

Matthew 9

1 He entered into a boat, and crossed over, and came into his own city. 2 Behold, they brought to him a man who was paralyzed, lying on a bed. Jesus, seeing their faith, said to the paralytic, “Son, cheer up! Your sins are forgiven you.”

3 Behold, some of the scribes said to themselves, “This man blasphemes.”

4 Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said, “Why do you think evil in your hearts? 5 For which is easier, to say, ‘Your sins are forgiven;’ or to say, ‘Get up, and walk?’ 6 But that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on earth to forgive sins...” (then he said to the paralytic), “Get up, and take up your mat, and go to your house.”

7 He arose and departed to his house. 8 But when the multitudes saw it, they marveled and glorified God, who had given such authority to men.

9 As Jesus passed by from there, he saw a man called Matthew sitting at the tax collection office. He said to him, “Follow me.” He got up and followed him. 10 As he sat in the house, behold, many tax collectors and sinners came and sat down with Jesus and his disciples. 11 When the Pharisees saw it, they said to his disciples, “Why does your teacher eat with tax collectors and sinners?”

12 When Jesus heard it, he said to them, “Those who are healthy have no need for a physician, but those who are sick do. 13 But you go and learn what this means: ‘I desire mercy, and not sacrifice,’[*] for I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.”[*]

14 Then John’s disciples came to him, saying, “Why do we and the Pharisees fast often, but your disciples don’t fast?”

15 Jesus said to them, “Can the friends of the bridegroom mourn, as long as the bridegroom is with them? But the days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast. 16 No one puts a piece of unshrunk cloth on an old garment; for the patch would tear away from the garment, and a worse hole is made. 17 Neither do people put new wine into old wine skins, or else the skins would burst, and the wine be spilled, and the skins ruined. No, they put new wine into fresh wine skins, and both are preserved.”

18 While he told these things to them, behold, a ruler came and worshiped him, saying, “My daughter has just died, but come and lay your hand on her, and she will live.”

19 Jesus got up and followed him, as did his disciples. 20 Behold, a woman who had an issue of blood for twelve years came behind him, and touched the fringe[*] of his garment; 21 for she said within herself, “If I just touch his garment, I will be made well.”

22 But Jesus, turning around and seeing her, said, “Daughter, cheer up! Your faith has made you well.” And the woman was made well from that hour.

23 When Jesus came into the ruler’s house, and saw the flute players, and the crowd in noisy disorder, 24 he said to them, “Make room, because the girl isn’t dead, but sleeping.”

They were ridiculing him. 25 But when the crowd was put out, he entered in, took her by the hand, and the girl arose. 26 The report of this went out into all that land. 27 As Jesus passed by from there, two blind men followed him, calling out and saying, “Have mercy on us, son of David!”

28 When he had come into the house, the blind men came to him. Jesus said to them, “Do you believe that I am able to do this?”

They told him, “Yes, Lord.”

29 Then he touched their eyes, saying, “According to your faith be it done to you.” 30 Their eyes were opened. Jesus strictly commanded them, saying, “See that no one knows about this.” 31 But they went out and spread abroad his fame in all that land.

32 As they went out, behold, a mute man who was demon possessed was brought to him. 33 When the demon was cast out, the mute man spoke. The multitudes marveled, saying, “Nothing like this has ever been seen in Israel!”

34 But the Pharisees said, “By the prince of the demons, he casts out demons.”

35 Jesus went about all the cities and the villages, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the Good News of the Kingdom, and healing every disease and every sickness among the people. 36 But when he saw the multitudes, he was moved with compassion for them, because they were harassed[*] and scattered, like sheep without a shepherd. 37 Then he said to his disciples, “The harvest indeed is plentiful, but the laborers are few. 38 Pray therefore that the Lord of the harvest will send out laborers into his harvest.”

Hosea 6:6

NU omits “to repentance”.

or, tassel

TR reads “weary” instead of “harassed”

Matthew 10

1 He called to himself his twelve disciples, and gave them authority over unclean spirits, to cast them out, and to heal every disease and every sickness. 2 Now the names of the twelve apostles are these. The first, Simon, who is called Peter; Andrew, his brother; James the son of Zebedee; John, his brother; 3 Philip; Bartholomew; Thomas; Matthew the tax collector; James the son of Alphaeus; Lebbaeus, who was also called[*] Thaddaeus; 4 Simon the Canaanite; and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.

5 Jesus sent these twelve out, and commanded them, saying, “Don’t go among the Gentiles, and don’t enter into any city of the Samaritans. 6 Rather, go to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. 7 As you go, preach, saying, ‘The Kingdom of Heaven is at hand!’ 8 Heal the sick, cleanse the lepers,[*] and cast out demons. Freely you received, so freely give. 9 Don’t take any gold, silver, or brass in your money belts. 10 Take no bag for your journey, neither two coats, nor shoes, nor staff: for the laborer is worthy of his food. 11 Into whatever city or village you enter, find out who in it is worthy; and stay there until you go on. 12 As you enter into the household, greet it. 13 If the household is worthy, let your peace come on it, but if it isn’t worthy, let your peace return to you. 14 Whoever doesn’t receive you, nor hear your words, as you go out of that house or that city, shake off the dust from your feet. 15 Most certainly I tell you, it will be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment than for that city.

16 “Behold, I send you out as sheep among wolves. Therefore be wise as serpents, and harmless as doves. 17 But beware of men: for they will deliver you up to councils, and in their synagogues they will scourge you. 18 Yes, and you will be brought before governors and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them and to the nations. 19 But when they deliver you up, don’t be anxious how or what you will say, for it will be given you in that hour what you will say. 20 For it is not you who speak, but the Spirit of your Father who speaks in you.

21 “Brother will deliver up brother to death, and the father his child. Children will rise up against parents, and cause them to be put to death. 22 You will be hated by all men for my name’s sake, but he who endures to the end will be saved. 23 But when they persecute you in this city, flee into the next, for most certainly I tell you, you will not have gone through the cities of Israel, until the Son of Man has come.

24 “A disciple is not above his teacher, nor a servant above his lord. 25 It is enough for the disciple that he be like his teacher, and the servant like his lord. If they have called the master of the house Beelzebul,[*] how much more those of his household! 26 Therefore don’t be afraid of them, for there is nothing covered that will not be revealed; and hidden that will not be known. 27 What I tell you in the darkness, speak in the light; and what you hear whispered in the ear, proclaim on the housetops. 28 Don’t be afraid of those who kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul. Rather, fear him who is able to destroy both soul and body in Gehenna.[*]

29 “Aren’t two sparrows sold for an assarion coin?[*] Not one of them falls on the ground apart from your Father’s will, 30 but the very hairs of your head are all numbered. 31 Therefore don’t be afraid. You are of more value than many sparrows. 32 Everyone therefore who confesses me before men, him I will also confess before my Father who is in heaven. 33 But whoever denies me before men, him I will also deny before my Father who is in heaven.

34 “Don’t think that I came to send peace on the earth. I didn’t come to send peace, but a sword. 35 For I came to set a man at odds against his father, and a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law. 36 A man’s foes will be those of his own household.[*] 37 He who loves father or mother more than me is not worthy of me; and he who loves son or daughter more than me isn’t worthy of me. 38 He who doesn’t take his cross and follow after me, isn’t worthy of me. 39 He who seeks his life will lose it; and he who loses his life for my sake will find it. 40 He who receives you receives me, and he who receives me receives him who sent me. 41 He who receives a prophet in the name of a prophet will receive a prophet’s reward. He who receives a righteous man in the name of a righteous man will receive a righteous man’s reward. 42 Whoever gives one of these little ones just a cup of cold water to drink in the name of a disciple, most certainly I tell you he will in no way lose his reward.”

NU omits “Lebbaeus, who was also called”

TR adds “raise the dead,”

Literally, Lord of the Flies, or the devil

or, Hell.

An assarion is a small coin worth one tenth of a drachma or a sixteenth of a denarius. An assarion is approximately the wages of one half hour of agricultural labor.

Micah 7:6

Matthew 11

1 When Jesus had finished directing his twelve disciples, he departed from there to teach and preach in their cities. 2 Now when John heard in the prison the works of Christ, he sent two of his disciples 3 and said to him, “Are you he who comes, or should we look for another?”

4 Jesus answered them, “Go and tell John the things which you hear and see: 5 the blind receive their sight, the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear,[*] the dead are raised up, and the poor have good news preached to them.[*] 6 Blessed is he who finds no occasion for stumbling in me.”

7 As these went their way, Jesus began to say to the multitudes concerning John, “What did you go out into the wilderness to see? A reed shaken by the wind? 8 But what did you go out to see? A man in soft clothing? Behold, those who wear soft clothing are in kings’ houses. 9 But why did you go out? To see a prophet? Yes, I tell you, and much more than a prophet. 10 For this is he, of whom it is written, ‘Behold, I send my messenger before your face, who will prepare your way before you.’[*] 11 Most certainly I tell you, among those who are born of women there has not arisen anyone greater than John the Baptizer; yet he who is least in the Kingdom of Heaven is greater than he. 12 From the days of John the Baptizer until now, the Kingdom of Heaven suffers violence, and the violent take it by force.[*] 13 For all the prophets and the law prophesied until John. 14 If you are willing to receive it, this is Elijah, who is to come. 15 He who has ears to hear, let him hear.

16 “But to what shall I compare this generation? It is like children sitting in the marketplaces, who call to their companions 17 and say, ‘We played the flute for you, and you didn’t dance. We mourned for you, and you didn’t lament.’ 18 For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, ‘He has a demon.’ 19 The Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they say, ‘Behold, a gluttonous man and a drunkard, a friend of tax collectors and sinners!’ But wisdom is justified by her children.”[*]

20 Then he began to denounce the cities in which most of his mighty works had been done, because they didn’t repent. 21 “Woe to you, Chorazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida! For if the mighty works had been done in Tyre and Sidon which were done in you, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes. 22 But I tell you, it will be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon on the day of judgment than for you. 23 You, Capernaum, who are exalted to heaven, you will go down to Hades.[*] For if the mighty works had been done in Sodom which were done in you, it would have remained until today. 24 But I tell you that it will be more tolerable for the land of Sodom, on the day of judgment, than for you.”

25 At that time, Jesus answered, “I thank you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that you hid these things from the wise and understanding, and revealed them to infants. 26 Yes, Father, for so it was well-pleasing in your sight. 27 All things have been delivered to me by my Father. No one knows the Son, except the Father; neither does anyone know the Father, except the Son, and he to whom the Son desires to reveal him.

28 “Come to me, all you who labor and are heavily burdened, and I will give you rest. 29 Take my yoke upon you, and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in heart; and you will find rest for your souls. 30 For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.”

Isaiah 35:5

Isaiah 61:1-4

Malachi 3:1

or, plunder it.

NU reads “actions” instead of “children”

or, Hell

Matthew 12

1 At that time, Jesus went on the Sabbath day through the grain fields. His disciples were hungry and began to pluck heads of grain and to eat. 2 But the Pharisees, when they saw it, said to him, “Behold, your disciples do what is not lawful to do on the Sabbath.”

3 But he said to them, “Haven’t you read what David did, when he was hungry, and those who were with him; 4 how he entered into God’s house, and ate the show bread, which was not lawful for him to eat, neither for those who were with him, but only for the priests?[*] 5 Or have you not read in the law, that on the Sabbath day, the priests in the temple profane the Sabbath, and are guiltless? 6 But I tell you that one greater than the temple is here. 7 But if you had known what this means, ‘I desire mercy, and not sacrifice,’[*] you would not have condemned the guiltless. 8 For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath.”

9 He departed there, and went into their synagogue. 10 And behold there was a man with a withered hand. They asked him, “Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath day?” that they might accuse him.

11 He said to them, “What man is there among you, who has one sheep, and if this one falls into a pit on the Sabbath day, won’t he grab on to it, and lift it out? 12 Of how much more value then is a man than a sheep! Therefore it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath day.” 13 Then he told the man, “Stretch out your hand.” He stretched it out; and it was restored whole, just like the other. 14 But the Pharisees went out, and conspired against him, how they might destroy him. 15 Jesus, perceiving that, withdrew from there. Great multitudes followed him; and he healed them all, 16 and commanded them that they should not make him known: 17 that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying,

18 “Behold, my servant whom I have chosen;

my beloved in whom my soul is well pleased:

I will put my Spirit on him.

He will proclaim justice to the nations.

19 He will not strive, nor shout;

neither will anyone hear his voice in the streets.

20 He won’t break a bruised reed.

He won’t quench a smoking flax,

until he leads justice to victory.

21 In his name, the nations will hope.”[*]

22 Then one possessed by a demon, blind and mute, was brought to him and he healed him, so that the blind and mute man both spoke and saw. 23 All the multitudes were amazed, and said, “Can this be the son of David?” 24 But when the Pharisees heard it, they said, “This man does not cast out demons, except by Beelzebul, the prince of the demons.”

25 Knowing their thoughts, Jesus said to them, “Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation, and every city or house divided against itself will not stand. 26 If Satan casts out Satan, he is divided against himself. How then will his kingdom stand? 27 If I by Beelzebul cast out demons, by whom do your children cast them out? Therefore they will be your judges. 28 But if I by the Spirit of God cast out demons, then God’s Kingdom has come upon you. 29 Or how can one enter into the house of the strong man, and plunder his goods, unless he first bind the strong man? Then he will plunder his house.

30 “He who is not with me is against me, and he who doesn’t gather with me, scatters. 31 Therefore I tell you, every sin and blasphemy will be forgiven men, but the blasphemy against the Spirit will not be forgiven men. 32 Whoever speaks a word against the Son of Man, it will be forgiven him; but whoever speaks against the Holy Spirit, it will not be forgiven him, neither in this age, nor in that which is to come.

33 “Either make the tree good, and its fruit good, or make the tree corrupt, and its fruit corrupt; for the tree is known by its fruit. 34 You offspring of vipers, how can you, being evil, speak good things? For out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth speaks. 35 The good man out of his good treasure brings out good things, and the evil man out of his evil treasure[*] brings out evil things. 36 I tell you that every idle word that men speak, they will give account of it in the day of judgment. 37 For by your words you will be justified, and by your words you will be condemned.”

38 Then certain of the scribes and Pharisees answered, “Teacher, we want to see a sign from you.”

39 But he answered them, “An evil and adulterous generation seeks after a sign, but no sign will be given to it but the sign of Jonah the prophet. 40 For as Jonah was three days and three nights in the belly of the whale, so will the Son of Man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth. 41 The men of Nineveh will stand up in the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it, for they repented at the preaching of Jonah; and behold, someone greater than Jonah is here. 42 The queen of the south will rise up in the judgment with this generation, and will condemn it, for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, someone greater than Solomon is here.

43 When an unclean spirit has gone out of a man, he passes through waterless places, seeking rest, and doesn’t find it. 44 Then he says, ‘I will return into my house from which I came out,’ and when he has come back, he finds it empty, swept, and put in order. 45 Then he goes, and takes with himself seven other spirits more evil than he is, and they enter in and dwell there. The last state of that man becomes worse than the first. Even so will it be also to this evil generation.”

46 While he was yet speaking to the multitudes, behold, his mother and his brothers stood outside, seeking to speak to him. 47 One said to him, “Behold, your mother and your brothers stand outside, seeking to speak to you.”

48 But he answered him who spoke to him, “Who is my mother? Who are my brothers?” 49 He stretched out his hand towards his disciples, and said, “Behold, my mother and my brothers! 50 For whoever does the will of my Father who is in heaven, he is my brother, and sister, and mother.”

1 Samuel 21:3-6

Hosea 6:6

Isaiah 42:1-4

TR adds “of the heart”

Matthew 13

1 On that day Jesus went out of the house, and sat by the seaside. 2 Great multitudes gathered to him, so that he entered into a boat, and sat, and all the multitude stood on the beach. 3 He spoke to them many things in parables, saying, “Behold, a farmer went out to sow. 4 As he sowed, some seeds fell by the roadside, and the birds came and devoured them. 5 Others fell on rocky ground, where they didn’t have much soil, and immediately they sprang up, because they had no depth of earth. 6 When the sun had risen, they were scorched. Because they had no root, they withered away. 7 Others fell among thorns. The thorns grew up and choked them. 8 Others fell on good soil, and yielded fruit: some one hundred times as much, some sixty, and some thirty. 9 He who has ears to hear, let him hear.”

10 The disciples came, and said to him, “Why do you speak to them in parables?”

11 He answered them, “To you it is given to know the mysteries of the Kingdom of Heaven, but it is not given to them. 12 For whoever has, to him will be given, and he will have abundance, but whoever doesn’t have, from him will be taken away even that which he has. 13 Therefore I speak to them in parables, because seeing they don’t see, and hearing, they don’t hear, neither do they understand. 14 In them the prophecy of Isaiah is fulfilled, which says,

‘By hearing you will hear,

and will in no way understand;

Seeing you will see,

and will in no way perceive:

15 for this people’s heart has grown callous,

their ears are dull of hearing,

they have closed their eyes;

or else perhaps they might perceive with their eyes,

hear with their ears,

understand with their heart,

and would turn again;

and I would heal them.’[*]

16 “But blessed are your eyes, for they see; and your ears, for they hear. 17 For most certainly I tell you that many prophets and righteous men desired to see the things which you see, and didn’t see them; and to hear the things which you hear, and didn’t hear them.

18 “Hear, then, the parable of the farmer. 19 When anyone hears the word of the Kingdom, and doesn’t understand it, the evil one comes, and snatches away that which has been sown in his heart. This is what was sown by the roadside. 20 What was sown on the rocky places, this is he who hears the word, and immediately with joy receives it; 21 yet he has no root in himself, but endures for a while. When oppression or persecution arises because of the word, immediately he stumbles. 22 What was sown among the thorns, this is he who hears the word, but the cares of this age and the deceitfulness of riches choke the word, and he becomes unfruitful. 23 What was sown on the good ground, this is he who hears the word, and understands it, who most certainly bears fruit, and produces, some one hundred times as much, some sixty, and some thirty.”

24 He set another parable before them, saying, “The Kingdom of Heaven is like a man who sowed good seed in his field, 25 but while people slept, his enemy came and sowed darnel weeds[*] also among the wheat, and went away. 26 But when the blade sprang up and produced fruit, then the darnel weeds appeared also. 27 The servants of the householder came and said to him, ‘Sir, didn’t you sow good seed in your field? Where did these darnel weeds come from?’

28 “He said to them, ‘An enemy has done this.’

“The servants asked him, ‘Do you want us to go and gather them up?’

29 “But he said, ‘No, lest perhaps while you gather up the darnel weeds, you root up the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the harvest time I will tell the reapers, “First, gather up the darnel weeds, and bind them in bundles to burn them; but gather the wheat into my barn.”’”

31 He set another parable before them, saying, “The Kingdom of Heaven is like a grain of mustard seed, which a man took, and sowed in his field; 32 which indeed is smaller than all seeds. But when it is grown, it is greater than the herbs, and becomes a tree, so that the birds of the air come and lodge in its branches.”

33 He spoke another parable to them. “The Kingdom of Heaven is like yeast, which a woman took, and hid in three measures[*] of meal, until it was all leavened.”

34 Jesus spoke all these things in parables to the multitudes; and without a parable, he didn’t speak to them, 35 that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophet, saying,

“I will open my mouth in parables;

I will utter things hidden from the foundation of the world.”[*]

36 Then Jesus sent the multitudes away, and went into the house. His disciples came to him, saying, “Explain to us the parable of the darnel weeds of the field.”

37 He answered them, “He who sows the good seed is the Son of Man, 38 the field is the world; and the good seed, these are the children of the Kingdom; and the darnel weeds are the children of the evil one. 39 The enemy who sowed them is the devil. The harvest is the end of the age, and the reapers are angels. 40 As therefore the darnel weeds are gathered up and burned with fire; so will it be at the end of this age. 41 The Son of Man will send out his angels, and they will gather out of his Kingdom all things that cause stumbling, and those who do iniquity, 42 and will cast them into the furnace of fire. There will be weeping and the gnashing of teeth. 43 Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the Kingdom of their Father. He who has ears to hear, let him hear.

44 “Again, the Kingdom of Heaven is like a treasure hidden in the field, which a man found, and hid. In his joy, he goes and sells all that he has, and buys that field.

45 “Again, the Kingdom of Heaven is like a man who is a merchant seeking fine pearls, 46 who having found one pearl of great price, he went and sold all that he had, and bought it.

47 “Again, the Kingdom of Heaven is like a dragnet, that was cast into the sea, and gathered some fish of every kind, 48 which, when it was filled, they drew up on the beach. They sat down, and gathered the good into containers, but the bad they threw away. 49 So will it be in the end of the world. The angels will come and separate the wicked from among the righteous, 50 and will cast them into the furnace of fire. There will be the weeping and the gnashing of teeth.” 51 Jesus said to them, “Have you understood all these things?”

They answered him, “Yes, Lord.”

52 He said to them, “Therefore every scribe who has been made a disciple in the Kingdom of Heaven is like a man who is a householder, who brings out of his treasure new and old things.”

53 When Jesus had finished these parables, he departed from there. 54 Coming into his own country, he taught them in their synagogue, so that they were astonished, and said, “Where did this man get this wisdom, and these mighty works? 55 Isn’t this the carpenter’s son? Isn’t his mother called Mary, and his brothers, James, Joses, Simon, and Judas?[*] 56 Aren’t all of his sisters with us? Where then did this man get all of these things?” 57 They were offended by him.

But Jesus said to them, “A prophet is not without honor, except in his own country, and in his own house.” 58 He didn’t do many mighty works there because of their unbelief.

Isaiah 6:9-10

darnel is a weed grass (probably bearded darnel or lolium temulentum) that looks very much like wheat until it is mature, when the difference becomes very apparent.

literally, three sata 3 sata is about 39 liters or a bit more than a bushel

Psalm 78:2

or, Judah

Matthew 14

1 At that time, Herod the tetrarch heard the report concerning Jesus, 2 and said to his servants, “This is John the Baptizer. He is risen from the dead. That is why these powers work in him.” 3 For Herod had laid hold of John, and bound him, and put him in prison for the sake of Herodias, his brother Philip’s wife. 4 For John said to him, “It is not lawful for you to have her.” 5 When he would have put him to death, he feared the multitude, because they counted him as a prophet. 6 But when Herod’s birthday came, the daughter of Herodias danced among them and pleased Herod. 7 Whereupon he promised with an oath to give her whatever she should ask. 8 She, being prompted by her mother, said, “Give me here on a platter the head of John the Baptizer.”

9 The king was grieved, but for the sake of his oaths, and of those who sat at the table with him, he commanded it to be given, 10 and he sent and beheaded John in the prison. 11 His head was brought on a platter, and given to the young lady: and she brought it to her mother. 12 His disciples came, and took the body, and buried it; and they went and told Jesus. 13 Now when Jesus heard this, he withdrew from there in a boat, to a deserted place apart. When the multitudes heard it, they followed him on foot from the cities.

14 Jesus went out, and he saw a great multitude. He had compassion on them, and healed their sick. 15 When evening had come, his disciples came to him, saying, “This place is deserted, and the hour is already late. Send the multitudes away, that they may go into the villages, and buy themselves food.”

16 But Jesus said to them, “They don’t need to go away. You give them something to eat.”

17 They told him, “We only have here five loaves and two fish.”

18 He said, “Bring them here to me.” 19 He commanded the multitudes to sit down on the grass; and he took the five loaves and the two fish, and looking up to heaven, he blessed, broke and gave the loaves to the disciples, and the disciples gave to the multitudes. 20 They all ate, and were filled. They took up twelve baskets full of that which remained left over from the broken pieces. 21 Those who ate were about five thousand men, besides women and children.

22 Immediately Jesus made the disciples get into the boat, and to go ahead of him to the other side, while he sent the multitudes away. 23 After he had sent the multitudes away, he went up into the mountain by himself to pray. When evening had come, he was there alone. 24 But the boat was now in the middle of the sea, distressed by the waves, for the wind was contrary. 25 In the fourth watch of the night,[*] Jesus came to them, walking on the sea.[*] 26 When the disciples saw him walking on the sea, they were troubled, saying, “It’s a ghost!” and they cried out for fear. 27 But immediately Jesus spoke to them, saying, “Cheer up! It is I![*] Don’t be afraid.”

28 Peter answered him and said, “Lord, if it is you, command me to come to you on the waters.”

29 He said, “Come!”

Peter stepped down from the boat, and walked on the waters to come to Jesus. 30 But when he saw that the wind was strong, he was afraid, and beginning to sink, he cried out, saying, “Lord, save me!”

31 Immediately Jesus stretched out his hand, took hold of him, and said to him, “You of little faith, why did you doubt?” 32 When they got up into the boat, the wind ceased. 33 Those who were in the boat came and worshiped him, saying, “You are truly the Son of God!”

34 When they had crossed over, they came to the land of Gennesaret. 35 When the people of that place recognized him, they sent into all that surrounding region, and brought to him all who were sick; 36 and they begged him that they might just touch the fringe[*] of his garment. As many as touched it were made whole.

The night was equally divided into four watches, so the fourth watch is approximately 3:00 a.m. to sunrise.

see Job 9:8

or, I AM!

or, tassel

Matthew 15

1 Then Pharisees and scribes came to Jesus from Jerusalem, saying, 2 “Why do your disciples disobey the tradition of the elders? For they don’t wash their hands when they eat bread.”

3 He answered them, “Why do you also disobey the commandment of God because of your tradition? 4 For God commanded, ‘Honor your father and your mother,’[*] and, ‘He who speaks evil of father or mother, let him be put to death.’[*] 5 But you say, ‘Whoever may tell his father or his mother, “Whatever help you might otherwise have gotten from me is a gift devoted to God,” 6 he shall not honor his father or mother.’ You have made the commandment of God void because of your tradition. 7 You hypocrites! Well did Isaiah prophesy of you, saying,

8 ‘These people draw near to me with their mouth,

and honor me with their lips;

but their heart is far from me.

9 And in vain do they worship me,

teaching as doctrine rules made by men.’”[*]

10 He summoned the multitude, and said to them, “Hear, and understand. 11 That which enters into the mouth doesn’t defile the man; but that which proceeds out of the mouth, this defiles the man.”

12 Then the disciples came, and said to him, “Do you know that the Pharisees were offended, when they heard this saying?”

13 But he answered, “Every plant which my heavenly Father didn’t plant will be uprooted. 14 Leave them alone. They are blind guides of the blind. If the blind guide the blind, both will fall into a pit.”

15 Peter answered him, “Explain the parable to us.”

16 So Jesus said, “Do you also still not understand? 17 Don’t you understand that whatever goes into the mouth passes into the belly, and then out of the body? 18 But the things which proceed out of the mouth come out of the heart, and they defile the man. 19 For out of the heart come evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, sexual sins, thefts, false testimony, and blasphemies. 20 These are the things which defile the man; but to eat with unwashed hands doesn’t defile the man.”

21 Jesus went out from there, and withdrew into the region of Tyre and Sidon. 22 Behold, a Canaanite woman came out from those borders, and cried, saying, “Have mercy on me, Lord, you son of David! My daughter is severely possessed by a demon!”

23 But he answered her not a word.

His disciples came and begged him, saying, “Send her away; for she cries after us.”

24 But he answered, “I wasn’t sent to anyone but the lost sheep of the house of Israel.”

25 But she came and worshiped him, saying, “Lord, help me.”

26 But he answered, “It is not appropriate to take the children’s bread and throw it to the dogs.”

27 But she said, “Yes, Lord, but even the dogs eat the crumbs which fall from their masters’ table.”

28 Then Jesus answered her, “Woman, great is your faith! Be it done to you even as you desire.” And her daughter was healed from that hour.

29 Jesus departed there, and came near to the sea of Galilee; and he went up into the mountain, and sat there. 30 Great multitudes came to him, having with them the lame, blind, mute, maimed, and many others, and they put them down at his feet. He healed them, 31 so that the multitude wondered when they saw the mute speaking, the injured healed, the lame walking, and the blind seeing—and they glorified the God of Israel.

32 Jesus summoned his disciples and said, “I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days and have nothing to eat. I don’t want to send them away fasting, or they might faint on the way.”

33 The disciples said to him, “Where should we get so many loaves in a deserted place as to satisfy so great a multitude?”

34 Jesus said to them, “How many loaves do you have?”

They said, “Seven, and a few small fish.”

35 He commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground; 36 and he took the seven loaves and the fish. He gave thanks and broke them, and gave to the disciples, and the disciples to the multitudes. 37 They all ate, and were filled. They took up seven baskets full of the broken pieces that were left over. 38 Those who ate were four thousand men, besides women and children. 39 Then he sent away the multitudes, got into the boat, and came into the borders of Magdala.

Exodus 20:12; Deuteronomy 5:16

Exodus 21:17; Leviticus 20:9

Isaiah 29:13

Matthew 16

1 The Pharisees and Sadducees came, and testing him, asked him to show them a sign from heaven. 2 But he answered them, “When it is evening, you say, ‘It will be fair weather, for the sky is red.’ 3 In the morning, ‘It will be foul weather today, for the sky is red and threatening.’ Hypocrites! You know how to discern the appearance of the sky, but you can’t discern the signs of the times! 4 An evil and adulterous generation seeks after a sign, and there will be no sign given to it, except the sign of the prophet Jonah.”

He left them, and departed. 5 The disciples came to the other side and had forgotten to take bread. 6 Jesus said to them, “Take heed and beware of the yeast of the Pharisees and Sadducees.”

7 They reasoned among themselves, saying, “We brought no bread.”

8 Jesus, perceiving it, said, “Why do you reason among yourselves, you of little faith, ‘because you have brought no bread?’ 9 Don’t you yet perceive, neither remember the five loaves for the five thousand, and how many baskets you took up? 10 Nor the seven loaves for the four thousand, and how many baskets you took up? 11 How is it that you don’t perceive that I didn’t speak to you concerning bread? But beware of the yeast of the Pharisees and Sadducees.”

12 Then they understood that he didn’t tell them to beware of the yeast of bread, but of the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees. 13 Now when Jesus came into the parts of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, “Who do men say that I, the Son of Man, am?”

14 They said, “Some say John the Baptizer, some, Elijah, and others, Jeremiah, or one of the prophets.”

15 He said to them, “But who do you say that I am?”

16 Simon Peter answered, “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.”

17 Jesus answered him, “Blessed are you, Simon Bar Jonah, for flesh and blood has not revealed this to you, but my Father who is in heaven. 18 I also tell you that you are Peter,[*] and on this rock[*] I will build my assembly, and the gates of Hades[*] will not prevail against it. 19 I will give to you the keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, and whatever you bind on earth will have been bound in heaven; and whatever you release on earth will have been released in heaven.” 20 Then he commanded the disciples that they should tell no one that he was Jesus the Christ. 21 From that time, Jesus began to show his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things from the elders, chief priests, and scribes, and be killed, and the third day be raised up.

22 Peter took him aside, and began to rebuke him, saying, “Far be it from you, Lord! This will never be done to you.”

23 But he turned, and said to Peter, “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, for you are not setting your mind on the things of God, but on the things of men.” 24 Then Jesus said to his disciples, “If anyone desires to come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. 25 For whoever desires to save his life will lose it, and whoever will lose his life for my sake will find it. 26 For what will it profit a man, if he gains the whole world, and forfeits his life? Or what will a man give in exchange for his life? 27 For the Son of Man will come in the glory of his Father with his angels, and then he will render to everyone according to his deeds. 28 Most certainly I tell you, there are some standing here who will in no way taste of death, until they see the Son of Man coming in his Kingdom.”

Peter’s name, Petros in Greek, is the word for a specific rock or stone.

Greek, petra, a rock mass or bedrock.

or, Hell

Matthew 17

1 After six days, Jesus took with him Peter, James, and John his brother, and brought them up into a high mountain by themselves. 2 He was transfigured before them. His face shone like the sun, and his garments became as white as the light. 3 Behold, Moses and Elijah appeared to them talking with him.

4 Peter answered, and said to Jesus, “Lord, it is good for us to be here. If you want, let’s make three tents here: one for you, one for Moses, and one for Elijah.”

5 While he was still speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them. Behold, a voice came out of the cloud, saying, “This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased. Listen to him.”

6 When the disciples heard it, they fell on their faces, and were very afraid. 7 Jesus came and touched them and said, “Get up, and don’t be afraid.” 8 Lifting up their eyes, they saw no one, except Jesus alone. 9 As they were coming down from the mountain, Jesus commanded them, saying, “Don’t tell anyone what you saw, until the Son of Man has risen from the dead.”

10 His disciples asked him, saying, “Then why do the scribes say that Elijah must come first?”

11 Jesus answered them, “Elijah indeed comes first, and will restore all things, 12 but I tell you that Elijah has come already, and they didn’t recognize him, but did to him whatever they wanted to. Even so the Son of Man will also suffer by them.” 13 Then the disciples understood that he spoke to them of John the Baptizer.

14 When they came to the multitude, a man came to him, kneeling down to him, and saying, 15 “Lord, have mercy on my son, for he is epileptic, and suffers grievously; for he often falls into the fire, and often into the water. 16 So I brought him to your disciples, and they could not cure him.”

17 Jesus answered, “Faithless and perverse generation! How long will I be with you? How long will I bear with you? Bring him here to me.” 18 Jesus rebuked him, the demon went out of him, and the boy was cured from that hour.

19 Then the disciples came to Jesus privately, and said, “Why weren’t we able to cast it out?”

20 He said to them, “Because of your unbelief. For most certainly I tell you, if you have faith as a grain of mustard seed, you will tell this mountain, ‘Move from here to there,’ and it will move; and nothing will be impossible for you. 21 But this kind doesn’t go out except by prayer and fasting.”[*]

22 While they were staying in Galilee, Jesus said to them, “The Son of Man is about to be delivered up into the hands of men, 23 and they will kill him, and the third day he will be raised up.”

They were exceedingly sorry. 24 When they had come to Capernaum, those who collected the didrachma coins[*] came to Peter, and said, “Doesn’t your teacher pay the didrachma?” 25 He said, “Yes.”

When he came into the house, Jesus anticipated him, saying, “What do you think, Simon? From whom do the kings of the earth receive toll or tribute? From their children, or from strangers?”

26 Peter said to him, “From strangers.”

Jesus said to him, “Therefore the children are exempt. 27 But, lest we cause them to stumble, go to the sea, cast a hook, and take up the first fish that comes up. When you have opened its mouth, you will find a stater coin.[*] Take that, and give it to them for me and you.”

NU omits verse 21.

A didrachma is a Greek silver coin worth 2 drachmas, about as much as 2 Roman denarii, or about 2 days’ wages. It was commonly used to pay the half-shekel temple tax, because 2 drachmas were worth one half shekel of silver. A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

A stater is a silver coin equivalent to four Attic or two Alexandrian drachmas, or a Jewish shekel: just exactly enough to cover the half-shekel temple tax for two people. A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, usually in the form of a silver coin.

Matthew 18

1 In that hour the disciples came to Jesus, saying, “Who then is greatest in the Kingdom of Heaven?”

2 Jesus called a little child to himself, and set him in the middle of them, 3 and said, “Most certainly I tell you, unless you turn, and become as little children, you will in no way enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. 4 Whoever therefore humbles himself as this little child, the same is the greatest in the Kingdom of Heaven. 5 Whoever receives one such little child in my name receives me, 6 but whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to stumble, it would be better for him that a huge millstone should be hung around his neck, and that he should be sunk in the depths of the sea.

7 “Woe to the world because of occasions of stumbling! For it must be that the occasions come, but woe to that person through whom the occasion comes! 8 If your hand or your foot causes you to stumble, cut it off, and cast it from you. It is better for you to enter into life maimed or crippled, rather than having two hands or two feet to be cast into the eternal fire. 9 If your eye causes you to stumble, pluck it out, and cast it from you. It is better for you to enter into life with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into the Gehenna[*] of fire. 10 See that you don’t despise one of these little ones, for I tell you that in heaven their angels always see the face of my Father who is in heaven. 11 For the Son of Man came to save that which was lost.

12 “What do you think? If a man has one hundred sheep, and one of them goes astray, doesn’t he leave the ninety-nine, go to the mountains, and seek that which has gone astray? 13 If he finds it, most certainly I tell you, he rejoices over it more than over the ninety-nine which have not gone astray. 14 Even so it is not the will of your Father who is in heaven that one of these little ones should perish.

15 “If your brother sins against you, go, show him his fault between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained back your brother. 16 But if he doesn’t listen, take one or two more with you, that at the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may be established.[*] 17 If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the assembly. If he refuses to hear the assembly also, let him be to you as a Gentile or a tax collector. 18 Most certainly I tell you, whatever things you bind on earth will have been bound in heaven, and whatever things you release on earth will have been released in heaven. 19 Again, assuredly I tell you, that if two of you will agree on earth concerning anything that they will ask, it will be done for them by my Father who is in heaven. 20 For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there I am in the middle of them.”

21 Then Peter came and said to him, “Lord, how often shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? Until seven times?”

22 Jesus said to him, “I don’t tell you until seven times, but, until seventy times seven. 23 Therefore the Kingdom of Heaven is like a certain king, who wanted to reconcile accounts with his servants. 24 When he had begun to reconcile, one was brought to him who owed him ten thousand talents.[*] 25 But because he couldn’t pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, with his wife, his children, and all that he had, and payment to be made. 26 The servant therefore fell down and knelt before him, saying, ‘Lord, have patience with me, and I will repay you all!’ 27 The lord of that servant, being moved with compassion, released him, and forgave him the debt.

28 “But that servant went out, and found one of his fellow servants, who owed him one hundred denarii,[*] and he grabbed him, and took him by the throat, saying, ‘Pay me what you owe!’

29 “So his fellow servant fell down at his feet and begged him, saying, ‘Have patience with me, and I will repay you!’ 30 He would not, but went and cast him into prison, until he should pay back that which was due. 31 So when his fellow servants saw what was done, they were exceedingly sorry, and came and told to their lord all that was done. 32 Then his lord called him in, and said to him, ‘You wicked servant! I forgave you all that debt, because you begged me. 33 Shouldn’t you also have had mercy on your fellow servant, even as I had mercy on you?’ 34 His lord was angry, and delivered him to the tormentors, until he should pay all that was due to him. 35 So my heavenly Father will also do to you, if you don’t each forgive your brother from your hearts for his misdeeds.”

or, Hell

Deuteronomy 19:15

Ten thousand talents (about 300 metric tons of silver) represents an extremely large sum of money, equivalent to about 60,000,000 denarii, where one denarius was typical of one day’s wages for agricultural labor.

100 denarii was about one sixtieth of a talent, or about 500 grams (1.1 pounds) of silver.

Matthew 19

1 When Jesus had finished these words, he departed from Galilee, and came into the borders of Judea beyond the Jordan. 2 Great multitudes followed him, and he healed them there. 3 Pharisees came to him, testing him, and saying, “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife for any reason?”

4 He answered, “Haven’t you read that he who made them from the beginning made them male and female,[*] 5 and said, ‘For this cause a man shall leave his father and mother, and shall join to his wife; and the two shall become one flesh?’[*] 6 So that they are no more two, but one flesh. What therefore God has joined together, don’t let man tear apart.”

7 They asked him, “Why then did Moses command us to give her a bill of divorce, and divorce her?”

8 He said to them, “Moses, because of the hardness of your hearts, allowed you to divorce your wives, but from the beginning it has not been so. 9 I tell you that whoever divorces his wife, except for sexual immorality, and marries another, commits adultery; and he who marries her when she is divorced commits adultery.”

10 His disciples said to him, “If this is the case of the man with his wife, it is not expedient to marry.”

11 But he said to them, “Not all men can receive this saying, but those to whom it is given. 12 For there are eunuchs who were born that way from their mother’s womb, and there are eunuchs who were made eunuchs by men; and there are eunuchs who made themselves eunuchs for the Kingdom of Heaven’s sake. He who is able to receive it, let him receive it.”

13 Then little children were brought to him, that he should lay his hands on them and pray; and the disciples rebuked them. 14 But Jesus said, “Allow the little children, and don’t forbid them to come to me; for the Kingdom of Heaven belongs to ones like these.” 15 He laid his hands on them, and departed from there.

16 Behold, one came to him and said, “Good teacher, what good thing shall I do, that I may have eternal life?”

17 He said to him, “Why do you call me good?[*] No one is good but one, that is, God. But if you want to enter into life, keep the commandments.”

18 He said to him, “Which ones?”

Jesus said, “‘You shall not murder.’ ‘You shall not commit adultery.’ ‘You shall not steal.’ ‘You shall not offer false testimony.’ 19 ‘Honor your father and your mother.’[*] And, ‘You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’”[*]

20 The young man said to him, “All these things I have observed from my youth. What do I still lack?”

21 Jesus said to him, “If you want to be perfect, go, sell what you have, and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come, follow me.” 22 But when the young man heard the saying, he went away sad, for he was one who had great possessions. 23 Jesus said to his disciples, “Most certainly I say to you, a rich man will enter into the Kingdom of Heaven with difficulty. 24 Again I tell you, it is easier for a camel to go through a needle’s eye, than for a rich man to enter into God’s Kingdom.”

25 When the disciples heard it, they were exceedingly astonished, saying, “Who then can be saved?”

26 Looking at them, Jesus said, “With men this is impossible, but with God all things are possible.”

27 Then Peter answered, “Behold, we have left everything, and followed you. What then will we have?”

28 Jesus said to them, “Most certainly I tell you that you who have followed me, in the regeneration when the Son of Man will sit on the throne of his glory, you also will sit on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 29 Everyone who has left houses, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my name’s sake, will receive one hundred times, and will inherit eternal life. 30 But many will be last who are first; and first who are last.

Genesis 1:27

Genesis 2:24

So MT and TR. NU reads “Why do you ask me about what is good?”

Exodus 20:12-16; Deuteronomy 5:16-20

Leviticus 19:18

Matthew 20

1 “For the Kingdom of Heaven is like a man who was the master of a household, who went out early in the morning to hire laborers for his vineyard. 2 When he had agreed with the laborers for a denarius[*] a day, he sent them into his vineyard. 3 He went out about the third hour,[*] and saw others standing idle in the marketplace. 4 He said to them, ‘You also go into the vineyard, and whatever is right I will give you.’ So they went their way. 5 Again he went out about the sixth and the ninth hour,[*] and did likewise. 6 About the eleventh hour[*] he went out, and found others standing idle. He said to them, ‘Why do you stand here all day idle?’

7 “They said to him, ‘Because no one has hired us.’

“He said to them, ‘You also go into the vineyard, and you will receive whatever is right.’ 8 When evening had come, the lord of the vineyard said to his manager, ‘Call the laborers and pay them their wages, beginning from the last to the first.’

9 “When those who were hired at about the eleventh hour came, they each received a denarius. 10 When the first came, they supposed that they would receive more; and they likewise each received a denarius. 11 When they received it, they murmured against the master of the household, 12 saying, ‘These last have spent one hour, and you have made them equal to us, who have borne the burden of the day and the scorching heat!’

13 “But he answered one of them, ‘Friend, I am doing you no wrong. Didn’t you agree with me for a denarius? 14 Take that which is yours, and go your way. It is my desire to give to this last just as much as to you. 15 Isn’t it lawful for me to do what I want to with what I own? Or is your eye evil, because I am good?’ 16 So the last will be first, and the first last. For many are called, but few are chosen.”

17 As Jesus was going up to Jerusalem, he took the twelve disciples aside, and on the way he said to them, 18 “Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be delivered to the chief priests and scribes, and they will condemn him to death, 19 and will hand him over to the Gentiles to mock, to scourge, and to crucify; and the third day he will be raised up.”

20 Then the mother of the sons of Zebedee came to him with her sons, kneeling and asking a certain thing of him. 21 He said to her, “What do you want?”

She said to him, “Command that these, my two sons, may sit, one on your right hand, and one on your left hand, in your Kingdom.”

22 But Jesus answered, “You don’t know what you are asking. Are you able to drink the cup that I am about to drink, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with?”

They said to him, “We are able.”

23 He said to them, “You will indeed drink my cup, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with, but to sit on my right hand and on my left hand is not mine to give; but it is for whom it has been prepared by my Father.”

24 When the ten heard it, they were indignant with the two brothers.

25 But Jesus summoned them, and said, “You know that the rulers of the nations lord it over them, and their great ones exercise authority over them. 26 It shall not be so among you, but whoever desires to become great among you shall be[*] your servant. 27 Whoever desires to be first among you shall be your bondservant, 28 even as the Son of Man came not to be served, but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many.”

29 As they went out from Jericho, a great multitude followed him. 30 Behold, two blind men sitting by the road, when they heard that Jesus was passing by, cried out, “Lord, have mercy on us, you son of David!” 31 The multitude rebuked them, telling them that they should be quiet, but they cried out even more, “Lord, have mercy on us, you son of David!”

32 Jesus stood still, and called them, and asked, “What do you want me to do for you?”

33 They told him, “Lord, that our eyes may be opened.”

34 Jesus, being moved with compassion, touched their eyes; and immediately their eyes received their sight, and they followed him.

A denarius is a silver Roman coin worth 1/25th of a Roman aureus. This was a common wage for a day of farm labor.

Time was measured from sunrise to sunset, so the third hour would be about 9:00 a.m..

noon and 3:00 p.m.

5:00 p.m.

TR reads “let him be” instead of “shall be”

Matthew 21

1 When they came near to Jerusalem, and came to Bethsphage,[*] to the Mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples, 2 saying to them, “Go into the village that is opposite you, and immediately you will find a donkey tied, and a colt with her. Untie them, and bring them to me. 3 If anyone says anything to you, you shall say, ‘The Lord needs them,’ and immediately he will send them.”

4 All this was done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken through the prophet, saying,

5 “Tell the daughter of Zion,

behold, your King comes to you,

humble, and riding on a donkey,

on a colt, the foal of a donkey.”[*]

6 The disciples went, and did just as Jesus commanded them, 7 and brought the donkey and the colt, and laid their clothes on them; and he sat on them. 8 A very great multitude spread their clothes on the road. Others cut branches from the trees, and spread them on the road. 9 The multitudes who went in front of him, and those who followed, kept shouting, “Hosanna[*] to the son of David! Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the highest!”[*]

10 When he had come into Jerusalem, all the city was stirred up, saying, “Who is this?” 11 The multitudes said, “This is the prophet, Jesus, from Nazareth of Galilee.”

12 Jesus entered into the temple of God, and drove out all of those who sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the money changers’ tables and the seats of those who sold the doves. 13 He said to them, “It is written, ‘My house shall be called a house of prayer,’[*] but you have made it a den of robbers!”[*]

14 The blind and the lame came to him in the temple, and he healed them. 15 But when the chief priests and the scribes saw the wonderful things that he did, and the children who were crying in the temple and saying, “Hosanna to the son of David!” they were indignant, 16 and said to him, “Do you hear what these are saying?”

Jesus said to them, “Yes. Did you never read, ‘Out of the mouth of babes and nursing babies you have perfected praise?’”[*]

17 He left them, and went out of the city to Bethany, and camped there. 18 Now in the morning, as he returned to the city, he was hungry. 19 Seeing a fig tree by the road, he came to it, and found nothing on it but leaves. He said to it, “Let there be no fruit from you forever!”

Immediately the fig tree withered away. 20 When the disciples saw it, they marveled, saying, “How did the fig tree immediately wither away?”

21 Jesus answered them, “Most certainly I tell you, if you have faith, and don’t doubt, you will not only do what was done to the fig tree, but even if you told this mountain, ‘Be taken up and cast into the sea,’ it would be done. 22 All things, whatever you ask in prayer, believing, you will receive.”

23 When he had come into the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came to him as he was teaching, and said, “By what authority do you do these things? Who gave you this authority?”

24 Jesus answered them, “I also will ask you one question, which if you tell me, I likewise will tell you by what authority I do these things. 25 The baptism of John, where was it from? From heaven or from men?”

They reasoned with themselves, saying, “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will ask us, ‘Why then did you not believe him?’ 26 But if we say, ‘From men,’ we fear the multitude, for all hold John as a prophet.” 27 They answered Jesus, and said, “We don’t know.”

He also said to them, “Neither will I tell you by what authority I do these things. 28 But what do you think? A man had two sons, and he came to the first, and said, ‘Son, go work today in my vineyard.’ 29 He answered, ‘I will not,’ but afterward he changed his mind, and went. 30 He came to the second, and said the same thing. He answered, ‘I go, sir,’ but he didn’t go. 31 Which of the two did the will of his father?”

They said to him, “The first.”

Jesus said to them, “Most certainly I tell you that the tax collectors and the prostitutes are entering into God’s Kingdom before you. 32 For John came to you in the way of righteousness, and you didn’t believe him, but the tax collectors and the prostitutes believed him. When you saw it, you didn’t even repent afterward, that you might believe him.

33 “Hear another parable. There was a man who was a master of a household, who planted a vineyard, set a hedge about it, dug a wine press in it, built a tower, leased it out to farmers, and went into another country. 34 When the season for the fruit came near, he sent his servants to the farmers, to receive his fruit. 35 The farmers took his servants, beat one, killed another, and stoned another. 36 Again, he sent other servants more than the first: and they treated them the same way. 37 But afterward he sent to them his son, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’ 38 But the farmers, when they saw the son, said among themselves, ‘This is the heir. Come, let’s kill him, and seize his inheritance.’ 39 So they took him, and threw him out of the vineyard, and killed him. 40 When therefore the lord of the vineyard comes, what will he do to those farmers?”

41 They told him, “He will miserably destroy those miserable men, and will lease out the vineyard to other farmers, who will give him the fruit in its season.”

42 Jesus said to them, “Did you never read in the Scriptures,

‘The stone which the builders rejected,

the same was made the head of the corner.

This was from the Lord.

It is marvelous in our eyes?’[*]

43 “Therefore I tell you, God’s Kingdom will be taken away from you, and will be given to a nation producing its fruit. 44 He who falls on this stone will be broken to pieces, but on whomever it will fall, it will scatter him as dust.”

45 When the chief priests and the Pharisees heard his parables, they perceived that he spoke about them. 46 When they sought to seize him, they feared the multitudes, because they considered him to be a prophet.

TR & NU read “Bethphage” instead of “Bethsphage”

Zechariah 9:9

“Hosanna” means “save us” or “help us, we pray”.

Psalm 118:26

Isaiah 56:7

Jeremiah 7:11

Psalm 8:2

Psalm 118:22-23

Matthew 22

1 Jesus answered and spoke again in parables to them, saying, 2 “The Kingdom of Heaven is like a certain king, who made a marriage feast for his son, 3 and sent out his servants to call those who were invited to the marriage feast, but they would not come. 4 Again he sent out other servants, saying, ‘Tell those who are invited, “Behold, I have prepared my dinner. My cattle and my fatlings are killed, and all things are ready. Come to the marriage feast!”’ 5 But they made light of it, and went their ways, one to his own farm, another to his merchandise, 6 and the rest grabbed his servants, and treated them shamefully, and killed them. 7 When the king heard that, he was angry, and sent his armies, destroyed those murderers, and burned their city.

8 “Then he said to his servants, ‘The wedding is ready, but those who were invited weren’t worthy. 9 Go therefore to the intersections of the highways, and as many as you may find, invite to the marriage feast.’ 10 Those servants went out into the highways, and gathered together as many as they found, both bad and good. The wedding was filled with guests. 11 But when the king came in to see the guests, he saw there a man who didn’t have on wedding clothing, 12 and he said to him, ‘Friend, how did you come in here not wearing wedding clothing?’ He was speechless. 13 Then the king said to the servants, ‘Bind him hand and foot, take him away, and throw him into the outer darkness; there is where the weeping and grinding of teeth will be.’ 14 For many are called, but few chosen.”

15 Then the Pharisees went and took counsel how they might entrap him in his talk. 16 They sent their disciples to him, along with the Herodians, saying, “Teacher, we know that you are honest, and teach the way of God in truth, no matter whom you teach, for you aren’t partial to anyone. 17 Tell us therefore, what do you think? Is it lawful to pay taxes to Caesar, or not?”

18 But Jesus perceived their wickedness, and said, “Why do you test me, you hypocrites? 19 Show me the tax money.”

They brought to him a denarius.

20 He asked them, “Whose is this image and inscription?”

21 They said to him, “Caesar’s.”

Then he said to them, “Give therefore to Caesar the things that are Caesar’s, and to God the things that are God’s.”

22 When they heard it, they marveled, and left him, and went away.

23 On that day Sadducees (those who say that there is no resurrection) came to him. They asked him, 24 saying, “Teacher, Moses said, ‘If a man dies, having no children, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up offspring[*] for his brother.’ 25 Now there were with us seven brothers. The first married and died, and having no offspring[*] left his wife to his brother. 26 In the same way, the second also, and the third, to the seventh. 27 After them all, the woman died. 28 In the resurrection therefore, whose wife will she be of the seven? For they all had her.”

29 But Jesus answered them, “You are mistaken, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God. 30 For in the resurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are like God’s angels in heaven. 31 But concerning the resurrection of the dead, haven’t you read that which was spoken to you by God, saying, 32 ‘I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob?’[*] God is not the God of the dead, but of the living.”

33 When the multitudes heard it, they were astonished at his teaching. 34 But the Pharisees, when they heard that he had silenced the Sadducees, gathered themselves together. 35 One of them, a lawyer, asked him a question, testing him. 36 “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the law?”

37 Jesus said to him, “‘You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your mind.’[*] 38 This is the first and great commandment. 39 A second likewise is this, ‘You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’[*] 40 The whole law and the prophets depend on these two commandments.”

41 Now while the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them a question, 42 saying, “What do you think of the Christ? Whose son is he?”

They said to him, “Of David.”

43 He said to them, “How then does David in the Spirit call him Lord, saying,

44 ‘The Lord said to my Lord,

sit on my right hand,

until I make your enemies a footstool for your feet?’[*]

45 “If then David calls him Lord, how is he his son?”

46 No one was able to answer him a word, neither did any man dare ask him any more questions from that day forward.

or, seed

or, seed

Exodus 3:6

Deuteronomy 6:5

Leviticus 19:18

Psalm 110:1

Matthew 23

1 Then Jesus spoke to the multitudes and to his disciples, 2 saying, “The scribes and the Pharisees sat on Moses’ seat. 3 All things therefore whatever they tell you to observe, observe and do, but don’t do their works; for they say, and don’t do. 4 For they bind heavy burdens that are grievous to be borne, and lay them on men’s shoulders; but they themselves will not lift a finger to help them. 5 But all their works they do to be seen by men. They make their phylacteries[*] broad, enlarge the fringes[*] of their garments, 6 and love the place of honor at feasts, the best seats in the synagogues, 7 the salutations in the marketplaces, and to be called ‘Rabbi, Rabbi’ by men. 8 But don’t you be called ‘Rabbi,’ for one is your teacher, the Christ, and all of you are brothers. 9 Call no man on the earth your father, for one is your Father, he who is in heaven. 10 Neither be called masters, for one is your master, the Christ. 11 But he who is greatest among you will be your servant. 12 Whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.

13 “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you devour widows’ houses, and as a pretense you make long prayers. Therefore you will receive greater condemnation.

14 “But woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you shut up the Kingdom of Heaven against men; for you don’t enter in yourselves, neither do you allow those who are entering in to enter.[*] 15 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you travel around by sea and land to make one proselyte; and when he becomes one, you make him twice as much of a son of Gehenna[*] as yourselves.

16 “Woe to you, you blind guides, who say, ‘Whoever swears by the temple, it is nothing; but whoever swears by the gold of the temple, he is obligated.’ 17 You blind fools! For which is greater, the gold, or the temple that sanctifies the gold? 18 ‘Whoever swears by the altar, it is nothing; but whoever swears by the gift that is on it, he is obligated?’ 19 You blind fools! For which is greater, the gift, or the altar that sanctifies the gift? 20 He therefore who swears by the altar, swears by it, and by everything on it. 21 He who swears by the temple, swears by it, and by him who was living[*] in it. 22 He who swears by heaven, swears by the throne of God, and by him who sits on it.

23 “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you tithe mint, dill, and cumin,[*] and have left undone the weightier matters of the law: justice, mercy, and faith. But you ought to have done these, and not to have left the other undone. 24 You blind guides, who strain out a gnat, and swallow a camel!

25 “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you clean the outside of the cup and of the platter, but within they are full of extortion and unrighteousness.[*] 26 You blind Pharisee, first clean the inside of the cup and of the platter, that its outside may become clean also.

27 “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you are like whitened tombs, which outwardly appear beautiful, but inwardly are full of dead men’s bones, and of all uncleanness. 28 Even so you also outwardly appear righteous to men, but inwardly you are full of hypocrisy and iniquity.

29 “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you build the tombs of the prophets, and decorate the tombs of the righteous, 30 and say, ‘If we had lived in the days of our fathers, we wouldn’t have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets.’ 31 Therefore you testify to yourselves that you are children of those who killed the prophets. 32 Fill up, then, the measure of your fathers. 33 You serpents, you offspring of vipers, how will you escape the judgment of Gehenna?[*] 34 Therefore behold, I send to you prophets, wise men, and scribes. Some of them you will kill and crucify; and some of them you will scourge in your synagogues, and persecute from city to city; 35 that on you may come all the righteous blood shed on the earth, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zachariah son of Barachiah, whom you killed between the sanctuary and the altar. 36 Most certainly I tell you, all these things will come upon this generation.

37 “Jerusalem, Jerusalem, who kills the prophets, and stones those who are sent to her! How often I would have gathered your children together, even as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, and you would not! 38 Behold, your house is left to you desolate. 39 For I tell you, you will not see me from now on, until you say, ‘Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord!’”[*]

phylacteries (tefillin in Hebrew) are small leather pouches that some Jewish men wear on their forehead and arm in prayer. They are used to carry a small scroll with some Scripture in it. See Deuteronomy 6:8.

or, tassels

Some Greek manuscripts reverse the order of verses 13 and 14, and some omit verse 13, numbering verse 14 as 13. NU omits verse 14.

or, Hell

NU reads “lives”

cumin is an aromatic seed from Cuminum cyminum, resembling caraway in flavor and appearance. It is used as a spice.

TR reads “self-indulgence” instead of “unrighteousness”

or, Hell

Psalm 118:26

Matthew 24

1 Jesus went out from the temple, and was going on his way. His disciples came to him to show him the buildings of the temple. 2 But he answered them, “You see all of these things, don’t you? Most certainly I tell you, there will not be left here one stone on another, that will not be thrown down.”

3 As he sat on the Mount of Olives, the disciples came to him privately, saying, “Tell us, when will these things be? What is the sign of your coming, and of the end of the age?”

4 Jesus answered them, “Be careful that no one leads you astray. 5 For many will come in my name, saying, ‘I am the Christ,’ and will lead many astray. 6 You will hear of wars and rumors of wars. See that you aren’t troubled, for all this must happen, but the end is not yet. 7 For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom; and there will be famines, plagues, and earthquakes in various places. 8 But all these things are the beginning of birth pains. 9 Then they will deliver you up to oppression, and will kill you. You will be hated by all of the nations for my name’s sake. 10 Then many will stumble, and will deliver up one another, and will hate one another. 11 Many false prophets will arise, and will lead many astray. 12 Because iniquity will be multiplied, the love of many will grow cold. 13 But he who endures to the end, the same will be saved. 14 This Good News of the Kingdom will be preached in the whole world for a testimony to all the nations, and then the end will come.

15 “When, therefore, you see the abomination of desolation,[*] which was spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place (let the reader understand), 16 then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains. 17 Let him who is on the housetop not go down to take out the things that are in his house. 18 Let him who is in the field not return back to get his clothes. 19 But woe to those who are with child and to nursing mothers in those days! 20 Pray that your flight will not be in the winter, nor on a Sabbath, 21 for then there will be great oppression, such as has not been from the beginning of the world until now, no, nor ever will be. 22 Unless those days had been shortened, no flesh would have been saved. But for the sake of the chosen ones, those days will be shortened.

23 “Then if any man tells you, ‘Behold, here is the Christ,’ or, ‘There,’ don’t believe it. 24 For there will arise false christs, and false prophets, and they will show great signs and wonders, so as to lead astray, if possible, even the chosen ones.

25 “Behold, I have told you beforehand. 26 If therefore they tell you, ‘Behold, he is in the wilderness,’ don’t go out; ‘Behold, he is in the inner rooms,’ don’t believe it. 27 For as the lightning flashes from the east, and is seen even to the west, so will be the coming of the Son of Man. 28 For wherever the carcass is, there is where the vultures[*] gather together. 29 But immediately after the oppression of those days, the sun will be darkened, the moon will not give its light, the stars will fall from the sky, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken;[*] 30 and then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in the sky. Then all the tribes of the earth will mourn, and they will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of the sky with power and great glory. 31 He will send out his angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they will gather together his chosen ones from the four winds, from one end of the sky to the other.

32 “Now from the fig tree learn this parable. When its branch has now become tender, and produces its leaves, you know that the summer is near. 33 Even so you also, when you see all these things, know that it is near, even at the doors. 34 Most certainly I tell you, this generation[*] will not pass away, until all these things are accomplished. 35 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will not pass away. 36 But no one knows of that day and hour, not even the angels of heaven,[*] but my Father only.

37 “As the days of Noah were, so will be the coming of the Son of Man. 38 For as in those days which were before the flood they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ship, 39 and they didn’t know until the flood came, and took them all away, so will be the coming of the Son of Man. 40 Then two men will be in the field: one will be taken and one will be left; 41 two women grinding at the mill, one will be taken and one will be left. 42 Watch therefore, for you don’t know in what hour your Lord comes. 43 But know this, that if the master of the house had known in what watch of the night the thief was coming, he would have watched, and would not have allowed his house to be broken into. 44 Therefore also be ready, for in an hour that you don’t expect, the Son of Man will come.

45 “Who then is the faithful and wise servant, whom his lord has set over his household, to give them their food in due season? 46 Blessed is that servant whom his lord finds doing so when he comes. 47 Most certainly I tell you that he will set him over all that he has. 48 But if that evil servant should say in his heart, ‘My lord is delaying his coming,’ 49 and begins to beat his fellow servants, and eat and drink with the drunkards, 50 the lord of that servant will come in a day when he doesn’t expect it, and in an hour when he doesn’t know it, 51 and will cut him in pieces, and appoint his portion with the hypocrites. There is where the weeping and grinding of teeth will be.

Daniel 9:27; 11:31; 12:11

or, eagles

Isaiah 13:10; 34:4

The word for “generation” (genea) can also be translated as “race.”

NU adds “nor the son”